Which competitive brand do you think is
most overrated?
>> Adidas.
Huh? Why?
>> They're going too fast. They're doing a
great job in running and I massively
appreciate what team have built. I would
just love that they would with all the
heritage they have in their backpacks
and all the cultural relevances and even
in basketball if they would just go
slightly slower and just not try to
recreate samba waves. look at stuff.
They do an amazing job in so many
places, but they're already always on to
the next. Just newness is the driver to
the business. I don't know their balance
sheet, but I think they could win more
consumer back to brand personality. I
think they could win more consumers
minds if they would just take it take
slower.