150 pitches from YC companies. I backed
13. Here are the three that stood out.
Number one, Toriel. Toriel is on a
mission to end mosquito misery. Not with
chemicals, not with candles,
with something far more satisfying.
Drones. I know that's not what you were
expecting. So, how do these drones work?
Well, each drone is covered in
microphones and ultrasonic parking
sensors that are emitters. [music] And
once they detect mosquitoes wing
frequency, the AI locks on and
intercepts the mosquitoes. Now, if this
all works out, this could be huge. We
get our summers back and we potentially
have an incredibly scalable and
cost-effective solution to fight
malaria. Number two, Clicks. Click isn't
trying to build another SAS front. And
Christ, we've had enough of them.
Instead, [music] they are creating the
first AI back office worker that works
just like a team member. How does it
work? [music] Just tell their AI agents
what tasks you want them to do via email
or Slack and watch them take over. CRM
updates, report generation, and data
entry while [music] adapting to your
existing software. No integrations, no
workflow changes needed. Phenomenally
slick and easy product to integrate.
[music] Third and finally, baby,
Crunched. Crunched is an AI co-pilot for
Microsoft Excel [music] power users. I'm
talking the uber nerd Microsoft Power
users with the red button in the middle
of the Lenovo ThinkPad. So, Crunch
builds models, edits them, [music]
checks them for errors. The difference,
it's built by people who've actually
lived this pain for years. I'm talking
about McKenzie consultants, not tech
bros in Silicon Valley just guessing,
building pretty products. No, this is
for consultants. This is for bankers.
[music] This is for PE investors who
live in spreadsheets, have no soul, and
their time is money. Crunch gives both
of them back to these poor souls. These
are the three that we back from this YC
batch. [music] Go check them out.