If you watch a foreign movie in Polish
language, all the voices, whether it's a
male [music] voice or a female voice,
are narrated with one single character.
So you have like a flat delivery for
everything in a movie. Like if you grow
up, as soon as you learn English, you
like switch out and you don't want to
watch content in this way. And it's
crazy that it still happens until today
in this [music] way for majority of
content. So combining that and I worked
with Palunteer, my co-ounder worked at
Google, we knew that that will change in
the future and that all the information
will be available globally. [music] And
the big thing was like instead of having
it just translated, could you have the
original voice, original emotions,
original inonation carried across? So
like imagine having this podcast but say
people could switch it over to Spanish
and they still hear Sarah, they still
hear Matty and the same voice, the same
delivery. So that was the original
insight and we then started digging
further which is that just so much of
the technology we interact with will
change.