What do you think of AI companions?
>> I think they will be a big thing and
exist in a big way. Like I would love to
start the day and like someone that
understands me and like start and tell
me what's like relevant to me and open
the blinds and then like tell me about
the weather and the sunshine that I'm
excited for. Of course, I think the
companion use cases will mention solving
loneliness and in that part I think
that's one way. Maybe there are like
different ways of engaging people back.
I do think there will be like an
interesting future even if you think
about education where you will have
superpower with learning from AI tutors.
But I think on the flip side of that and
I think this will like that's my
personal take. You all have education
good percent of time spent with AI
tutors but explicit percent [music] of
time spent without any technology human
to human. So you can kind of learn that
part too.