Hi listeners, welcome to No Priors. How
can we even begin to wrap this year up?
The AI field has grown, breaking out
into the mainstream and taking center
stage with policy makers. Chat GPT
shipped massive numbers and asked for
massive [music] dollars. Gemini and
Google roared back strong. And on the
application front, AI coding has shifted
to agents and is eating up all of our
inference capacity. Doctors are adopting
clinical decision support on mass and in
law and customer support. Enterprise
adoption is accelerating. [music] What's
next? On the research front, the race
has multiple live players with open
source closing the gap too. [music] A
handful of Neolabs, new research labs
got funded this year. And the narrative
is changing. Ilia is calling it the age
of research. People are trying different
ideas around diffusion,
self-improvement, data efficiency, EQ,
large scale Asian collaboration,
continual learning, energy transformers.
It's more open than it's ever been.
Finally, we had a lot of attempts to
make AI reach into the real world with
renewed optimism around robotics. Next
year, those companies are going to start
making contact with reality. From a
prediction standpoint, personally, I
think we're going to see somebody make a
lot of money. Hundreds of millions of
dollars trading markets with LLMs next
year. It's inevitable. So, we're in the
second or third inning. Markets are
running a little hot and a little
volatile. It's hot in the hot tub. So,
get into it with me and Alad. Okay.
Alad, it's been a year.
>> I know. How's it going? 2026, baby.
>> Are you feeling the AGI? Are you feeling
AI AI winter in a good way?
>> I think I'm actually just feeling
microplastics. I think I'm now 80%
microplastics and just increasing my
microplastic consumptions. A friend of
mine actually launched a new water brand
that uh has no microplastics by the way.
It's called Loop and they have like
glass bottles and also the cap doesn't
have plastic.
>> Does it come with continual testing?
>> Yeah, that's continual testing for you.
>> They did actually try to take out all
the microplastics and so they uh I guess
bottled water in actual bottles has more
microplastics than plastic bottles
because of the cap.
>> Okay, we'll check back in with you in 27
to see if you feel
>> Yeah. But I'm just completely oified out
of plastic. I'm actually really worried
about microlastics. What about all the
little glass particles? Aren't you
worried about that? People talk about
microlastics, but not microlastics. I'm
much more concerned about that.
>> I don't think those particles end up
embedded for you permanently.
>> Silicon. [laughter]
You're not worried about silicons. When
I go to the beach, I'm like, "Oh no,
microlastics everywhere." I'm actually
very willing to insert silicon in my
body eventually in my [laughter]
>> Wow, that was Yeah, I'm not gonna say
anything. We can keep going.
>> What's What's happening in AI? Al, what
are you where where are we and what are
you most excited about?
>> Yeah, I guess for 26 there's a bunch of
stuff I think will be interesting that's
coming. I think we will um I think
there's probably four or five things.
One is I think people will proclaim yet
again that AI is not doing much and it's
overhyped and like that MIT report that
people are quoting that I thought really
didn't matter and the reality of the
technology ways to take like 10 years to
propagate and people are getting
enormous value out of AI already and
they're going to get way more out of it
in the future. You know, so there's
these undoubtedly next year there'll be
these overstated but bubble claims as
well as um hey I actually isn't working
that well kind of claims and that
happens every technology cycle and we'll
just hear it again next year and
there'll be pundits and discussions and
just a bunch of waste of time on it. So
I think that'll happen. I think another
prediction for 26 is the next set of
verticals will hit massive scale. I
think this year we saw consolidation of
coding into a handful of players, of
medical scribing into a handful of
players, of legal into a handful of
players like Harvey and others. And so I
think we'll see that next set of
consolidated verticals happening. So
that'll be interesting. I can keep
going. I have like a bunch of these. Do
you want to go next? We can alternate. I
just did two. Why don't you do two?
>> Maybe I'll react.
>> Or react.
>> I'll react and then I'll and then I'll
give you two predictions. Um I have to
think of my predictions while I'm
reacting. So I'm glad I have at least
two threads. Yes. I I think that the
overall sentiment on AI in the investing
landscape is a lot of people getting
stressed about the amount of capital
they have at work and then just a level
of uncertainty around uh the adoption
cycle and technical bets that people are
making that they don't have full first
principles confidence on coming to
roost. So, uh I I think like any number
of exogenous factors plus noise about um
the speed of adoption, which by the way
seems like blinding overall and we can
talk about what the constraints are.
>> Yeah. So fast I don't even know what
people are talking about. I I just saw a
report um that talked about it's from
this group called uh off call that
talked about adoption of AI by doctors
and look there is just amazing adoption
of of course you know several different
categories like documentation clinical
decision support with things like a
bridge and open evidence and obviously
the general models but there's like
massive enthusiasm from most of the
physician profession here and I'm like
okay of of all of the domains that were
professional considered more
conservative. The fact that there is
this like you know desire to have things
that make work better seems like
obviously to continue in the other
professions. I I think this is by the
way super underd discussed that the
people who tended to be the slowest
adopters of technology love AI. That's
physicians, that's lawyers, that's
certain accounting types. It's, you
know, it's it's actually kind of
fascinating. It's compliance, you know,
it's all the people who always never
adopt technology are now adopting this
stuff fast. So, I do think that's really
notable and very under discussed.
>> It will keep happening. There are
actually lots of professions where like
being able to reason and interact with
unstructured data is very useful. Like I
expect that there's going to be some
like negative market current. Like you
know if Nvidia doesn't overperform by
some massive amount one quarter,
everybody's going to freak out. But I I
think that has very little to do with
the fundamental secular change.
>> Yeah. It has to do with microplastics
and Nvidia. It's my two cents.
>> It has to it has to do with um
microlastics as you said.
>> Yeah, it's true. Actually, the silicon
there is in the air. I bet that they
have microlastics all over the place.
It's messed up. Sarah,
>> it's part of the trade. If you make $20
million as an average Nvidia employee,
you also have to have microlastics in
your blood.
>> Don't listen to this, Jensen. Jensen's
our next guest. You can't hear that.
>> 1% microlastics in the blood.
>> I think um you know, a third area is the
next set of foundation models are going
to come. And by that I don't mean the
neolabs and the and the nextgen LLMs
which of course will happen but I mean
uh physics materials um science progress
by models math progress and I think
what'll happen is there'll be one or two
usea one or two cases where it works
really well for something they'll invent
some new material or there'll be some
conjecture proved or something
and then it'll fall into this overstated
hype cycle of it's going to change
everything about physical sciences or
whatever and that oneoff will be
overstated And in the long run, the
trend will be understated and will be
incredibly important. So that's what
that's another prediction for next year
is there'll be a couple anecdotal
one-offs in science that will make
people say, "Look, science is solved."
And they'll realize science has been
solved and then later science will be
solved.
>> I have uh Okay, fine. Three three quick
predictions for you. One is there's
going to be like some collapse of
sentiment around a set of robotics
companies next year. Not because it like
actually isn't as a field going to
progress but because you know people are
beginning to project timelines
>> and uh you know not everybody is going
to deliver on those timelines.
>> What's your timeline? I think that we
will see um humanoid and semihumanoid
robots get deployed at small scale in
environments be the consumer or
industrial next year and not everything
will work and that like the because
there's this you know hype cycle around
human rights overall as soon as
something doesn't perfectly work which
it will not people are going to freak
out right and then there's going to be
some bifurcation about people investing
>> yeah I mean we're in year 15 17 whatever
self-driving something around there and
it's really working now but it
seems like robotics should have maybe a
faster curve but a similar curve right
it's going to take some time to figure
all this stuff out and then once it's
figured out it's going to be really
valuable and the big question for me on
robotics you know it's interesting if
you look at self-driving there's like
two dozen three dozen whatever
legitimate self-driving companies really
good teams and good approaches and all
the rest and then arguably the two
biggest winners at least now are Whimo
and Tesla which were two incumbents
right Whimo's Google Tesla is Tesla So I
wonder what will happen to robotics. It
feels to me like Optimus or some form of
like Tesla robot will be one of the
winners most likely, right? High
probability. And then the question is
does Whimo just adopt what it's doing
for cars to robots as well? Because
there's some similar problems there. Is
it some other big industrial company? Is
it startups? Like who are who are the
winners and why? And structurally when
you have a lot of capital needs but also
a lot of hardware and manufacturing
needs that's going to favor incumbents
which is self-driving right um I guess
arguably the other winners in
self-driving are Chinese companies right
Chinese car companies which are banned
from coming into the US market and those
will probably also be winners in
robotics right the most likely global
winners in robotics will be some subset
of China plus Tesla plus something else
right maybe maybe one of the startups
>> I think that's right but that's like I I
think in most industries like
>> you know the incumbents are more likely
to win than the startups if you're just
looking at it like as as a numbers game.
>> I don't know. Yeah, I don't know. I
don't think so. I think um I think
there's startup industries where
startups should win and there's
incumbent industries where incumbents
should win and they have different
characteristics in terms of market
structure, in terms of capital needs, in
terms of certain of expertise and supply
chain, you know. So I do think there are
markets where incumbents should
definitionally do better. They don't
always but they typically do. And then I
think there are markets where startups
will do better.
>> Sure. But I I don't I don't argue that
like some markets are like the modes are
structurally deeper, right?
>> But one way that you might look at
autonomous vehicles is it's one very
complex single use case robot.
>> And it mostly does locomotion. It does
lots of other necessary types of
prediction, defensive drive, whatever
else. But it's it's it's a single use
case robot.
>> Yeah. And we and we forget there's a lot
of good ones like that. Dishwashers are
great single-use robots. Vacuum cleaners
are great. You know, like there's all
these things that we actually have that
are robots in the home that we pretend
aren't, right? We forgot that they're
robots. Elevators are robots.
>> No, seriously. Escalators are robots.
>> I'm going to use the language of like
for a robot [laughter] to be a robot, it
has to be somewhat intelligent, right?
Um and so dishwasher doesn't count as an
appliance. Um a self-driving car does
count as a robot, not just
>> where's the border of intelligence for
you? I I think like it's probably some
level of generalization, right? It can
work in different environments. It can
work on different tasks. It can work on
different objects. Otherwise,
>> self-driving car is okay. Yeah, I don't
know. I didn't have that complex of a
definition. I just had it as like
something that will do
>> certain pre-programmed types of labor
for you. But maybe that's maybe I have a
better definition. Let me look up what
definition of robot is. a machine
capable of carrying out a complex series
of actions automatically,
especially when programmable by a
computer. But you know, all these things
have chips in them now. Your dishwasher
has a chip in it, right? Or the computer
in it.
>> Okay. Yes. But like uh I would argue
that robotics has not been an
interesting area of innovation without
intelligence. And so that's the relevant
set for maybe you and me and many people
that are looking for something that
changes quickly.
>> Yeah, that's cool. I mean, I do think
that um on the on the on the topic of
robots, the biggest trend perhaps or one
of the biggest trends of 2026 100% will
be that self-driving will really begin
to matter and that'll be both in terms
of your own car, it'll be in terms of
Whimo and Tesla caps. It's going to be I
think one of the big things that's
talked about next year. So, I think I
think on the robotics team that's the
big E.
>> I think if you um look at all of the
potential use cases for robots besides
self-driving and say like self-driving
>> I mean the Optimus team actually proves
this like if you take if you take a
model that is powering Tesla
self-driving and you put it in Optimus
it can do locomotion but it can't do
many other things and you still have to
do the hardware right like manipulation.
And so I think that the advantages here
are not as strong as you believe they
are. And like startups, some set of
startups,
>> the scariest competition is the Chinese,
but I I do think that there is
opportunity here.
>> Oh, I totally think there's opportunity
for startups. And don't misinterpret me.
I just think that it's not just the fact
that you have a model or a base model.
You have the expertise to build the
model, but then you also have all the
supply chain. And I think that's really
important because a lot of the same
sensors that you need to use are there.
and you know how you think about
actually procuring and scaling things is
there you know there's there's good
overlap actually in terms of some of the
other skill sets that are needed that
take a long time to build usually at a
startup or that are a little bit painful
to build and people do it it's fine it's
not I mean did it and SpaceX did it and
you know all these companies have done
it it's extra stuff so that makes sense
I I do think I do think some startups
will succeed here I just trying to think
through you know besides the startups
who's going to be big and then also I
think there are one or two like
incumbent slots that will just default
happen unless something very strange
happens and you know one could have
argued that should have happened in
foundation models where Google should
have had a default slot in the end it
did right it got there and I think that
was very predictable that the Google
models will get good I think I even may
have wrote a post about this like two
three years ago that Google will be
relevant right because they just had all
the assets that were needed for them to
be a really important foundation model
company they obviously invented
transformers but they had all the data
they had all the capital they had TPUs
and GPUs had like the best people for
all sorts of things or some of the
people. So, um, it felt inevitable and I
think this feels the same to me. That
doesn't mean it's right. Do you want to
talk about IP as an M&A next year? What
do you think will happen there? I think
that's another big that's theme number
four, five, I guess. You know, three was
different types of models, four was
robots and self-driving, and then five
would be IPOs and M&A. What do you
think? More IPOs, less IPOs, more M&A,
less M&A, different types of M&A?
>> It depends on whether or not the bottom
of falls out of the AI market at some
point, right? But I think regardless,
>> what do you mean by the what do you mean
the bottom falls out? Like what what
what does that translate into?
>> Uh I think people just get skittish
about you you know the cycle here is
like what are people scared of? They are
concerned that demand isn't real. no
demand isn't real um for AI to support
the capex cycle that there is systemic
risk from people passing the ball around
in terms of who is actually responsible
for the capex buildout and these credit
agreements right or um you know pay on
delivery contracts for data centers and
for chips what else are they afraid of
they're afraid of like the
>> microlastics aka like too much
concentration
in Nvidia and a small number of other
players. If you're like a big public
markets investor, you're just like, you
know, you
>> silicon, it's too much silicon.
>> It's too much silicon. You're damned if
you do, you're damned if you don't. I
was talking to a friend of mine who runs
a large tech hedge fund
>> and they're already like a foundation
model investor in like multiple
significant labs that may or may not go
public in the next couple years. Yeah.
And they're like, "Okay, well the
question is, do you buy the IPO?" Their
game theory on it was like, "Actually,
no matter what I think about it, I have
to do it because retail will want it
>> because they like want to be part of the
AI revolution." And then if you're a
hedge fun, you get benchmarked on annual
performance and because of the retail
pop and some set of investors wanting to
buy into it as a pure play where you're
like, "Oh, I can't miss it like I missed
Nvidia." Then you have to buy it. And so
his view was like you buy the IPO
regardless of your fundamental view of
the company. And I was like, "Wow, this
is not the investing job I know how to
do."
>> What do you think happens?
>> I think there'll definitely be a lot
more IPOs next year. Um, I think if one
of the main AI companies goes out, it'll
be probably do extremely well depending
where they price. I mean, they obviously
if they're overly aggressive, it won't,
but in general, I think there's so much
retail appetite to actually participate
in AI besides Nvidia. Um, and then
that'll just get a lot of other people
to go public to just followers on it.
So, I I do expect there'll be a lot of
them. It's just one that even goes out.
Uh, and then also it's a great way to
raise huge amounts of money for some of
these labs potentially. So, um, it'll be
interesting to watch what happens there.
Any other predictions for 26? Yeah, I I
uh I think that I did not believe that
we were going to see that many like
unique consumer experiences
>> besides like chat GPT. I think we are
going to see like a slate of consumer
hardware that mostly fails, but I'm
still openminded to it. And then
definitely actually like it remains to
me see if any of these scales, but I am
seeing magical experiences of like
really different consumer agent software
that I like I actually want and will
use. And I I think people are barely
beginning to
>> well I these companies are in stealth
right now, but I I do think that like
there's going to be a lot more product
people that experiment with this and
model companies that experiment with
this next year. Um and so I'm I'm pretty
optimistic about that. Yeah, I agree
with that 100%. And I think um the big
question is what will end up being a
breakout startup and it'll undoubtedly
be some and then what will be a startup
that will grow really fast and then
it'll get cop copied by the main
lab/google and then it just gets
incorporated into the core product. And
the the interesting thing is unless a
company truly hits escape velocity and
build a network effect or something else
that's really defensible, usually
incumbents can launch two three years
later and catch up. And so if they have
the distribution and they have the core
product and they have but you know to
your point I think it's very exciting
and I've been waiting for this for a
while. I think two years ago, three
years ago, um this guy David Song who
was on my team at the time ran a two
quarter thing at Stanford where we had
different game supply uh from the
engineering programs there and it was
like groups of people building consumer
apps using AI because we said this wave
of AI is so fascinating why didn't
anybody building anything consumer so we
basically just gave people free GPU to
go and try stuff and there was no like
obligation on their side to do anything
with it you you know, in terms of us
getting involved. It was just you go do
cool stuff cuz this is such a good
playground and it was really neat
experiences that were being prototyped
and then I was just shocked that nothing
happened for a couple years in terms of
you know really interesting consumer
products. So I agree with you there's so
much room for that and I always wonder
is it because there's a different
generation of founders who don't want to
work on consumer or who've forgotten how
because you know the big consumer
companies have kind of aged out. Is it
the incumbents are just too scary? Is it
like what why is there so little
innovation actually on the consumer side
of AI? I still don't quite understand
what the issue is.
>> I Okay, let's let's like list the
reasons. I do think that the incumbents
are pretty scary. Um and anybody who was
around for the last generation of
interesting consumer ideas saw actually
the ingestion of those ideas into the
existing platform as you put out.
>> Yeah.
>> So there's that. I also think like the
first instinct that that I've seen from
companies uh from founders working on
like new consumer experiences is
essentially building like better
versions of like last generation
experiences with this generation
technology and it ends up like not being
that interesting. And so I actually
think you have to be like either quite
close to research or pretty creatively
ambitious to build like something very
different that has any chance. And so
[clears throat] I think I think like
there's just not that many people who
have had that experience set or that
creativity and now we're going to see
it.
>> Yeah, I think it's pretty exciting. The
other thing is um I was talking to a
really well-known consumer founder who's
running you know a giant public company
and his view is that perhaps in the
entire world there's a few hundred great
product people for consumer at least in
terms of who are actually working on it.
Obviously there's enormous human
potential and people who aren't working
in consumer products could and you know
but of the people working consumer
products he thinks at most there's a few
hundred people who are exceptional who
could actually come up with and launch
their own product that would be
interesting or good and so you could
also just say say that maybe there's
just a limitation on how many of these
things can exist just given human
potential within the set of people who
are already doing it which I think is
kind of an interesting argument I don't
know if I agree with it but I thought it
was an interesting argument that he made
>> I would limit myself to that number if
it it's also the set people who like
have the context of like what is
possible now.
>> If you've got great consumer product
instinct, but you're like work you're
like grinding away on the like 50th
iteration of an existing product like
>> Yeah. Yeah. You're working on the the
the little sub button in Gmail or
whatever instead of actually going off
and doing this 100%.
>> Yeah.
>> Cool. Anything else we should talk about
or any other big predictions for 26? I
feel like a very big um emergent thing
that happened this year was the
surprising funding of like Neolabs like
three through eight. What do you think
of that? What do you think about
alternative architectures? Like do you
have any point of view on um all of the
effort around like getting reinforcement
learning to be more general continual
learning? Uh some of the research
directions
>> you know I think there's enormous
amounts of really interesting research
being done. So I, you know, there's a
lot of juice to be squeezed out of these
models still in different ways and I
think that's really exciting. Well,
ultimately these things become capital
gains for certain types of approaches or
models because we know scale really
matters which means that eventually you
have to have collapse into a handful of
players because capital will aggregate
to things that are working the most.
They're generating revenue and so then
the question is what are those things?
At what point do things just get kind of
locked in from a usage perspective for
whatever reason? And there's all sorts
of ways you can imagine this being built
over time against some of the models. So
I think it's interesting. I think it's
exciting. I think we'll see how it plays
out.
>> I think to articulate what like the the
arguments could be for, you know, new
research directions is like Ilia, you
know, did this interview [clears throat]
recently where he describes it as the
age of research. And to to paraphrase,
he like basically says that yes, I
believe in scaling of course, but you
know, there's there's some
floor of compute that is not infinite
where we can test ideas at scale. And
then if we have [clears throat] let's
say secret ideas around like how to get
to more rapid or more compute efficient
improvement then it actually isn't just
a straight resource battle which like
the rat race does feel a little bit like
today. Um, I think the other argument
you you could take is actually like
multiple architectures and people have
done some research on this, but multiple
architectures are really relevant at big
domains of of um usefulness. They just
haven't been scaled, right? And like
there's enough capital out there to test
them, be they like diffusion or um SSMs
or whatever. And that's going to happen
this next year. And then I think there's
like a like a resource focus argument,
right? If Ilia is describing that some
set of labs they have an enormous amount
of compute but they have to spend a lot
of that compute on inference today then
how much do you spend on your particular
research direction uh be it
self-improvement or post- training or
emotional intelligence or very large
scale out agent stuff.
>> Yeah, it depends on what you're doing
because the inference is what ends up
then uh raising you money to pay for
everything else because you're
generating revenue. So I think uh sure
that it's effectively your way to
bootstrap into more and more scales. So,
I always thought perhaps incorrectly. I
I actually probably think it's
incorrect, but I always thought that
eventually you end up with evolutionary
systems is really how you build AI
because and maybe I'm overextulating up
a biology where you know effectively
your brain has a series of modules that
have different functions or tasks,
right? You have a visual system that's
um you know highly sort of pre-wired to
deal with vision really effectively. You
have uh different areas of high pier
thought and learning. You have memory.
You have uh mirror neurons that are
involved with empathy, right? Your brain
is actually very um specialized in some
ways. Although obviously there's people
who are born with literally like half a
brain hemisphere and the brain rewires
and sort of covers all the
functionality. But um there's a few
famous cases like that. Uh but you know
fundamentally um you have a lot of stuff
that evolves into very specialized
tasks. It's almost like ae or something,
you know. And the question is the degree
to which you recapitulate that as you're
doing further development of AI. And
when do you start just spawning off a
bunch of instances of something and just
have some utility function evolving
against that you then have some
selection and recombining and all the
other stuff that you kind of do to to
try and make some of that work versus
how much of it is a more analytical
approach or a more experimental and
iterative approach or you know so it's
or in a directed way. And so I think
it's really interesting to ask cuz if
you look again at biology as a as a
potential precedent although maybe a
very bad one. You look at protein design
and for a long time there are these like
super analytically designed proteins and
then they came up with all these systems
of this you know like phase display
and like mutagenic scans and all sorts
of things that give you dramatically
better results than if you just sat and
thought about it. And now of course we
kind of solved it with AI where you have
um all these 3D structural prediction
that are actually very good right that
that was um alpha fold and a few other
things that really were breakthroughs
there. So it feels like in the context
of AI maybe eventually we end up there
as well right where you just involve
these systems and then that may be a
very different type of approach and
training and you know that that that may
be where I think things really have a
interesting break and that's one of the
reasons arguably people are so focused
on code because code is arguably a
bootstrap into moving faster on
development of AGI but I think it's kind
of code plus self-evolution is really
the the potential really interesting
approach to it to to get some really
fast lift off but Maybe not, right?
We'll see.
>> What is um the one prediction you have
for 26 that has nothing to do with AI?
>> Do you think about anything else, Sarah?
[laughter]
>> I do.
>> I'm joking.
>> Really?
>> I mean, the other thing, by the way, one
other prediction that does have to do
with AI is I do think um defense will
accelerate in terms of startups and
defense tech and the shift to autonomous
or not autonomous but to drone based
systems in general. a massive reworking
of how you think about war and defense
and I think that's going to be a shoot
shift that we'll see go even faster this
coming year I think this is accelerating
in part to you know how the Trump
administration has been approaching it
and the secretary of war and everybody
there have been thinking about it but I
think in part just you have enough
density now of startups doing
interesting things so I think that's the
other thing that's like a huge shift
that you know it's a hype cycle right
now and I actually think again it's a
little bit under thought about because
it's it's going to be so big um outside
of AI I mean I think there's obvious
really interesting things happening in
space SpaceX and Starlink and I think
about communications and telefan that's
a big shift. There's really interesting
things in my opinion happening in energy
and mining and you know I I think
there's a lot going on in the world.
>> I agree on defense
with some like concern that you know we
have to wait for budget to actually
shift from contracts to primes to some
of these new companies at scale. But the
demand like the need to be competitive
in a world that's increasingly
autonomydriven
um is like so obvious right and I think
you know hype cycles and booms are good
in that they bring a lot of people to
the table you know capital
>> founders people who want to work in the
industry um and so you can make a lot of
progress in a quick amount of time even
if a lot of companies die
>> and there's there's um more enthusiasm a
very short period of time so I agree
with that. And I also don't think that's
necessarily bad, right? I
>> What's your high prediction?
>> I think that like I'm not the only one,
but I think that the like
[clears throat] GLP1 thing is just
>> despite all of the enthusiasm, like
still underrated for how much impact it
is having, right? And so I think that
the continual adoption of these is like
inexurable. I actually think it creates
a path that is interesting for like
other peptide and hormone therapies.
>> I think the fact that it has been so
effective has like lots of second order
effects both from people way like just
being a lot less overweight like
directly and the willingness to look at
other engineered peptides or like I
think it like everybody understands now
that like
>> delivery matters. there are these really
incredible medicines and I think that
the impact of that is going to like fuel
much more investment in um anything that
looks like that type of opportunity and
so I think that's exciting.
Yeah, I actually think um one thing that
you mentioned is really interesting
where if you look at the sort of
biohacking community, there's a lot of
peptide use now of different you know
different peptides that will do
different things in terms of you know
somebody will have some chronic corporal
cheerle thing and they'll fly to Dubai
to get you know peptides injected or
whatever and usually those are sort of
early indicators of potential larger
scale adoption society
>> and so I think that's a really
interesting trend right now in general
like this whole like um world of
peptides and their uses. and is there a
hymns of peptides like what's the what's
coming there so I think that's super
interesting you know
>> I also think like the biohacking
community as you said it like the set of
people who were really really early off
label GLP-1 adopters um interested in
longevity neurom modulation with
ultrasound um stem cell injection for
example like that has been like a fringe
small community
>> and I think that like I think it's going
to get less French.
>> Uh and a lot of these things
traditionally 10 years ago came out of
the bodybuilding community, right? The
bodybuilding community was like creatine
and all these things that are more
broadly used now, but also other other
things for sleep aids or other, you
know, magnesium and all this stuff.
>> And to round out this year-end episode,
we've asked some of our friends for
their predictions for 2026. I'm so
curious. My prediction for next year is
that uh the reasoning
uh systems are going to translate
directly uh to AIS that are much much
more versatile, much much more robust
and reasoning is going to impact is
going to revolutionize not just not just
language models but reasoning is going
to impact every single industry from
biology to uh self-driving cars to
robotics. And so reasoning, I think, is
is the big huge breakthrough that that
um is going to transform a lot of
different applications and industries.
In 2026, AI will stop being a reactive
tool that waits for us to prompt it.
Instead, it will become very proactive
and get deeply integrated in our work
life. It'll go where we go, hear what we
hear, know what tasks we need to work
on, and in fact, most of the times
complete those for us before we even ask
it to do so. It'll be our coach that
helps us improve our skills. It'll be
our manager who helps us prioritize our
work and manage our time. In short, it's
going to be the best work companion we
could wish for. I think the main AI
prediction that I have for next year is
I think context is just going to be the
most important part of every single
product. And honestly, like one of the
best experiences I've had with it so far
is just memory and chatbt. Like I think
that there are going to be a lot more
features that basically
their goal is to extract the user intent
and make the onus less on the user to
basically give all of the models or the
system or the product more and more
context. So in other words, how do you
put the onus on the product to actually
extract that from the user instead of
the user having to do all of the work to
do this up front?
>> My prediction for 2026 is there will be
a whole new suite of product experiences
that run on much faster inference.
>> My prediction for 2026 is that we'll
finally stop copy pasting stuff into
chat boxes. Instead, I think we're going
to have applications that have better
use of screen sharing and context
management across the sources that
matter the most.
>> One prediction for 2026, there's so much
talk of agents right now and there has
been for a while, but no one has truly
created a mass scale consumer agentic
AI. I think the models are there today
for this to be possible. And in 2026, we
will see the group that figures out the
right interface and system and product
that creates as big a step function and
overall experience as chat did when it
first came out. And I think this area is
not nearly as seated to the labs as
people assume. It really is anyone's
ball game. Hello, Aaron here. First of
all, I get quite awkward around doing
selfie videos. This is my ninth take of
this video. Um so I hope it goes okay
but uh 2026 prediction would be that uh
this is going to be certainly the
continued year number two of uh AI
agents but in particular AI agents in
the enterprise in either deep vertical
or domain specific areas. Um I think
this is going to be the main way that we
actually take all of the progress that
we're seeing in AI models and actually
deliver them into the enterprise. You
have to be able to tie to the workflow
of the organization. You have to be able
to get access to the data that they
have. You have to have the right context
engineering to make the agents actually
work. And then you have to do the change
management that makes the agents
effective. So this is going to be a year
where we start to see this pattern
emerge more and more. Uh which equally
means that we need to ensure that we
have a lot more happening on agent
harnesses. So shout out to Aorvosu and
Dex for that answer. Uh but it's
definitely going to be the year of age
and harness and seeing how do you start
to get you know an order of magnitude
improvement on the model's capabilities
by having all the right scaffolding
around the model. Uh and then finally it
will be the year of uh economically
useful evals. Um so really starting to
figure out how these models end up doing
a lot more knowledge worker tasks in the
economy. Um and that's going to uh we're
going to see a lot more of that in 2026.
We saw some previews of that this year
with Apex and GDP Val uh and a handful
of others. We're going to see way more
of that. So, those are the predictions
and we'll see you uh in 2026.
>> I think 2026 is going to be a very
interesting year for American open
models. Over the last year, the frontier
of open intelligence shifted from
America to China, starting with the
release of Deep Seek at the end of 2024.
and American institutions were slow to
notice this erosion of American
leadership in open intelligence but uh I
think they've noticed in a big way over
the last half year both from the
government level from the enterprise
level and there are some really
interesting uh neolabs starting to come
out with open intelligence as their
directive and there are a few of these
not just reflection and these companies
are starting to produce some very
interesting
small open models and next year I think
we'll see the US regaining leadership at
the open weight frontier at the largest
scale and I'm really excited to see
that. Hey folks, my prediction for 2026
is that I think we will see AI become
much more politicized. I think we'll see
it become a major point of discussion
for the 2026 midterm elections and some
people will come out strongly against
it. Some people will come out. It's
probably supportive of it. And um I'm
not sure which side's going to win out.
>> 2025 has marked an incredible year in AI
drug discovery. In the past year alone,
we've gone from being able to design
simple molecules on the computer to
designing simple antibodies and now most
recently fulllength antibodies with
drug-like properties zero shot on the
computer. If 2025 has been the year of
research in AI drug discovery, 2026 will
be the year of deployment. The models
have finally entered an era where
they're becoming really useful for drug
discovery. Not only do they make things
faster, but they're also allowing us to
go after really challenging targets
which have been traditionally really
difficult to do with traditional
techniques. I'm really excited to see
what comes next because the models show
no signs of slowing down. Okay, my
prediction for 2026 is it will be the
year that YOLO dies. we will begin
transforming ourselves from a you only
live once to don't die. I think right
now we're kind of a suicidal species. We
do very primitive things. We poison
ourselves with what we eat. We design
our lives so that we slowly kill
ourselves. Companies make profits by
making us addicted and miserable. We
destroy the only home we have. And
somehow we celebrate these things as
virtue. I think it's all backwards. And
I think one day we'll look back and
we'll be pretty astonished that we
behaved like this. Um I think the simp
the shift coming is going to be simple
and radical that we say yes to life and
no to death. It's simple but I think it
could be in response to AI's progress.
And we do this defiantly as a form of
unification. Um I think it does require
a lot of courage for us though to say we
recognize how sacred our existence is.
We don't want to throw it away and we
want to defend it with every bit of
courage and strength we have uh because
it is so precious. I think it's going to
be the year we end yolo and the
beginning of don't die.
>> The most striking thing about next year
is that the other forms of knowledge
work going to experience what software
engineers are feeling right now where
they went from typing you know most of
their lines of code at the beginning of
the year to typing barely any of them at
the end of the year. I think of this as
the claude code experience but for all
forms of knowledge work. I also think
that probably continual learning gets
sold in a satisfying way that we see the
first test deployments of home robots
and the software engineering itself goes
utterly wild next year.
>> Hey, I'm Ben Inspector.
>> I'm Ash inspectctor
>> and our prediction is that 2026 is the
year of energy efficient AI.
>> Data center buildouts are primarily
constrained by energy power
availability, great interconnects, high
voltage equipment, things like that.
Which is why XAI's Colossus was
initially powered by on-site gas trends.
The thing is the demand for comput is
continuing to grow. Labs, neolabs like
us and startups like cursor have a
pretty remarkably insatable demand for
both training and compute and this
demand is currently outstripping our
ability to push lots onto the grid. This
means that in 2026 it will be really
important to squeeze every available bit
of tons out of every wallet.
>> That said, in the long term, chips
probably matter more than power because
chips depreciate much more quickly than
the underlying power infrastructure. So
for example with data center power
supplies a titan per kilowatt hour the
chips cost section order amount more
than the power in a 5year depreciation
cycle.
>> So in 2026 we think intelligence per
watch is really important to squeeze as
much intelligence you can out of every
unit of energy but in the long term we
think it's the chips that matter more.
>> Happy holidays.
>> Happy new year.
>> Thanks to the year
>> happy 2026.
>> Happy 2026 listeners. Thank you.
Find us on Twitter [music] at no prior
pod. Subscribe to our YouTube channel if
you want to see our faces. Follow the
show [music] on Apple Podcasts, Spotify,
or wherever you listen. That way, you
get a new episode every week. And sign
up for emails [music] or find
transcripts for every episode at
no-bers.com.