How did you go about learning about
industries you knew nothing about?
>> It's surprising, you know, for example,
let's say that I was working in the
tissue business,
>> right? Paper tissue. Uh, I would
actually go to factories. I'd go to
manufacturing lines. I'd go to R&D
laboratories, talk to everybody that was
willing to give me time because
consultants can't just sit there and
articulate a point of view or provide
direction without really understanding
the details. So my philosophy was zoom
in before you zoom out. M
>> so in everything I've done I always went
deep into whatever the business was the
company was try to understand things
from the ground level then I'd zoom and
say what's missing here why is the
strategic direction in need of a re uh a
tweak or a reset and I'd go back and say
if we did reset it how would it sit in
the front line what changes would we
have to make then go back out so this
constant telephoto lens that I had in my
head is what stood me in goodstead
through my entire life. Zoom in, zoom
out, zoom in, zoom out.
>> How did that help you at PepsiCo when
you were CEO in terms of understanding,
you know, the right side of the decimal
place at at the low level and then also,
you know, 30,000 foot view setting
strategy for a huge company.
>> You know, some people say uh CEO should
be careful not to micromanage. I agree
with you. What I was focused on was
micro understanding because if you don't
understand the business down to where
the rubber meets the road you can make
decisions at the top which are not
implementable or in the implementation
the intent of the strategy gets lost. To
me strategy and implementation have to
go hand in hand. And very often the
reason operating executives rise to
become CEOs is because the belief is
they know how a strategy has to land in
the front line. In my case, I didn't
grow up in the operating businesses. I
grew up in strategy, finance, you know,
corporate operations, not you know P&L.
So my replacement for having not run a
P&L was go and learn each business from
the ground up. So you know whether it
was Steve Rinman who gave me an
opportunity to learn the right side of
the decimal or whether it was the work I
did with the Fredo distribution system
it was always zoom in learn the business
bottom up and have the humility to tell
people to teach you the business people
like it when you tell them hey can you
teach me this business you know I'd go
to the R&D laboratories I'd tell them
teach me how the concentrate is made
teach me how the Fredolay uh you know
chip is produced a lace chip or a
Doritos chip. I'd walk the manufacturing
lines, walk the research labs, talk to
people. I spent an enormous amount of
time doing that.
[Music]