when you were like the CEO of Pepsi, did
that change how you developed people
where the best thing for Pepsi might
have been for them to stay, but the best
thing for them might have been for them
to leave?
>> Well, at some point when people come to
you and say, "I've got this great
opportunity." You sit there going, would
they be better off leaving? And in case
I want them back, I can always go back
and get them. Or are they better off
staying at PepsiCo? Sometimes selfishly
I'd look at this and say I'm actually
better off if this person go goes and
gets this completely different
experience because I can bring them
back. So you always look at this in a
nice selfish way. I don't mean in a
negative selfish way. In a nice selfish
way. Somebody went to a tech company. Go
there. I'm sure the allure of PepsiCo
will make you want to come back if I
wanted you back. and now I have somebody
who's got the PepsiCo pedigree, has got
a tech background and now can come back
and contribute to the company in
profound ways or partner with me. So I'd
look at it that way. But if I felt that
a person did not have much runway in
PepsiCo, I would also tell them very
honestly that they might be viewed as a
critical professional in PepsiCo. You
know, they could have a career but not a
fantastic career. And if they got a
better opportunity somewhere, I would
provide the reference and I would help
them find something. I think if you
really care about people develop and
you've got to think that way.