So it was always this thing about push
yourself, don't sit idle. Satan has work
for idle hands. If you can read in every
spare minute, do it. So that's the
environment we grew up in. And we
couldn't go complain to somebody else
because our entire community was that
way. And so you sit there going, who am
I going to complain to? If I complain to
an aunt or an uncle, they'll say, oh,
I'm doing the same with my kids. So we
grew up in an environment where
everybody was being pushed. And we were
being pushed because we were growing up
in an environment where India had just
come out of 350 years of British rule
and it was trying to find its place in
society and we were looking at other
countries and saying wow you know there
could be growth there can be innovation
the economy could get a whole lot better
and so everybody needs to pull
themselves up to contribute to the
country in order to make the country
better. So that was the goal to push
young people. And so you sit there
going, I have to pull myself up. The
family pushed you, but you have to pull
yourself up. Everything in my childhood
was about that. It was about working
hard, being a team member at home, doing
chores, uh not having much money at all,
but lots of discipline, uh freedom
within a frame. That's what I remember.
Uh but work hard, study hard, and be
viewed as a reliable person. If you
promise something, deliver it. Okay?
Unless you're dead, you will deliver it.