Peter Teal said this best. He's like,
"Look at all the money that's going into
AI. There's really only one company
that's making any money, and that's
Nvidia." Like, at this point, the jury's
still out. We don't even know what AI
is. It's sort of like when the internet
was happening, everyone thought these
fiber optic switch companies were going
to make all the money. Turns out that
was wrong. It was the end applications
that made all the money. And they
competed in many different markets from
Google to Amazon to Uber. You can go
down the list of all the beneficiaries
of the core infrastructure technology of
the internet that was built out. So,
what is really going on? Well, AI is the
new lightning rod for fear and for
divisiveness that ultimately breeds
compliance and control, which is where
these politicians are trying to drive
the populace and the voting conditions
in the United States. And that's what's
going on right now. There's a lot of
fear about putting this data center in
my town is going to do X or Y or Z with
no real conversation about the truth of
that matter. There's a lot of fear about
wealth creation being aggregated in the
hand of a few when, as we saw with the
internet, it benefited the many. And
that fear mongering is a very similar
tactic that we've seen in the prior
generations where policies were
misstated, fear was used, and then
voting control allowed folks to come to
power that were looking for power. So, I
think it's just the lightning rod at the
moment.