All right, everybody. Welcome back to
your favorite podcast, the number one
podcast. In fact, in the entire
universe, the Allin podcast with your
besties. We're all here. It's the
original quartet. Everybody loves When
the Core Four are here. And we have a
docket for you today, guys. We got to
start out with Bernie Sanders. I know
this is becoming a bit repetitive, but
AI is the topic.
We reached a new level of retardation
this week that we cannot avoid. Bernie
Sanders has a major del pitch, a
moratorum on new AI data centers.
Here's his argument. Number one, the
billionaires are pushing AI because they
want more money and power. Number two,
there's going to be massive
unemployment. And he cites Skates,
Staro, Elon, saying that a AI would
replace most jobs. Number three, he uh
has an interesting point actually. AI is
harmful to kids because it decreases
social interaction. Actually, we kind of
agree with that one, I think, across the
board. But here's his pitch, Sachs. His
pitch
>> you want your using these chat box.
>> No, I've talked to my kids about it.
>> Okay, we'll get into it.
>> We can get into it, but I've talked to
them about it. Look, if you actually
look at the data, if you look at what
kids are doing, it's so much more
interactive and engaging for them to
talk to their friends on Snap or to
watch videos on Tik Tok. Those things
are super engaging. Whereas doing
research on an AI chatbot is just it's
way less engaging and you see this in
the data. So, I'm not saying there's not
an issue there. You want to pay
attention to the way that these
technologies are shaping the minds of
young kids, but I think people get a
little bit confused. what they're really
talking about is social media and then
they attribute all the ills of social
media over to these new AI chat apps and
they are a little different. You know,
when I when I asked my kids like
>> how much do you use these things? Are
they addictive? They said no, they're
more just really useful. It's like
Google.
>> It's like there's two
>> I couldn't do school without it.
>> Yeah, there's two pieces here. One,
using AI to be smarter and to learn
stuff and ask questions. Absolutely
fantastic. phenomenal. I think we'll all
agree on that. There is, and I don't
know if this is actually what he was
referencing, but there's character AI in
a in a long tale of spicy chats where
people we talked about getting
oneshotted and these parasocial
relationships. That's I think what he's
referring to, but maybe I'm reading it
wrong,
>> but let's get into it here. His pitch is
that we need to slow down so that quote
democracy can catch up and that Congress
should put a moratorum on new data
centers. That's his solution. He got
roasted obviously on social media for
this. It's the most absurd I think
solution to you know what are valid
concerns. friend of the podro kind of
who represents Silicon Valley. He
I guess supported it a bit and then he
replied to me and says his concerns are
not as acute and that he just wants to
make sure we use renewable energy which
I guess is you know a fine position to
have poly market put up a little uh
market here AI data center moratorium
passed before 2027.
Yeah, we'll see if that comes true or
not. But uh hey Saxs, you are our SGE.
Sachs or SGE, this is your time to
shine.
You have framed the AI debate as we
can't lose to China. Bernie framed it as
not letting the billionaire class get
more power and money by eliminating
American jobs. And last week on this
very program, Tucker framed it as what
are Americans going to get out of this?
Right? That that was the framing, you
know, as of December of 2025. So here's
your chance, Sax. Why should Americans
who have some concerns about losing
their jobs care about beating China? Why
should they care about that sex?
>> Why should they care about beating
China? Because AI is a profound
technology. It's going to have huge
economic and national security
implications. And the thing that Bernie
gets wrong is that he can't stop the
progress. I mean, he can't stop China
from making progress. We can stop
progress in the US, but it's not going
to stop China from advancing these
technologies. A lot of this is just
math. And just because we stopped
doesn't mean China's going to stop. So,
this would be the biggest own goal ever
if we took our leadership in the AI race
and just handed it to China. But look, I
appreciate Bernie's honesty in a way
because he is actually telling the truth
about what he wants. And I remember just
a week ago when President Trump signed
an executive order to advance a national
AI framework, a lot of critics and a lot
of Democrats were saying this was a
violation of states rights and we need
to support the states and regulating AI.
And here Bernie is acknowledging that
this is not about states rights because
he's saying that there needs to be a
moratorium on new data centers even if
the states want them. So he doesn't
support states rights either. He just
wants all the progress to stop. And I
think this is really the truth of the
matter is that all this talk about
states rights or affordability, it's all
a red hearing. And what's really going
on is there's a large and growing
contingent of people who just want all
the progress to stop. But again, we
can't stop China from making progress.
So all they would be doing is seeding
leadership of this AI race to China.
What people like Bernie really want is
they want the US to become like Europe.
You know, Europe has half the share of
global GDP that they had 30 years ago.
And that's because of their hostility
towards innovation and technological
progress. And that's kind of where
Bernie wants us to be is he wants us to
go down the the path of Europe. And the
reason he says is because, god forbid
someone gets rich. Well, look,
capitalism sometimes results in the
unequal distribution of wealth, but
socialism always results in the equal
distribution of poverty and misery. And
if the US stops developing AI, if we
hand this leadership to other countries,
it'll make the United States poor, it'll
make the American people poor, and it
will seed our leadership globally. We
will not be the pre-minent power in the
world anymore.
>> Okay.
>> So, I'll stop there.
>> No, no, it's great. Thank you. SGE David
Saxsberg,
there seems to be a couple of
conversations. Unfortunately, we weren't
here last week, but we had a really nice
uh visit from our pal Tucker, and we
talked about this. He seemed to think
there was a bit of a communication
problem with selling to the public the
value of these technologies. Do you
agree with that? And what do you think's
going on here in terms of the cross
conversations? One group wants to del,
has some concerns, environmental,
you know, job displacement, etc.
And then there is there an issue where
the China beating China doesn't resonate
with the American populace? You've been
harping on about the rise of socialism
for four plus years on this very
podcast. So from where you sit, what's
the actual disconnect in these multiple
conversations that are going on
concurrently and and seemingly coming to
a head here at the end of 2025? Well, if
you ask any of the politicians that are
making these proclamations about the
quote tech barons and try and actually
talk to them about what is the AI
technology delivering, what is it not
delivering, you kind of typically hit a
wall pretty quickly. It's very hard for
folks to articulate what is actually
happening. There's a tremendous amount
of capital being put at risk against
infrastructure to build out the capacity
for many companies, the entire economy,
the entire industry to deliver AI tools.
There isn't an aggregation
at this stage of value creation with the
exception of Nvidia which has really got
this $3 trillion market cap creation
that's happened in the last couple
years. Peter Teal said this best. He's
like look at all the money that's going
into AI. There's really only one company
that's making any money and that's
Nvidia. Like at this point the juryy's
still out. We don't even know what AI
is. It's sort of like when the internet
was happening. You know, everyone
thought these fiber optic switch
companies were going to make all the
money. Turns out that was wrong. It was
the end applications that made all the
money and they competed in many
different markets from Google to Amazon
to Uber. You can go down the list of all
the beneficiaries of the core
infrastructure technology of the
internet that was built out. So what is
really going on? Well, AI is the new
lightning rod for fear and for
divisiveness that ultimately breeds
compliance and control, which is where
these politicians are trying to drive
the the populace and the voting
conditions in the United States. And
that's what's going on right now.
There's a lot of fear about, oh, putting
this data center in my town is going to
do X or Y or Z with no real conversation
about the truth of that matter. There's
a lot of fear about wealth creation
being aggregated in the hand of a few
when, as we saw with the internet, it
benefited the many. And that fear
mongering is a very similar tactic that
we've seen in the prior generations
where policies were misstated, fear was
used, and then voting control allowed
folks to come to power that were looking
for power. So I think it's just the
lightning rod at the moment.
>> Okay, Jim, what's your take on this big
picture? What's going on here?
>> I think it's important to understand
that politicians have an incredible
sense of self-preservation.
So the question is why would Bernie
Sanders think he would not look totally
foolish in putting that video out? And
the reason it went viral is not because
it sounded so crazy. It was that to some
faction and percentage of people it
sounded rational and reasonable.
And the problem that highlights is that
we have a huge perception issue in AI.
We have a handful of companies.
All the PR that you see from those
handful of companies is a bunch of
circular deal making. It's a bunch of
capital that flows from one to the
other. It causes these stocks to go up
of which a small percentage of people
benefit. And at the tail end of it, it's
accompanied by a completely different
set of articles that everybody also
reads
about the sort of damocles that's about
to fall on their head. whether it's
electricity prices or whether it's their
jobs or whether it's the jobs of their
children or the quality of their
education. So we have a big perception
problem. So the question at hand is how
do we fix it? How do we get back to the
place where a video talking about
stopping all progress would seem as
laughable as it should be? And I think
you can go back to the guilded age and
you can ask the question, how did the
industrialist leaders of that era
respond through that 1880 to 1920 age of
industrialization when you had all of
this technological upheaval accompanied
by a handful of people with incredible
success, right? Andrew Carnegie, John D.
Rockefeller, Henry Ford. What did they
do? And I think the lesson we can borrow
from them is we now need to be on the
forward foot as an industry. Enough of
the stupid haircuts, dumb watches, ugly
clothes, ostentatious displays of
wealth. We've all done it. I've been
guilty of it. It has to stop. Absolutely
stop. And instead, we need to start to
use a percentage of the balance sheets
of these companies in order to benefit
as many Americans as possible. That is
the absolute minimum. Andrew Carnegie
built 2500 libraries.
The idea was as he built the railroads,
you're going to scale GDP. You're going
to scale education and knowledge. Those
libraries are artifacts that allowed
people to feel a dividend from that
industrial revolution. John D.
Rockefeller took all of his wealth and
invested in institutions and
universities. Henry Ford specifically
focused on wages. We need to
self-organize better and we need to be
more on the forward foot. We need to
start doing things that are practically
measurable by tens of millions of
American citizens. And it starts to beat
back the perception problem that we have
because Sax pointed out last week, the
data does not support the misperception.
But the problem is, and Sax and I were
talking about this last week, the
misperception is gaining steam. And so I
think we need to use these tools that we
have to provide some more practical
benefits that every man, woman, and
child can feel. Otherwise, this thing is
going to build and you'll see crazier
and crazier versions of this Bernie
Sanders video.
>> All right. I think it's well said and
you know, as I said last week, I think
beating China does not matter to the
average American. It's below their line,
Jimoth. Uh I think in many ways what
they care about is jobs. They care about
their kids getting jobs and yeah, they
care about costs. They care about
inflation. They care about energy costs
going up. Our industry has done a
terrible job of explaining how this
benefits the average American. And
they're seeing all these headlines
about, as you mentioned, all the cross
deal booking and all these stocks going
up. Half the country doesn't own stocks,
so they're not participating in it. And
they're not blind to seeing self-driving
cars or seeing their kids having a hard
time getting a job. and they're hearing
everybody talk about job displacement
and that's a valid concern. People are
scared and our industry is scaring them
I think by not meeting them where they
are and then beating China respectfully
is important sachs super important. I
can intellectually agree with you on
that.
>> But if you lose your job and your kids
can't get a job that's that's
existential. Yes. It's not
>> my child needs a job next year. They're
graduating from school with $100,000 in
debt and my energy bills going up and my
grocery bills are going up and they
haven't come down. That's what Americans
are experiencing. And yeah, maybe giving
uh I think you also made an interesting
point there too about the libraries.
>> The war with China is existential
because if we can keep it on the
battlefield of AI and intellectual and
economic prowess, we have a very good
chance of winning. If it devolves and
all of a sudden becomes a different kind
of battle, that's bad for everybody,
especially our children and our
children's children. So, we need to win
the current game on the field. But in
order to do that, we need to change
these misperceptions. We need to start
showing tactical artifacts that show
that this is a dividend that can benefit
everybody. And we need to start now. I'm
just putting it out there. We have so
much cash on the balance sheets of these
companies. Wall Street values it at
zero. If you look at the enterprise
value of any of these companies and you
do a sum of the parts, nobody cares
about that cash. So, we need to start
using that cash more effectively.
>> What's the equivalent of the library
metaphor here for you, Jamath? Do you
have any ideas?
>> I'm not going to frontr run
what's being worked on except to say
that the leaders of these companies have
gotten the message. They are working on
a whole host of solutions. And again,
we're fighting misperception, which is a
complicated battle, but it's winnable
and I think you're going to start to see
stuff in the new year.
>> Yeah, I would say education is at the
top of that list. Saxs, your thoughts
here as we wrap on this first topic.
>> I'm not sure whether to address the
particular hoaxes or the fact that there
are there's a larger effort here to try
and discredit AI and get AI development
to stop entirely.
Let's talk about some of these
particular hoaxes. So on the job loss
claim, I feel like I do this every week
now, but there's a new study from
Vanguard where they analyze job growth
and wage growth in occupations that are
highly exposed to AI automation versus
all occupations.
And they find that both job growth and
wage growth is higher, not lower, in the
occupations that are exposed to AI. So
if you look at job growth in occupations
exposed to AI, it's 1.7% compared to
0.8% for other. For wage growth, it's
3.8% versus 0.7% for other. So what you
see here is something maybe it's
counterintuitive, but it makes sense to
me, which is as you make workers more
productive, the value of their labor
increases, not decreases, and they end
up getting paid more, and you want to
hire more of them. So this is a huge
narrative violation. And again, this is
coming from Vanguard and it's showing
that AI productivity is good for
workers. This follows on the heels of
that study from Yale Budget Lab, which I
talked about in a previous show that it
said there's no discernable disruption
to the job market based on 33 months of
data after the launch of chat GPT. Now,
I understand that you can make
predictions as to the future that this
state's going to change, that there will
be AI job loss, but what I'm saying is
that if you look at the data so far,
there is no AI job loss. Quite the
opposite. It's job growth and job gains.
By the way, we have a 2% tailwind to GDP
growth right now. That's coming from
this AI boom, this capex boom that's
happening. And so, this is, I think, a
very good thing for the US economy. Now,
why do people want to sabotage it?
There's a really interesting article in
Semaphore recently that described how AI
critics were funding journalism
fellowships at major publications like
NBC News, Bloomberg, Time, The Verge, LA
Times, which by the way, I mean, I track
these things. They're relentlessly
negative about AI.
These fellowships were funded by future
of life institute
which is a doomer group that thinks that
AI is going to become sensient and
replace humans and they were funded by
a donation by Vitalic Buterine from
Ethereum. It's an interesting story
actually. He donated his dog coins to
future of life. They ended up being
worth $600 million.
>> Dogecoins.
>> Doge. And then you remember how there
was like those other dog coins.
>> She Oh, he had a collection of dog
coins. Got it.
>> He had a collection of dog coins.
Apparently people like air dropped them
to him as like a promotional thing.
>> Got it.
>> I don't think he wanted them. So he's
like, "How do I get rid of them?" So he
donates them to Future of Life and they
end up being worth $600 million. So by
this
>> Oh my god. almost like this accident.
This Doomer think tank ends up with a
$600 million war chest and they've been
funding these journalism fellowships.
They've been funding grants for
academics to study AI. Obviously, that's
going to end up being very negative. And
they are funding a lot of these nimi
organizations that are opposing data
centers because their goal is just to
get it to stop. That's their goal. They
just want the development to stop. And
you can't, I don't think, underestimate
how much of an impact this has had on
the public discourse. But if you look at
their actual claims, like for example,
the water use claims, it's a total hoax.
I mean, these AI data do not use a lot
of
>> Yeah, that was one of the things I
wanted to get into because yeah,
compared to a golf course, they're not
using that much or or walnuts and, you
know, almonds in central California. So,
I think it is worth maybe just
>> throwing a lot of spaghetti at the wall.
Look, you have to remember who was who
was Ida Tarbel because it's quite
interesting in the context of this. Ida
Tarbell was this American writer again
in the Gilded Age. She was part of the
Muckwreckers which was a group of
journalists that were doing
investigative research around the abuses
of the industrial revolution, labor
abuses and the like. And she took on
sandal. Exactly. If you look at that
example, I'm sure that the people in
this current generation who have a
Tarbell fellowship, what they're living
out is this desire to tell a story about
exploitation and wrong and misdoing. The
problem is that these things don't
factually hold together, but
unfortunately it adds to the perception
problem that we have and that has been
growing. As Sax said, like so many of
these things have been debunked, but
it's playing whack-a-ole, Jason, because
they'll throw the water thing out. It'll
get debunked next week. We'll probably
something about liquid cooling and all
the PAS and forever chemicals. We'll
have to debunk that. Then we'll go to
like air cooling and how that's a
problem. Then we'll go to something
else. Eventually, it'll be the upper
land grouse, but they're not going to
stop.
>> Sax, how do you do you have a plan to
reframe this to the American public?
You're explaining how these bad things
are happening and all the evil forces at
work behind the scenes.
>> Well, look, it's not evil forces, but I
don't think people understand the extent
to which the discourse has been impacted
by a few anti- AI tech billionaire.
>> I brought it up every week and on your
text.
>> I brought it up. Hold on. I brought it
up on this show and I tweeted about it
way back in November. Yeah.
>> And I linked to a writer named Nerret
Weisslat who has analyzed this whole
doomer industrial complex and she has
shown that there are hundreds of these
front organizations and they're all
really just funded by a few big tech
billionaires. It's Dustin Moskovitz, Yan
Talin and Vitalic Buterine. Well, when I
first described this, people thought
that this sounds kind of crazy like a
conspiracy theory. And then sure enough,
Semaphore comes out with the article
explaining that all these journalism
jobs are being funded by future of life,
which was the big donation by Vitalic
Buterine. So my point is just you can't
underestimate the extent to which a few
billionaires who've donated over a
billion dollars to this cause have
distorted the public debate. And you
really see this actually in the relative
popularity of AI in the United States
versus China. So there's recently a poll
on they call it AI optimism where they
ask people do you believe that the
benefits of AI will outweigh the harms.
83% of people in China believe the
benefits will outweigh the harms or AI
optimistic. In the US it's only 39%.
>> So again the discourse has really been
affected by a few of these
>> institutions. Let's say let's say that's
all true.
>> Yeah. My question to you is, what's your
plan to turn this around and explain to
the American people why they should be
optimistic about this? What's your plan,
David?
>> Well, look, I mean, you're right that we
have to flip the narrative around. And I
I do think that the tech companies have
done a really bad job explaining the
benefits. We talked about this with
Tucker. I think he brought up some
really good points. And you're right,
like the the AI companies lean way too
much into the whole job loss narrative
as as a way to explain their value prop.
And I think it's just either what Jamath
has said, which is this is about their
next fundraising round, or it's a form
of laziness because it's easier to
describe job loss or job replacement
than it is productivity, right? Like
multiffactor productivity is a difficult
concept to explain. So I do think that
they've played into this narrative. But
I think that what we have to do here is
just debunk these narratives. Again, no
evidence of job loss yet. No evidence of
the the water problems. I think the
electricity issues with data centers are
addressable. You have to let the AI
companies build their own power. They
don't have to connect to the grid. In
fact, that's what President Trump has
called for for the last 6 months is to
let the AI companies build their own
power so they're not drawing on the
grid. So, that problem is easily
addressed as well. Talking about the
affordability problem, but you're right,
we have to get the message out how this
technology will benefit Americans. And
the bottom line is, look, I've always
said I'm a technorealist, not a techno
accelerationist. Because at the end of
the day we don't have a choice. I mean
yeah China is gonna develop the
technology if we don't.
>> Okay.
>> So we don't really have a choice.
>> I you know as I said last week I think
the three most pressing issues chimat
education housing and healthcare. And
our industry is in a unique position to
use AI to impact all three of those. So
why don't we as an industry collectively
explain all the great things going on
there. I gave a shout out to Daniel,
Prenovo, Pernovo rather, all these great
companies analyzing our blood. There's
so much going on in healthcare that
could massively lower the cost, make
people's lives better.
>> Obviously, in construction, you could
have incredible advances, and certainly
in education, but we haven't explained
those three things. What's your point?
Is there anything you can think of to
add to that list?
>> We have to understand the president and
Sachs, they're responsible for
shephering the GDP of America. And as
Sax said, half of American GDP over the
next few years is forecasted to come
from all of the capital that goes in to
build out our capabilities in AI. We
need this to happen. There's the
existential reason why, but there's also
a basic economic reason why. So Jason,
the social license comes when off to the
side, the private companies
start to take this perception problem
more seriously. So to your point, are
there things that they can do around
housing? Yes. And again, not to frontr
run, they're actively working on
something that I think could be
transformational separately. Could they
do something on healthcare? TBD, but we
should look at it. Can you do something
in education? TBD, but we should look at
it. But the point is, if you can have
the same companies that are on the
forward foot building this revolution
for us, recognize that we need to bring
some more folks along take some of their
balance sheet capital and invest it to
create this social license to operate.
We will flip this perception on its
head.
>> Yeah, I think it's well said. And you
know, there was a really interesting I
don't you guys must remember this. The
AT&T commercials, you will. Do you
remember those
>> by the way? Sorry, that's another great
example, Jason. AT&T at the turn of the
century. What did they do? They took
their capital and they created Bell
Labs. What did Bell Labs do? Bell Labs
drove all of modern information theory.
It was the precursor to the internet.
They did so much fundamental research. I
want to be clear. I don't think that
this is a five alarm fire. This is very
fixible right now. And the litmus test
quite honestly is in 3, four, five, six
months. Jason, when you see the trickle
of progress if we can get organized,
does your perception change and does the
language that you use and the tone that
you've used over these last 6 months has
me?
>> No, no, no. I'm actually thinking that
you've actually been quite a good early
warning system
>> for what a certain percentage of
Americans think. And so,
>> yes, I predicted it perfectly. Yes.
>> It's been extremely useful. But now we
got to act on it and you have to change
your mind.
>> Oh, no. No. My my mind has been very
crystal clear. I won't let you
you know, tell what I'm saying is my
opinion has been job displacements
coming.
>> Jason, let me be clear. We have to earn
you changing your mind publicly on this
show. If we do that, we're back in a
good place.
>> Uh, yeah. No, I think that you're saying
that in a very condescending way. I have
brought up I have brought up Okay.
Unintentionally.
>> Here, let me let me try to say again.
Sorry. Let me try this again. We have
>> You're saying it as if I'm misguided.
>> No, no, no. You have a perception
>> which is what do you think my perception
is? that on the balance it's a coin flip
about whether AI is going to be
>> all good for all people or very good for
a small subset of people. That's what I
would roughly say that's I would say
that's accurate job.
So let me finish. So if we can execute
this plan again, meaning marry all the
stuff we're doing on the forward foot
within in investing
>> with some of the stuff that we also need
to do to bring a broader swath of the
American population along.
>> Yeah.
>> You will have a different perception if
we are successful. And what I'm saying
is you've had this one perception and
our goal would be to shift you and
people like you.
>> Okay. I I I take it I think it's
completely fair. Yeah. I have been
trying to bring up that as an industry,
we have not recognized people's valid
concerns about job displacement. That's
all I've brought up on this program. I'm
not saying I think it's going to be
cataclysmic or we can't handle it. But I
think if we constantly talk about, hey,
winning the AI race in China, that's
abstract for people. And if we deny the
fact that robo taxis and human robotics
are coming and intelligent people like
Elon or other leaders are saying, "Yeah,
we're we're planning on replacing those
jobs. We're doing a terrible job
communicating this." And I do think part
of this is communication and part of it
is, "Hey, these are valid concerns." So
I think great resolution. Yeah, sure.
I'll be the litmus.
>> Do you guys know what um the Mottton
Bailey fallacy is?
>> No, explain it to the audience. I mean,
I think I've heard of it, but
>> the M and Bailey Castle is an early
medieval fortification where there's
like a very protected area, the keep or
the M. And then the Bailey is kind of
this looser area that's harder to
defend. Right. So, what happens is if
they need to retreat, they'll go into
the M. Okay.
>> Yeah. Lord of the Rings. Right. Right.
So, this has become known as a debating
trick or fallacy where people will make
a really outrageous claim, which is
they'll they'll basically run to the
Bailey and then when you prove that it's
false, they'll run back into the M and
say something very unobjectionable. So,
in the context of like the AI job loss
fallacy,
the Bailey is people will say this is
causing massive job loss, massive
disruption. It's already here. you can
see it and then when I point out well
actually if you look at the Yale Budget
Lab study or you look now at the
Vanguard study there is no job loss then
they'll retreat into the M and they'll
say no no no I'm talking about what's
going to happen in the future which is a
position that's fundamentally
irrefutable and then when I point that
out well wait you just totally change
what you're saying you're like no no no
I was only talking about the future and
then as soon as we sort of seem to have
agreement
>> then the people in the M will race out
to the Bailey and basically saying well
look at happening with Uber drivers or
what have you. So there is this Mott and
Bailey thing happening all the time on
this job loss question
>> and I just want people to be straight
about or honest about it which is look
if your claim is that this will cause
job loss in the future. It's true. I
can't refute that because none of us can
prove what's going to happen in the
future. But be honest about what's
happening today. And in the first three
years after the launch of AI chatbots,
there's been no discernable disruption
to the labor market and the early
studies and data are showing
>> wage increases and actually job
increases and there's definitely job
increases in blue collars because of the
construction boom.
>> This has been our first debate club
corner. Every week we're going to teach
you how to debate better here. No, it's
you know and I I appreciate that and I
have really tried to say here like I'm
not a doomerist at all. you know the
statistics I look at you know I talk to
Dar I have actually sincerely that's why
I don't use I use displacement you know
I really use refined language I do I do
and when I talked to DA he told me in
areas where robo taxis like Whimo are
occurring what they did specifically to
deal with this issue was they stopped
trying to hire drivers in cal in Los
Angeles and in San Francisco because
there are so many whimos they don't want
them to have a had experience. So, you
know, you
wherever in the castle we're talking
about this, I I I don't have a a horse
in this race. I'm not part of this habal
of, you know, Dustin Mosvitz's people. I
just know from talking to Uber and Whimo
and these other companies and, you know,
other companies that are building
software where they're trying to
eliminate jobs. And so, I'm just
bringing that up as a a really
interesting example. Uber and Whimo,
Elon with Tesla, they are actually
making plans right now to deal with this
displacement of drivers and they're
coming up with new products and services
for those drivers. So, one of the things
they're doing is data labeling at Uber.
They they bought a data labeling company
and they're taking the drivers and
saying, "Hey, you want to do some data
labeling over here?" And actually
creating AI jobs for them. So, this is,
you know, uh something that the whole
industry is working on.
>> Look, there's going to be a spectrum,
right? Some jobs are going to change,
some jobs will be eliminated. The
question is with respect to job
eliminations, will that be more than
offset by the net new job creations? If
you're looking at things like Uber
drivers and we go to full self-driving,
then obviously there's going to be some
category of job loss there. So, I'm not
claiming that there's not going to be
any elimination of certain types of
jobs, but I believe that on the whole,
what we're seeing is that when you
improve the productivity of workers,
their wages go up and there's more
demand for their labor, not less. That's
what the data is showing so far and I
just don't think you get that from the
media right now because they are
promoting this dumer narrative and a lot
of that is astroturfed by these
enormously deeped organizations that
have been funded by a few effective
altruists. All right, topic number two.
Economic numbers are out. It's a mixed
bag. Unemployment rate is up and
government payrolls are down. Inflation
somewhere in between. Let's get into the
numbers here. Fun with numbers.
unemployment rate rose to 4.6% from 4.4%
in September and 4% in January of 2025
when President Trump took over. US
economy added 64,000 jobs in new jobs in
November. October saw about 104,000 job
losses, but 162,000 of those job losses
came from the federal government. You
remember the Doge buybacks, friend of
the pod Elon Musk was involved in. Uh
those all took effect at the end of
September. So, there was a little bit of
a balloon payment that occurred. An
analyst from Moody's says, quote, "It's
a frozen job market. There's not much
hiring. There's not much firing
happened." That tracks with what I'm
seeing on the ground. Meanwhile,
inflation came in better than expected
at 2.7%, beating the 3.1%
expectation, but still far away from the
2% target for the Fed. Trump gave an
18minute very loud emphatic address to
the nation last night and it was not
that we're invading Venezuela. It was uh
mostly him talking about his
accomplishments
in terms of uh prices and affordability
and uh a little bit of admonishing
Biden. Here's a 20 second clip. The last
administration and their allies in
Congress looted our treasury for
trillions of dollars, driving up prices
and everything at levels never seen
before. I am bringing those high prices
down and bringing them down very fast.
>> Sax, your thoughts on the economic data.
>> Well, you're you're painting it as
you're painting the economic data as
mixed. I don't know how you have a
economic report that's better than what
we just had today. So, first of all, we
saw that CPI came in at 2.7% like you
said, but the expectations were 3.1%.
That's why the market is rallying today
in a big way. Core inflation is down to
2.6%.
These are significant beats. And this
puts core CPI inflation in the US at its
lowest level since March of 2021. So,
since the whole CO thing. And if you
listen to Kevin Hasset, he said that
over the past 3 months, core inflation's
been running at 1.6%. So the trend line
is going down even further. So it looks
to me like inflation's rolling over and
that's just about a solved problem which
is really good news for what it implies
for interest rates because it implies
that interest rates are coming down and
that's going to bring down things like
mortgage costs and the costs of
financing a car payment and things like
that. Now you talk about unemployment. I
think the unemployment news is very very
good. So if you look at the data from
September to November, the overall
employment is down 41,000. But why was
that? Private employment was up 121,000,
but government employment in the last 2
months has declined by 162,000. So this
is what the media was focused on is they
were trying to claim that unemployment
was up, but actually it's just that the
government jobs decreased. Why did the
government jobs decrease? Well, you
remember that when Doge went in and made
their cuts at the beginning of the year,
they offered people a buyout as of
October 1st. Now, some people took the
buyout right away, but a lot more waited
until the last possible day, which was
October 1st. And that's why you saw this
big spike in October unemployment, but
those are government jobs that are being
cut. And moreover, there are people who
voluntarily wanted to take the buyout
and they took that deal. So again, I
think the employment picture is looking
actually quite good and if you believe
what we believe, you don't want an
excessive number of government jobs. And
President Trump has presided over, I
think, the first decrease in the federal
workforce in decades. We've seen a 10.7%
decrease in federal workers in 2025.
Basically, the number's gone from 2.4
million to 2.15 million. I know that'll
make Freeberg very happy. But look, what
we had during the Biden years is we had
9% inflation. We had a very weak
economy. We did have a recession. It was
that two quarter shallow recession. And
the media even tried to start redefining
what a recession was to avoid those
headlines. But what the Biden
administration did in response to that
is they went hog wild with government
hiring. And what we're seeing now is
inflation is now coming back down and
we're seeing the number of government
workers come down to a more reasonable
level and the private economy is making
up for it. We still have a relatively
historically low unemployment rate. So
those numbers look good. Then you look
at the deficit. We've reduced the
deficit year-over-year by 600 billion.
That will help bring interest rates
down. And then on prices, you got the
lowest gas prices in five years, below
$3 nationally. And then finally, on
wages, real wages are up by over $1,000
on average. And um it's $1,300 for
factory workers, $1,800 for construction
workers. And again, that's a big change
from the buying years where you saw that
in real terms, wages went down by about
$3,000 on average per worker. So look, I
mean, it seems to me like we're on the
cusp of a golden age here. I don't see
how the numbers could really be better.
And then on top of it, again, you've got
this AI tailwind, which I think is a
huge positive, not a negative, which is
adding roughly 2% GDP growth every year
because of huge capex investment with so
far no job loss associated with that. So
I would just say sit back and enjoy
this. I think we're headed for a gang
busters 2026. Rates are coming down.
Inflation's coming down. And you're also
getting tax cuts going into effect next
year because of the big beautiful bill.
No tax on tips, no tax on overtime, no
tax on social security, plus the
standard deductions being beefed up. So
people haven't even felt the benefit of
those tax cuts. That's coming in in
April. I don't see how things could be
much better.
>> Okay, Freeberg, any thoughts here on the
data as it's come in? Or Chimath? I'll
I'll go to either one of you.
>> Directionally, I think it's really
positive. You want to see
private sector jobs growing and the
shrinkage of government sector jobs has
profound impacts not just on the budget,
but it starts to create obvious air
pockets where you get a little bit more
rational regulation. You can deregulate
in the appropriate places. You can shift
the burden and the responsibility to
private industry. So, it's more than
just what's in the numbers that I think
is positive. I've told you this story
before, Jason, to do some of the things
that I've wanted to do. I'll give you an
example. When we started a battery
business 5 years ago, when we filed with
the DOE, the Department of Energy, these
are 700page reports. You spend millions
of dollars and you hire teams of 50 and
100 people. And what are we trying to
do? We're trying to build a battery
business in the United States so that we
can delever from the Chinese.
to the extent that we could do that a
little bit simpler and a little bit
easier because there's fewer folks and
so the burden goes to state and local
regulators which we all already have to
deal with. These are just generally good
things for productivity. They're
generally good things for GDP. It allows
us to invest more aggressively in the
things that help America. So it's
trending in the right direction. By the
way, Sachs didn't mention this
explicitly, but I'll say it.
>> The other thing in 26 is you get a bunch
of tax cuts that kick in. No tax on
tips, no tax on overtime. the
deductibility of the cost of interest
for
things like car loans.
These are big stimulation
accelerated depreciation. You have big
stimulative actions for the United
States economy.
>> Yeah. I think what you guys are missing
>> respectfully is that uh
>> you know uh Trump promised something
completely different. He said starting
on day one we will end inflation and
make America affordable again to bring
down the prices of all goods. And when
he was running for election, he promised
the Americans that he would reduce
prices. Now, what's happened is prices
have not come down. They've gone up 2.5
to 3.1%. But what really matters, and I
think you guys are doing a great job,
you know, pro- administration, part of
the administration. What you're missing
is the American people don't believe
you. And the American people are
experiencing something different. And
when you look at the uh approval rating,
Trump's approval rating is at its
historic lows. and specifically on
inflation. Pull up the silver bullet and
meta analysis there. This is the
disconnect and this is why it seemed
tonedeaf last night when Trump was
telling everybody it's great and when
you say it's the golden age, Americans
aren't experiencing that. That's just
not what they experience. They are
experiencing grocery prices that have
continued to go up and they are
experiencing unemployment that's gone up
15%. Whether it's the federal employees,
whether it's private sector, and you
debate the numbers, or there's a golden
age coming because of no tax on tips,
these are all talking points. What the
American people remember is the Trump
administration said prices would go
down. Prices have gone up. That jobs and
manufacturing, there'd be all these
incredible manufacturing things.
Obviously, that's going to take years.
That has not happened yet. So, I hope
for the best. I hope inflation goes down
to two. And I hope they turn this
around. But the American people don't
believe the Trump administration. And
it's a big difference between promising
stuff in 2024 and delivering it. And
here we are in the first year and the
delivery that's come in from the Trump
administration on inflation and on the
economy is not good if you're in the
bottom half of society that doesn't own
equities. Period. Full stop.
>> So, first of all, prices have come down.
You look at gas prices are the lowest in
five years. They're below $3 nationally.
Now, I don't know how you want a new
administration to come in and literally
affect every single change on day one.
How do you do that?
>> Oh, no. That's just what he said.
>> No. What the president said is they
would start working on they would start.
>> I'm not saying it's possible. That's
what he said.
>> No, he said he'd start working on it on
day one. And so he did. And look at the
results. Inflation's now down to 2.7%
way below expectations. I don't know how
you want a better report than this.
Unemployment is very low. The only
reason Remember the uh the economic
target was 3 three and three 3% GDP
growth, 3% deficit to GDP and 3%
inflation. They're below 3% inflation.
They're above 3% GDP growth and the
deficit to GDP is not where it needs to
be. So cutting is still ahead. But I
looked at the budgets for 2026 for a
number of the departments in the cabinet
over the last couple days and they do
have big cuts that they're trying to
implement across the federal government.
We're going to be interviewing Scott
Bessent tomorrow morning that'll come
out shortly after this episode airs. But
this is the catchup conversation with
Scott on how's the 333 plan going. But
on two of the three metrics, Jay Cal, it
does appear like things are good. I'm
not trying to be a spokesperson for the
Trump administration, but I'd say if you
look at this just from the raw economic
data and the the goals of the
administration following that, there
should be a flow through in terms of job
growth, the flow through in terms of
affordability, in terms of wage growth,
all those other sort of economic
indicators that actually affect people
on Main Street every day. Uh that's also
TBD in the narrative is still to be
written, but those high level economic
goals are still, you know, are starting
to kind of fall within the the framework
of what they set out to do, which is
generally good, right?
>> Yeah. I'm just pointing out the
disconnect again. This is the disconnect
with the American people. I mean,
>> no, no, I'm looking at year one.
>> Just year one. We're here at the end.
>> Time to implement an agenda.
>> I totally agree. I'm just telling you
the American people don't believe the
Trump administration right now. There's
more work to do.
>> That's the data that came out today is
looking awesome. By the way, that
Vanguard report that I mentioned that
also exposes the AI job loss hoax, it
also has a new economic assessment for
next year is projecting 3% growth for
next year, which I think is
conservative, and an improved labor
market outlook for 2026, and it says the
most robust improvement will come in the
second half of the year. So, Vanguard is
saying that 2026 is looking very good.
And by the way, that's when the fight
for Congress will unfold is next year.
So, you know, the thing about polls is
it's obviously just a snapshot in time
and it doesn't tell you what things are
going to look like 6 months from now or
a year from now. I think they're going
to look very good.
>> Yeah. I mean, maybe he turns it around.
>> I think it's already been turned around.
It just takes time to kick in.
>> Yeah. I mean, the the public's
perception it hasn't turned around and
inflation was supposed to go down and it
stayed.
>> It has. No, it stayed at it's still way
above the 2%
>> 1.6% for the last three months.
>> No, it has not. It was just 2.7.
>> No, that's the problem I think with the
administration and your part of it. Like
you guys cherry pick numbers and it's
not matching the numbers on the field.
So when you cherryick cherry picking,
this says CPI report.
>> The the the number
>> open the cover of the Wall Street
Journal. 2.7 Hold on. 2.7% CPI 2.6% 6%
core
>> 1.6% for last 3 months.
>> Okay.
>> What is hard to understand about this?
Obviously, the last three months are
going to tell you what the trajectory
is.
>> Okay. The the fact is
>> you're looking for every excuse you can
to basically downplay what is
>> an awesome report and just look at the
stock market which is ripping today
because this is way below expectations.
You're the only one who's not happy
about this news, Jacob.
>> No, no. the the country is not happy
about it. I I'm not I don't have a horse
in this race. I'm doing fantastic. I own
equities. I'm doing better than I ever
have in my life. I'm talking about how
the bottom half of America perceives it.
This is the blind spot of the Trump
administration. You've proved my point
by not addressing it. Let's go to the
next subject.
>> No, I haven't. What? What?
>> No, I guess the fact that you guys My
point is the American people
>> expected that inflation would go down
and prices would go down. Prices have
continued to go up. Fed has a 2% target.
It's a little bit unrealistic to say
that what you want to you want wait you
want to have you want to have a negative
inflation rate.
>> Trump said prices will go down. They
have not. That's what the American
people feel. Unemployment has gone up.
They expect it to go down. So the this
idea that we're in the golden age is not
tracking with the bottom half of
Americans. That's just facts, David.
It's just facts. You have work to do.
Trump has work to do. You're you're
saying that anything less than deflation
anything less than deflation in your
view is
>> I did not say that you keep telling I
keep telling you what I'm reporting in
terms of facts then you tell me I said
something different I didn't say that
the American people are very
disappointed in the Trump
administration's first year when it
comes to inflation and the economy
>> I don't understand how the numbers could
be any better we just blew past
expectations here 2.7%
>> I don't know whose expectations I don't
know whose
>> pulse you think you have the finger of
but the economists who put together
>> these expectations
>> were expect
one more time for me just pull up the
chart for me uh so I can just explain
that this isn't bias on my part I'm just
putting the fact on the field no it is
not this is
>> these are numbers that you can look at
and see that Trump's two worst
categories right now are the economy and
inflation the American people thought he
was
>> these are snapshots in time and they're
going to
snapshot time from February goes down.
That's the snapshot time. Every month
you have 12 months there to look at.
>> Let me explain. I don't know what's so
hard about this is a really partisan
point that you're making it. You're
basically saying
>> I'm not part economy is like a giant
super
>> tanker. I'm not part
>> Can I finish my point?
>> Sure you can.
>> I mean you must know this and I think
you're pretending not to. The US economy
is like a giant super tanker. It takes
time to turn around. It takes time to
implement your economic agenda. It took
the president the first six months of
the administration to implement the big
beautiful bill which is his economic
program. But it doesn't even go into
effect until January 1st. So the tax
cuts have not gone into effect. The
inflation reductions have happened.
We've gone from 9% under Biden to now
2.6% core 1.6% the last 3 months. I
don't know what more you could want.
Interest rates have come down. They're
projected to come down even more because
inflation's coming down. This is again a
huge ship that's in the process of
turning around and I predict that by
next year the numbers are going to be
even better. Let me remind you of what
happened in the early 1980s under Ronald
Reagan when Reagan took over. Okay, the
misery index was at like 20%. Reagan
implemented his economic agenda, but it
took a couple of years to actually
implement it. By 1983, we actually had a
very severe recession because Vulkar had
raised interest rates so much to tame
inflation. We're lucky we don't have
that issue today. In any event, it took
like three years for Reagan to implement
his economic agenda and his popularity
was very low by 1983, but by 1984, the
program had worked and it was morning in
America again. And he won the biggest
landslide election, I think, in American
history. So, you got to give it time for
the president's agenda to play out and
work. And it certainly looks like after
10 months that is performing extremely
well. and we are just beginning to see
the impact of it.
>> I think the core issue is Trump
overpromised and underd delivering year
one and it's not the golden age for the
bottom half of Americans and they don't
feel it's the golden age and I think
just t tackling that head on and saying
yeah we have more work to do and I
actually think that's what the address
last night was about. I suspect
somebody, maybe Susie or the the chief
of staff or somebody said, "Hey, we got
to start communicating better about the
cost of living and our promises during
the election so that we turn this
around." That's actually what I think is
happening. But I I don't have a horse in
this race. I'm doing fabulous because I
own equities. I'm happy. I'm concerned,
sure, that the bottom half of society
needs to do a little bit better. That's
all. All right. But you, you know,
listen, I I'm never going to win with
you, Saxs, because you're the captain of
the debate club. You will win every
debate. You're you're incredible.
>> Well, look, I mean, like the president
the president made the right point last
night, which is he inherited a giant
mess. Again, under the Biden years, we
had a $3,000 reduction in in real wages
by American workers. That's already gone
up by $1,000 under President Trump in
the first year. But yeah, if you're a
worker and you're just looking at your
situation, you're underwater 2,000
relative to where you were 5 years ago.
So obviously you're going to be salty
about that, but that's the situation
that that President Trump inherited. I
don't know how much more progress you
could make in 10 months, but give it
another year and then we'll really see.
>> All right, I am rooting for you guys. I
hope you turn it around in year two.
Okay, Freeberg, we got an important
story here we have to get to.
>> Do you guys want to hear a crazy
personal story for 2 minutes as a
palette cleanser?
>> Oh, 32.
>> Oh, yes. As a palette cleanser,
>> this is an amuse bougge.
>> Okay, this is an amuse. A little a
little pomplamoose sorbet.
>> This is the craziest story
>> in my life right now.
>> Pull up the photo, Nick. The first
photo.
>> You guys remember my dog, Monty?
>> Yeah. This is the virtue signal dog.
>> Not the virtue signal.
>> Oh, this is the best dog. This is Monty.
>> This is Monty. Monty. Monty was my dog
for 10 years. I got him 10 years ago in
January and he died suddenly in May. He
turns out he had a tumor on his heart
and his heart burst open in front of me
and he died. It was the worst thing. He
was with me every second of every day
>> that I wasn't at work. He slept on my
bed. He was in my office all day. You
guys have seen him a million times in
the background during the all-in pod. My
best friend in the world. The greatest
thing I've ever come across in my life.
>> So, he died suddenly. It was very
brutal, very hard. So, I'm at my house
the other day. My next door neighbor
walks in and he's got this dog on his
leash. Pull up this photo. This is this
dog. So, my next door neighbor finds
this dog at Rocket Dog Rescue. It was
pulled out of a kill shelter. The vet
estimates this dog is like a decade old.
Today, I live probably 40 miles away
from where we got Monty. He was found
wandering the streets of the Mission
District in San Francisco. This random
dog here was found at some random kill
shelter somewhere in California, pulled
out of the kill shelter a few days ago,
put into Rocket Dog, and rescued by my
next door neighbor. Brings him over.
He's walking him in the street. And I'm
like, "Oh my god, that dog looks just
like my old dog, Monty." We ran a DNA
test. This dog is Monty's brother.
>> What?
>> This dog is Monty's brother. It is the
craziest. There's like a billion dogs on
planet Earth. And of the billion dogs,
some random dog from some random litter
from some street pup in the Mission
District from a decade ago found its way
into a shelter, into another rescue
center, into my next door neighbor's
arms, and brought back to my house
months after Monty died. How crazy is
that?
What is his personality like?
>> I'm going to hang out with him this
afternoon. I got to go see.
>> But how crazy is this? Just It's Monty's
actual brother from the same
>> Monty in fairness.
>> Monty.
>> Well, the angles are off.
>> Step brother.
>> Monty's more robust.
>> Yeah. Well, Monty was wellfed. This dog
lived in a freaking kill shelter. So,
>> Monty was a heck of a dog. Take take 12
pounds off Monty. But
>> wait, where's the other tests?
>> Don't lie.
>> Where's the uh dog that was being
tortured by Revlon?
>> That dog. The dogs have gotten robust,
too.
>> Yeah.
>> Was it Rabon who was torturing your
>> She she Daisy has a thousand siblings,
not just one.
>> And uh Daisy Daisy I'm fine with. It's
Mitchell. It's Mitchell Freeberg. I hate
>> Marshall. Marshall.
>> Marshall Freeber. I hate Marshall
Freeberg.
>> I got to hang out.
>> He ate the pistachios last Christmas.
Marshall's like a little
>> Monty's father must have really gotten
around San Francisco.
>> He had a great run on
>> What are the odds of this?
>> Same mother, same father. It's not a
half brother. This is the same Monty's
dad was a
>> same same litter, same dog, same same
mother, same father, same litter on the
streets of San Francisco a decade ago.
And they all find their way in different
parts of California and come to Andy's
buried in my backyard. And this dog
>> samples
love. Was it the summer of the same?
>> You would say no way, but you got to see
better shots of it. I'll put more
>> photo side by side.
>> Yeah,
>> this doesn't make sense.
>> I know. It's the craziest ever. And by
the way, like
>> yeah, it doesn't look like they're
related. I'll be honest with you.
>> Gotta find you a proper photo of
>> What's going on? Chop up with Oki and
Joker. How old are these dogs now?
>> Oh my god. From your lips, the God's
yours, bro. Aie is 14 and a half. She
turns 15 in July.
>> She's so precious.
>> And Joker's eight or nine. So Touchwood,
they're uh
>> Yeah,
>> Golden Retrievers don't really live to
15, but my god, she's been
>> You got a lot of good years. I was just
on the I was on the floor last Thursday
snuggling with her and it was so
precious.
>> Well, you know what we did the I think
the best thing that we did was we got
much more disciplined about diet for AI
when she turned about 13.
Little bit calorie restricted. It's not
nearly as much. She lost a few kilos. It
helped her a lot walking and
>> she's a little deaf unfortunately, but
she can see.
>> Dogs are the best. My god,
>> dogs are the best. Here's my Here's
here's my other photo of the dog that
Chamoth hates. Pull it up just so you
can see.
>> Marshall, listen. Last last Christmas at
Nat's birthday dinner on the 26th, which
is her birthday, Marshall Freeberg
jumped on the table, started eating all
of the pistachios and the nuts,
>> ruined them,
>> ruined all of them, slobbered
everywhere.
>> All David Freeberg was like, "Oh, look
at that." Allison Freeberg was like,
"Marshall Freeberg, they they have no
control over what's going on."
>> Here, pull this photo up, Nick. This is
a a medical issue Marshall Friedberg's
been dealing with. He wakes up with
irreoverable erections, so he can't
walk.
>> What?
>> Pull this up.
>> Irreoverable.
>> So, Nick, you got to blur this out. When
you
>> Oh, dude's packing.
>> So, this little guy, he wait erection.
>> He has these erections and well, the
doctors say like, "You just got to wait
and if it ends up staying for too long,
there's going to be a surgery." But like
right now, he's okay. But he can't move
when he gets them and he's stuck and
he'll just stand there unable to move
for like 20 minutes like with his little
>> thing happened. I gave Chimat some of my
roast sparks and he had a similar thing
happened. He was frozen.
>> There's there's a Brian Johnson joke in
here. But
>> that is a problem.
>> Yeah.
>> How's Moose doing? Jake's my special
guy.
>> Here he is. Special.
>> Oh,
>> is that your dog?
>> This is the moose. The moose is trying
to keep Oh, buddy. Oh, buddy. Fish is my
buddy. Oh, good. What are you doing?
What are you chewing on?
>> What's he doing?
>> I think you got a pop. Get that out of
your mouth. Come on. Get that out of
your mouth. He is such a little love
buddy. Sh love.
>> It's like a gremlin.
>> He loves it.
>> It's great. It's great to see you so in
control.
>> Jason, you're such a natural dog guy,
Jason.
That's buddy.
>> A disciplinarian. This dog loves food.
>> You're really and he loves to wrestle.
>> You're like a modern believable
at the ranch.
>> Does he headbutt you?
>> The dog whisper
>> Moose. Take it easy, buddy. I know. He
loves to wrestle this dog.
>> He's heavy, right? He's
>> Well, we he added about four or five
pounds cuz he wasn't eating all that
much when we got him. And then we
realized he needs a little bit of extra
food. We gave him a little more food and
he became a little less um grumpy
>> and then he just
>> we take him for like maybe three one
mile walks a day on the ranch.
>> Totally fine. If he misses a walk,
doggy's got way too much energy. So,
he's not he's a ranch dog, not a city
dog. This dog
>> I know. I know. I told you.
>> Yeah, he needs to run. When he doesn't
run, you got a problem. All right, let's
keep going through the docket here. Uh
that's dog corner. That's K9 corner.
What do you guys think? That's a good
corner. It's a good cat corner. It's the
best corner.
>> But how crazy is that? One like one in a
billion's got to be that this dog lands
up next to me. It's just the craziest
thing. Anyway,
>> yeah. And uh yeah, there's no cat corner
here. Cats are horrible.
>> Shout out to our friends at Whimo for
eliminating the cat problem in San
Francisco.
>> I mean, that's just that was the
greatest update to their software ever.
If they can eliminate more cats,
>> what's that paradox that the AI has
where it's like, do I hit the trolley?
It's like the cat problem. Go for the
problem. Go for the cat. It's just go
for the cat.
>> Absolutely. You could get somebody there
on time or you could get them there 30
seconds late and take out a cat. Take
out the cat. Less stray cats. Cats are
horrible. Shout out to our cat ladies
listening to the pod. There's I wonder
how many cat ladies listen to this pod.
I think there are a few.
>> Oh, there are a few.
>> Are there a few? Yeah, they hear from
they're on blue sky talking about Oh,
god. I had a joke. I'm not going to do
it. All right. According to a Reuters
report, Freeberg, China has built a
prototype of ASML's EUV machine. Hey, if
this is true, this report, it's uh it
could have a profound impact on the AI
race that we talked about. For those of
you who don't know, ASML is the Dutch
company worth $400 billion,
22nd largest market cap in the world,
and uh they are the only company that
makes EUV machines, also called
lithography. That stands for uh extreme
ultraviolet. That's how you make H100s.
Here's a photo of one of these giant
machines. They cost $250 million to
make, and they take 6 months to make,
filled with all kinds of important
parts. Carl Zeiss lenses, etc. Since
2018,
these machines have been limited for
sale by the Dutch. Why? Why can't China
buy these machines? Well, in 2018,
Trump's Secretary of State, Mike Pompeo,
put pressure on the Dutch to impose
export controls on China. And uh later
that same year, they did. So,
according to Reuters in this news story,
Freeberg,
China used former ASML engineers
allegedly to reverse engineer the
machines. Reuters has pointed out that
the machine in China has not yet
produced any working chips. It's a
prototype. The CCP is targeting 2028 uh
for working chips. Some sources say
maybe 2030 is more likely. You've been
talking about China lithography on the
show. We can play the Chariots of Fire
music that Freeberg insists we play when
he does his victory lap. Chimoth, here's
his victory lap. Episode 224. Last year,
China announced and began a 37 billion
investment in developing their own
3nanometer uh chimp technology. China
made a claim that this investment they
had made was starting to pay off and
they had developed their own EUV system
and their big semiconductor companies
called the semiconductor manufacturing
international corporation or SMIC in
China. They launched a seven nanometer
chip with Huawei in their Mate 60 Pro,
which is sort of like their iPhone
competitor in China. And so they're
proclaiming that they've already got
this EUV technology. From what I
understand, and Sax would know better
than I, it sounds like there was a lot
of reverse engineering and workound of
existing technology in order to deliver
that system.
>> Who do you think has the best chance of
challenging Nvidia? My early prediction
for 2026 is Huawei where I think that
there's lithography technology that
exists in China that is not publicly
discussed that is going to be deployed
in Huawei and all these fabs that
they're building in mainland China.
>> So announcements 2026 impact 27 probably
fair.
>> Do you have first first on allin
Freeberg? Congratulations on your weekly
>> victory lap here. I don't I don't I
honestly don't think that the Reuter
story is necessarily news cuz I think
it's a little bit of a narrow scope in
trying to describe what happened which
is that they quote stole ASML technology
because scientists are working on it.
That's not really the full scope of
what's been going on in China for a
number of years and it really
understates the technological progress
that China's independently made in using
other systems to try and achieve
lithography parody. So if you go back a
number of years, the current kind of
investment vehicle is actually Chinese
banks put capital into a fund that's
roughly $48 billion uh US dollars which
is actually what's called the national
integrated circuit industry investment
fund phase 3. So there was phase 1 which
started in 2014 which focused on
manufacturing. So developing fabs with
groups like SMIC. Phase two was stood up
in 2019 which focused primarily on
design and materials. And then this
phase three fund was established in 2024
explicitly to pivot to what they call
choke points or bottlenecks in the
manufacturing process. And state media
has confirmed the existence of this
phase 3 fund and the intentionality of
the phase 3 fund to try and replicate
lithography technology. Couple of months
ago, if you pull up the link, Nick,
here's a publication on this paper. So
this is the leading research group out
of China that's been backing into
lithography technology using AIdriven
systems. They published this paper which
was a very good summary of where they
are in July.
Was this in nature? No, it's in light
science and applications and this paper
is called advancements and challenges in
inverse lithography technology a review
of artificial intelligence-based
approaches. If you read into the paper
and then you read the other publications
from this particular research team at
Singua University, they have made a
number of breakthroughs in using AI to
try and reestablish alternative systems
and the traditional Zeiss optics and
other control systems that are used in
the ASML platform. And the way that
they've done it, I I won't spend too
much time on it, but there's a bunch of
neural networks that they've used,
trained, and have made discoveries from,
including doing things like working with
suboptimal optics, meaning you can have
optics that have a degree of diffusion.
And then how do you actually recreate
3nmter printing techniques or 3nm masks
by having shadowy effects accounted for
in the AI? So, you almost like assume
that the shadowy effects are going to
come out and you print differently than
you otherwise would. you don't need the
degree of precision that you need and
you don't necessarily need to go get the
Zeiss optics. There was another paper
that was published early this year by
another Chinese research team that
actually demonstrated how they did use
AI to discover a novel method for doing
optics. So there is a very broad and
wellunded effort that's been underway
for over a decade. But just in the last
couple of years with artificial
intelligence based approaches, they've
made a series of breakthroughs. It is
very likely the case that Huawei already
has a lithography system that they'll be
putting into production and this is why
I kind of talked about it when we were
in Vegas and pointed it out earlier this
year.
>> But I again I think Reuters just sort of
maybe caught on to some narrow segment,
but this is a bigger story and a bigger
set of progress that's been made over
quite some time. ramification stacks
here and and what you're thinking.
Obviously, you've talked a bunch about,
hey, let's sell our stack in there and
they're clearly working on their own
stack. What what's uh what's the
ramification of this if it's true?
>> Well, I've never supported selling EUV
lithography to China. It is probably,
>> you know, selling the stack of H1,
whatever the previous Nvidia stack was.
Yeah, EUV lithography. These machines
that are made by ASML is probably our
single biggest advantage in the AI race
because they're the only machines that
are capable of creating say 2 to 3
nanometer chips, semiconductors, and
it's sort of the perfect export control
because there's only one company that
makes these machines like you showed.
They're gigantic. They're expensive. So
if you think about like trying to put an
export control on a commodity, there'd
be a lot of ways to circumvent it
because there's a lot of sources for a
commodity. But in this case, there's
literally only one company that makes
these machines. So it's been a
tremendous advantage, I'd say, for the
West that we have EUV lithography. I'm
not surprised that China is trying to
reverse engineer it. It's kind of the
obvious thing to do. No advantages
forever. It does seem likely that at
some point they'd be able to figure out
how to do it. So I think that this
article is not altogether a surprise in
that sense. I mean I'm sure that China
is trying really really hard to reverse
engineer this. In the meantime, however,
they've also made substantial progress
with DUV lithography. So the previous
generation of lithography before EUV was
DUV. E is extreme. D is deep. In any
event, DUV was supposed to sort of top
out at say 14 nanometer chips and China
was able to push the technology to get
to 7 nanometer and now to five. So
they've able to get a lot further using
DUV lithography than anyone thought
possible and that is why the Huawei
chips, the Ascent chips are they're not
as good as our chips, but they're
serviceable and they've been able to use
their prowess in networking to string
more of them together. You have the
cloud matrix 384 technology where Huawei
will string together 384 of their Huawei
Ascent chips into a rack and that will
perform comparable to an Nvidia rack but
using a lot more power. So the bottom
line is China's been able to create a
lot of these workarounds to our
restrictions. But if they figured out
how to reverse EUV that would be I'd say
a blow because it is a real advantage
for us. But I'm not convinced that this
Reuter story is the the full picture. I
think it's just a data point.
>> Jim, any thoughts here?
>> If you want a very short summary of how
the last generation of chips work, the
best way to think about this is that the
most profitable and valuable chips to
date have taken a very compute ccentric
approach. That's why we've needed these
ultra advanced process nodes. But the
reality is that in a world of infinite
inference, let's say the next generation
of silicon will not take the same
compute heavy approach and will probably
rely on a much more memorycentric
architecture that uses a lot of SRAM.
The value of that is that you can
produce these things as Sax said at 14
nanometer at 75 all of these process
nodes that are much less advanced that I
actually think is the future. So, in a
weird way,
if they steal this, which I think we
should assume they've already stole it
quite honestly and they figured it out,
the question is how bad is it? That's
the really important question. And the
thing about a more memory ccentric
approach for AI inference or these next
generation forms of silicon, it demands
a lot more of compilers. It demands a
lot more of the software. I still think
that's where we are light years ahead.
So, I don't think it's the end of the
world and we're still in a very good
place,
but it is bad. Friberg, weren't we
supposed to uh start onshoring with the
chips act and maybe get trending towards
having this production ability in
America? And obviously that's been
really hard to do.
And China and their relationship with
Taiwan seems to be and and the
possibility that they actually take over
Taiwan in a military fashion has been
this existential concern or even
short-term concern.
>> Maybe it's a better way to say it. The I
think the biggest security implication
to consider at this moment is that both
the US and mainland China are onshoring
manufacturing and that makes Taiwan less
of a strategic point of interest for the
United States and for United States
industry. Maybe one of the ways to think
about the positive aspect of what is
going on which is maybe call it the
bulcanization of generally manufacturing
but specifically semiconductor
manufacturing in this case is reduced
security concerns. So there's no longer
this flash point perhaps in Taiwan. If
China did invade Taiwan and the US had
fab manufacturing, we're less likely to
want to defend Taiwan. And frankly, if
China has fabs on mainland, do they
really need to invade Taiwan?
>> What's the economic interest in doing
so?
>> Yeah, that's kind of where I was going
with it. But if they also wanted to
jumpstart Freedberg, they could just go
to Taiwan and take the machines. Like,
is that actually the plan?
>> Like I I don't know what the CCP's plan
is. I think that's a pretty um simple
statement to make. I think just going to
Taiwan is probably a lot more
complicated than
>> of course it is. My point is if this if
this was super existential to get those
chips for China and they go to Taiwan
and they then they've reverse engineered
the machine by default.
>> We we need to recognize we keep using
the term reverse engineering as if ASML
is the only way to do this and it is
not. If you read their papers and you
read what's coming out, there are
alternative production manufacturing
methods and systems that are being
developed in China that not only maybe
provide parody to ASML, but get ahead of
ASML. And I think this is really
important to understand. China is not
just in a catch-up race. They're in a
primacy race and they are trying to
develop privacy in lithography
technology which will give them privacy
in manufacturing which will give them
primacy in AI which will give them
economic leverage over the planet and
that is very critical for us to
understand. This is not about stealing
data from ASML. Like, no one gives a
[__] If you're sitting in China, you're
thinking about I've got the world's best
scientists or some of the world's best
scientists and I'm giving them the
resources and I'm giving them the
mandate to go solve this problem. The
government, as I mentioned last year,
put $40 billion against this problem and
said, "Go figure it out." And these guys
at Singa are publishing some
groundbreaking research on how to do it.
>> But it's easier to catch up or to copy
than to innovate.
So if you're China, the first thing
you'd want to do is just copy EUV and
get that technology for yourself.
>> Well, let me ask you this. What would
you do? So you're the AIAR. You're
sitting in the United States and China's
got this lithography technology. Is your
goal to steal their technology or is
your goal to get your best scientists
and say, "Let's get ahead of their
technology."
>> If I'm China,
>> neither are the United States.
>> It's to solve the problem. What is the
actual economic commercial problem we're
solving?
>> Right. So if you can figure out a way to
do manufacturing better, cheaper, faster
than the way the that China does it, you
would obviously take that path. You're
not trying to get to par with China, if
you view yourself to be supreme to
China,
>> China. But you have to understand even
with these EUV machines and the same is
true in the other side
>> at two or even sub 2 nanometer scale,
you have these incredible laws of
physics that you are pushing to the
boundaries of which cause these chips to
have pretty low yield. you have a lot of
systems that actually aren't that
efficient and highly utilized as a
result. So these systems are brittle.
The second thing is that when you have
these compute- ccentric architectures,
you end up making design decisions like
HBM, they'll have to go and steal all
the HBM which is the high bandwidth
memory business that SKHix and Samsung
have. But again, that's where Nvidia and
then Google have an effective monopoly.
>> Let me ask you a question, S. I mean,
what's your strategic response if China
next year goes into manufacturing? with
a sub 2 nanometer system that's got
higher yields, is faster, is cheaper
than anything that we're seeing anywhere
else in the world.
>> Well,
I don't think that's going to happen.
Let's talk about that if it actually
happens. I don't think it's going to.
But what would I be focused on right
now? I would say we want to get more of
the leading edge manufacturing in the
United States. TSMC has already opened a
big fab in Arizona and they're planning
on increasing the size of that and
that's really important and we should
get all these restrictions out of the
way. They're facing all sorts of
permitting restrictions. I mean all the
stuff that Bernie is talking about where
he wants to slow down. I mean he's
talking about data centers but not
>> manufacturing but the concepts are the
same.
>> Yeah. Roana, Elizabeth Warren, you've
got
>> exactly wrong. I mean,
>> anti-che progress people saying, "Let's
stop all this stuff." Meanwhile, China
is not just racing to catch up, but
they're likely going to get ahead of the
United States. And if we're caught
flatfooted because we've got a
moratorium on development, a moratorium
on production, it's going to be
extraordinarily damaging,
>> right? Well, look, this is where I agree
with you is that if this Reuters report
is accurate, it does speed up the
timeline on China closing the chip gap
from
>> decades to a few years. You can go read
the Singua papers. You'll see that these
guys are so advanced.
>> If they care about being ahead, why are
they publishing that paper?
>> So, by the way, this is a really
important point and I've picked up on
this from a number of different
disciplines in scientific research. So,
what's been going on is scientists in
China, they're very smart people.
There's very great scientists there. And
like all scientists, they don't think
necessarily in terms of nationalism
first. They think in terms of science.
They want to publish their research.
They want to be known. They want to be
the discoverers of these new frontiers
and so they publish. And what we've seen
in several instances is that the
scientific research groups will publish
and they'll publish slightly ahead. And
once they get ahead of the market or
they get ahead of the world, suddenly
they stop publishing. And it's almost
like the CCP comes in and it's like,
okay, you guys are now, you know, going
too far. We don't want to tip our hat
too far. And the stuff starts to recede.
And I think there was this one paper on
optics that is designed to replace the
Zeiss monopoly in optics that suddenly
disappeared and that research team
stopped publishing. I got to find this
paper. This came out last year.
>> There are a number of these disciplines
where there's publications that go to a
certain extent and then they stop
publishing. So I think that there's a
little bit of a
>> because of the funding cycle in China.
You have every single local government
that's given capital to invest in
businesses and so they compete and
compete until it gets to the state level
and you have one or two national
champions. But if this was so important,
Freeberg, would there also be an
argument to
publish things that would send um that
would be misinformation or send people
down a wrong direction?
>> No, because you have to again the
funding cycle is you get as a policy
person in Shanghai, you get promoted
because you make a good bet.
>> Yeah. No, but you so by the time it
becomes a one national to Freeberg's
point, when's the last time you saw BYD
or CL publish anything meaningful,
>> but when they were not the national
champion, they were probably publishing
very aggressively.
But at that time, there was 50 different
companies competing to be the national
champion. So I suspect what's happening
here is there's 50 different semi-
startups all over China. Everybody's
trying to support their own local
version and eventually when there's one
they disappear.
>> Okay. Interesting.
>> I mean, one of the things we see is
China does give money to these research
institutions on frontier science and
then there's an industrialization. It's
something the US isn't quite as good at.
And I think it's again, we've talked
about the co-opting of our universities
as research institutions over the last
couple of decades. They've become these
sort of employment centers, if you will,
and they've become these sort of weird
social engineering systems. They've kind
of gotten away from some of the core
research or that that's been kind kind
of co-opted. In China, there are these
sort of dedicated research centers and
then there are universities where
there's very clear independent research
that goes on on university campuses.
They typically get quite a bit of
funding. And the way this worked, if you
look into the details of this China
National Integrated Circuit Industry
Investment Fund, and there were three
funds, one, two, and three, the funds
get bigger and bigger as the research
teams make progress. Uh, it's a very
smart way of doing things from a central
planning perspective. And then in in
phase three, they're now targeting these
specific unlocks that then will enable
industrialization. So they're funding
some of this core research. The core
research has these breakthroughs and
then it gets industrialized. It's during
that research phase where we see a lot
of publications happening and this is
happening in life sciences as well and
in physics and in material science and
as soon as they start to get a little
bit ahead of the curve then it gets
industrialized and the and the
publications kind of stop. So I don't
know if it's necessarily the CCP
stepping in and saying hey stop
publishing you're going to let the world
know too much of what we're having
versus okay the handoff is now happening
and industrialization begins. Yeah,
look, I would just say that to me the
takeaway here is that the timeline on
China closing the gap with us is being
sped up. Whether it's the fact that
they're copying what we're doing,
whether EUV is being reverse engineered
or maybe their scientists are figuring
out a way to leaprog, we are in a pretty
close race with China. And that's why I
think it's really important that we
don't listen to Bernie and others who
just want to stop the progress because
the progress is not going to stop. This
is going to happen in China and that
will be a big problem for the United
States.
>> All right, speaking of
socialism/communism,
uh you guys thinking about coming to
Austin, my neck of the woods.
>> I've been uh pulling up these photos in
Austin of these homes.
>> You know I'm doing it right.
>> Welcome to Texas, boys.
>> Like on the lake.
>> Sachs already bought a house. Sachs
already bought a house.
>> He hooked me up with the uh agent.
>> What does she got you looking at?
>> I'm not sure yet. We're just
>> You guys are bidding against each other,
[__]
>> You can have my sloppy seconds.
>> You have the high ground, so you can
negotiate hard.
>> Uh there is so much inventory, but only
like 20% of the inventory is on the MLS.
80% here because it's a no reporting
state is off market. So, it's completely
different than
>> any other market. Certainly California.
>> I want to be on the lake. Like, if I'm
going to do this on the water,
>> Oh, really? I don't want the lake. I
mean, if you're here, here's the
challenge with the lake. People are
going to come up to your house and take
pictures and hang out like 2 feet off
your house and starting at 7 a.m.
>> Texas house in San Francisco.
>> Everybody's zipping around the lake in
motorboats starting at 7 a.m. It's
beautiful.
>> I love your thing. It's great, but just
>> understand it's going to get loud at 7
a.m.
>> There's nothing a good motorboating
doesn't
>> Who doesn't love a good motorboat?
Jal, I heard you're like an hour away.
You're not even in Austin.
>> I I'm in the Hill Country on my ranch,
but we're getting a place closer to the
city, actually. So, we're 30 minutes
outside the city.
>> 30 minutes? My god.
>> I heard you're
>> I heard you're in the sticks.
>> No, not that far. Not that far.
>> No, he's in the suburbs of the suburbs.
>> No, if you want to have like, you know,
dozens of acres, you can't do that in
the city.
>> When I was growing up in Memphis, they
called that Bumble Egypt.
BF
>> Bumble.
>> I mean, if you want a ranch and you want
like dozens of acres, you can't do that
in You can get an acre to three acres
inside of the city.
>> I found an acre in Terry Town.
>> An acre is doable. Two acres is
possible.
>> You know what's so sad? Even if this
bill doesn't get on the books, which I
think
>> everyone's leaving,
>> there's a decent chance it ripped the
band-aid off, the revenues of California
are going to plummet.
plummet.
>> Man, it is um yeah, I mean we saw the
writing on the wall. Socialism is coming
and you know this one of the great
things about having a United States of
America that different states can
optimize for different things.
>> The thing here
>> that one bill this proposed billionaire
tax has singlehandedly changed the
trajectory of the California economy by
a hundred to$200 billion dollars over
the next 5 to 10 years. It's an enormous
cell phone. People were here willing to
pay the money and now
>> Yeah, people were willing to put up with
a lot in this state.
>> As soon as you tell people, "Hey, we're
we're doing property seizures,
>> property seizures or their threat of
property seizures or the fact that
people didn't come out against property
seizures is enough for everyone to be
like, "See you see you later." The fact
that all the politicians didn't in
uniform stand up and say, "This is
ridiculous. We're never going to let
this happen." They let this happen by
not defending the property rights that
are endowed in this country. They lost
everything.
>> They had to defend it.
>> What do you think happens to the state
budget over the next four or five years
as a result of this?
>> You're right. It's trash. And by the
way, and that that's what drives the
socialist spiral because then they try
and do more property seizures and they
try and get the money back.
>> Who are they going to tax? Everybody's
going to be gone now.
>> And here's the other crazy statistic
that we never talk about. I was going to
try and put some data together and get
it as a topic, but we should save it for
the new year. But the California pension
fund system is underfunded by roughly a
trillion dollars. So these folks in the
California pension fund system are
sitting around waiting for money to come
to them every year for the next 30, 40,
50 years and the money isn't there.
They're guaranteed that money from this
pension fund system and it's not there.
What are they going to do? It's a
trillion dollars short. That's a state
obligation. Why would anybody hear
something like that and think giving
politicians more money is a good idea?
These people are so fiscally
irresponsible. They're fiscally
illiterate.
There is that
it's pretty clear to me that in New York
and California it'll be 60 plus% taxes.
And you know, if you were living in a
perfect society that appreciated it and
you had this incredible safety, you had
extraordinary schools and the roads and
the public transit,
>> everything worked.
>> Yeah. Like Japan,
>> you'd pay 60%, you would be ecstatic.
>> Yeah. You'd be like, "Okay, I mean, it's
a lot, but hey, this is a pretty great
place to live." If you're paying that
and people are breaking into your home
and there's nine overdoses a day, you're
like, "Wait a second." And then on top
of that, by the way,
>> and they're seizing your private
property now.
>> Seizing your property.
>> They're seizing your property. And by
the way, they don't care about you when
it when you look at the laws. I was just
talking to some law enforcement people.
>> City's using your money to give homeless
people vodka. It's just
>> Well, I mean, if it was tequila, I mean,
I have a good tequila brand we could
give to the homeless. Maybe we can make
a deal.
>> Yeah.
>> Shout out to all at Gaya coming to you.
Uh to delivery is happening right now.
Um, in all seriousness, I was talking to
some security folks um and was talking
to my security guy in Cal who's a in
California and um in California, not
only do they not have the castle
doctrine, they've replaced the castle
doctrine where you can like defend your
home if somebody comes into it with your
gun uh and protect your family and your
property.
Now you have to have this um duty to
flee. So you have to be able to run out
of your home with your family as opposed
to defend your family. So they literally
are telling the criminals, "Hey, listen.
If you break into somebody's home in
California, don't worry about getting
shot. You they're going to have to run
out or else they're in the wrong." Like
this is deranged. The the inmates have
literally taken over the asylum. They
they have taken over the asylum. I I
realized this two years ago and I pulled
the rip cord. Some Elon realized it six
years ago when he tried to build a
factory. He pulled the rip cord. You
guys are realizing it now. Everybody's
realizing this. New York uh the hedge
fund guys in New York and in Jersey and
Connecticut. They realized it. What?
>> Only Hollywood guys. I know a bunch of
Hollywood guys leaving.
>> Yeah. I literally this producer, one of
the major producers who has produced
billions of dollars worth of films came
here last year. I met him at a football
game. He said, "Tell me everything." I
told him everything. He moved here. He
moved here. He's going to start making
movies here. And he is one of the top
top I won't say who he is, but you know
his films because his partner who is an
incredibly high-profile comedian, like
amongst the highest profile in history,
where they make films together, he moved
here. Why? He he doesn't want to live in
LA and risk his family's life to an home
invasion and and the house burning down
because they don't fill water in the
reservoir. I mean, guys,
>> hopefully not everyone realizes it cuz I
need to sell my house to someone.
>> Good luck. You'll be okay. You'll be
okay. There's a Chinese billionaire.
>> Actually, you know, you know who you'll
be able to sell your house.
>> There's no billionaires left in
California.
>> It's whoever uh the politicians are that
are able to aggregate power and money in
the socialist.
>> Gavin will buy your house and turn it
into a home.
>> Gavin's gone. You guys are going to look
You guys are going to look back on Gavin
and realize he was the most uh
>> upstanding moderate governor that
California had in modern era and
suddenly we're going to be like what the
>> and I think that's a great place to stop
it, boys.
>> We will be doing a couple of episodes
between now and the end of the year and
uh yeah, no weeks off. Hopefully we get
to see each other over the holidays.
I'll see you Saxs uh and you as well
Jimath and Freedberg shortly. Oh, by the
way, the president just signed an
executive order reclassifying marijuana
from schedule one to schedule three.
>> Schedule one to schedule three. Okay. Uh
that's something Obama wanted to do in
the second term and never did. So,
>> I think it's a good thing. I mean,
schedule one is like heroin. You know,
it just never made sense to treat it the
same as heroin. You know, I know a lot
of people aren't thrilled about
marijuana. It's not great when people
are in the
>> I don't like marijuana, but I I agree
with this.
>> It's not heroin.
I mean it would be on I think most
people intellectually would put it on
the same level as alcohol, right?
>> I just want it studied so that we can
have toxicity labels. That's the big
thing that I want because like if these
kids
>> Yeah.
>> That's the most important thing is put a
tox label on these things so you know
what you're taking.
>> It's the the strength of these things
over the last 50 years has changed
dramatically. And there are Yeah. There
there there are these um shards they
create of this like incredibly intense
THC that will make you like go
psychotic. Like it's really dangerous.
So the smoking a joint from our youth is
very different than smoking these like
resins and stuff that they've created
apparently that are like a 100 times the
potency 200 times potency and they can
put you in a psychotic state. Really
dangerous folks.
>> Oh that's that's where like the FDA
should regulate it. More like alcohol or
something. 100%. Much better process,
especially since kids are getting messed
up. Yeah.
>> All right, everybody. Another amazing
episode of your favorite podcast in the
world, the all in pockets. Love you.
>> Happy holidays, everybody. Merry
Christmas.
>> Happy Hanukkah. Merry Christmas.
>> Happy Hanukkah. Christmas, whatever
you're into.
>> Let your winners ride.
Rainman David
>> and it said we open sourced it to the
fans and they've just gone crazy with
it.
>> Queen of
besties are
my dog taking a notice driveway.
Oh man, my habitasher will meet up.
>> We should all just get a room and just
have one big huge orgy cuz they're all
just It's like this like sexual tension
that we just need to release somehow.
>> Your feet.
Waiting to get Mercury's are going all
in.