Heat. [music]
[music]
Heat.
Perfect.
[music]
Hello everyone.
Amazing.
I've created a leading [music]
indicators of what countries have their
ingredients project the next 10 years
growth rate. India is best. I think
India over the next 10 years [music] has
all the ingredients to really be the
strongest growth rate and and an
improvement. [music]
A
>> youngster in India who's 25 years old,
how does he make money?
>> Two things I'd suggest. First, play the
game. Find a game that you [music] love
and then be around people who are pros
at playing the game so you can chat
about it. That's a good path.
How do you view crypto and the world of
Bitcoin or even like stable coin? Tell
me this. If you were to back
>> You got to give me one question at a
time. Yeah.
>> Okay, let's do Bitcoin and then we're
stable coin. [music]
Hi Rey. Uh thank you for doing this. As
a trader myself, I've been trading now a
long time about 21 years. I think there
will be a lot I can learn from you and
many others back home in India like me
can also learn from you. If I can
contextualize the audience we are
talking to today, they are young Indian
wannabe entrepreneurs
uh investors, want to be traders, people
who want to make a living in the stock
markets. I would say between the ages of
18 and 30.
>> Wonderful. That's that's exactly um the
group that I would like to speak to at
this stage in my life because I've
learned a lot and I would just want to
pass what I've learned along to those
people. So, thank you for allowing me to
do that.
>> No, thank you for doing this.
Everybody knows you, but if we could go
through like the big events of your life
and very briefly just to set context
again, could you tell us how you look at
your life from the very beginning from
when you were younger up until today?
>> Okay.
Um, my dad was a jazz musician. My mom
uh was a sort of say it mom. Uh I was
raised in u I didn't have any brothers
or sisters.
Um
it was a loving family. Um it was um not
poor. Not there was lower middle class.
Um I
did jobs when I was young. Uh I one of
those jobs was catting for at a golf
course and because I cattied at a golf
course at the time when there was a
stock market. Boom. The people I cied
with I would have conversations with and
I took the money I earned $6 a bag. I
carried two bags $12 for a round. When I
got $50 I would put it in the stock
market. And so I started um playing
around in the stock market much like
you're describing our audience does. And
um the first stock I bought I bought
only because it was the only company I
ever heard of that was selling for less
than $5 a share. And I thought, well
then I can buy more shares, so if it
goes up, I'll make more money. Which of
course made no sense. But it was a
company that uh was about to go
bankrupt, but another company acquired
it and it tripled in value and I thought
this is easy. It's not easy, but I got
hooked on the markets at 12.
>> Do you think it's like that? I I often
think about this. There was a really
tiny when I was 17, I bought this
company called Marsoft, a defunct
software company in India and the share
price again doubled or tripled. The
first experience of the stock market.
The people who tend to continue are the
ones who get lucky. Do you think so?
>> I think positive reinforcement works.
Negative reinforcement. Sure.
>> If you lost money on your first trade,
you would never have done it. Maybe
>> probably, you know, you put your hand on
a hot stove and it takes How many times
do you do that and then you react to it?
So, I can't say for sure, but probably.
But I got into the game,
>> right?
>> It was a game and it was it's a great
game.
>> If you play it, you think of it as a
game and that if you play it well, that
pays you money.
>> Do you think the stock market has
emotion? Does it treat you a certain way
at the beginning?
>> I I think it's unemotional. We are
emotional
and we certainly have emotions. N that's
one of the reasons the way I learn to
invest
uh was to write down my criteria when I
was making a decision. Every time I'd
make a decision,
I would then think why am I making that
decision? And then I write down the
criteria and see how it would have
worked in the past. It took me a while
to do this
>> because of my experiences and also you
know when you're wrestling with
positions particularly a position that
goes against you. Yeah.
>> You know you're wondering am I missing
something and then how old do how long
do I hold that position and what do I
do? So emotions and intellect and lack
of perspective is a pom. So when you
have a decision rule that then you know
how it would have worked all through
time. Now you're just playing that
decision rule and it helps you know.
>> Did you trade on leverage at the very
beginning?
>> Um I didn't trade on leverage in the
beginning but I bought in the beginning
very early in my age I bought futures
cuz it wouldn't give me leverage.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. I decided very nobody traded
futures right.
>> Okay. there were no commodities. It just
very little. Okay. But I realized that
it would give me leverage.
>> And so I figured if I was going to be
good in the markets, I would want to do
have that leverage because I'd make more
money. So that's what drew me to.
>> Was it about four or five times
leverage?
>> Well, it was the futures contracts.
>> The margin requirement would be about 15
20%.
>> Yeah. And that would be a good demo,
>> right?
>> Odd one. Yeah. And what kind of
contracts were you trading in the very
beginning?
>> Well, then it was commodities,
>> right?
>> Okay. So, then it was um
um everything from precious metals to
cattle where I got really into grain and
uh livestock and
um you know those types of commodities.
So when I uh so my background okay you
wanted a couple of stories so I'll give
you the stories.
So I did this and I went to college and
then um what was a defining moment my
learning experience was um I the year I
graduated from college 1971
I clerked on the floor of the New York
Stock Exchange
>> and this is before I went to graduate
school so it was in the summer
>> and on August 15th 197 71, President
Nixon defaulted on his obligation, the
US's obligation to give gold paper
money.
>> You know, back then, gold was money. The
paper money was like checks in a
checkbook.
>> Did he default or did he say that he
will no longer back the dollar with
gold?
>> I don't know the difference. [laughter]
>> The way you say it, there was a promise
that you could bird in, take $35, get an
ounce of gold. Then he said, "You can't
take your $35 to get an ounce of gold."
So that to me is
>> and that was because of Vietnam and
going to the moon.
>> Well, because we were spending a lot
more. This is the thing through history.
>> Yeah,
>> we always have to look at this. We'll
get into this, I'm sure, but through
history back to the Old Testament and
everything, the years of Jubilee and so
on, it's when there is a lot of claims
on money and there's not enough money in
the bank.
>> Mhm. Okay. And that's happened
throughout history. So we have a central
bank that was that started in 1913
and the idea was it had gold and there
were many more claims on the gold than
there was gold in the bank because for
the same reason you borrow a lot of
money and when you borrow a lot of money
and a lot more one man's debts are
another man's assets. So they're holding
it expecting that they can get the money
and then they want the money but there's
not enough money. And that was the
Federal Reserve Bank's problem in 1971.
>> What is money?
>> What is money? Money is money is a
medium of exchange and a storehold of
wealth. Very important to to recognize
it as a storehold of wealth. What is a
storehold of wealth? Okay. So when you
um in India many people realize that
gold is a storehold of wealth. Now what
we uh and then we p it's the perception
of money
>> that it can be used as a medium of
exchange that I can go around the world
>> and I can go from one country to another
and I can turn it in and get value to be
able to buy things. Right? So that is
what it is. Um and through history, gold
has been the most used money, most
accepted around the world. Um you know,
then when uh but it's the perception of
it. And so when we think about let's say
money as we commonly think about it,
which is fiat money, then that
>> but there's a difference there, right?
Like gold is a asset which is not a
liability on anyone else's book.
>> Exactly. It's a money.
>> It's the only money. Well, maybe it's
not. We could talk about crypto is
crypto, but yes, gold is the only money
that you can have and nobody has to give
you anything to have it.
>> Yeah. Other money, all other money is
dependent on somebody giving you
something. Okay? Whether they give you
and so it's unique in that it's
confiscation risk is less than others.
So that's why one of the reasons gold is
unique but it is also back to your main
point main point it is a widely
recognized storehold of wealth that I
could bring around the world and I could
uh use it and it's particularly
important in um that it is not deflate
uh you can't deflate its value but you
can't print it you create more of it and
then it also in order to hold its
>> I have a personal question here I hold a
lot of gold I for a long time have kept
10% of my asset base in gold. U the
thing I wonder with gold is while it
can't be replicated today. I mean there
are people who are talking it about it
as a byproduct of fusion and how they
will create it like they did lab grown
diamonds. I I don't want to extrapolate
that far.
But with gold isn't it based on faith?
Isn't it a bit like religion? Because
gold inherently I get that it's a great
place to store value but does gold have
enough utility in isolation?
>> I money doesn't have much utility
generally speaking right if you're
carrying around cash
it's paper it doesn't have much utility.
So I don't think it's utility. I think
you got to get out of the utility
perspective of gold. Um every go every
thing that's money could be a risk. Does
it stay money? So for example in the
history of gold when there were great
discoveries of gold then the value of
gold is affected by the quantity of
those discoveries and if they could
replicate gold or like they'd been
replicating diamonds then that becomes a
risk of gold. So there are all risks to
all monies and that are of a similar
nature in terms of uh replicating the
the supply of them or also um the
acceptance of them as a money. You know
there became um gold fell out of fashion
>> as a money and bonds fell into fashion.
But the historic thing to know is that
throughout history there is always the
temptation uh when when when you uh
there's a fiat money which easily could
be produced and then there's the
temptation of the interest rate.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay. Gold doesn't have an interest
rate.
>> Okay. No interest rate
>> in India it does.
>> Oh gold has an interest rate.
>> Uh so India doesn't produce very much
gold of our own. we end up importing a
lot of the gold. So to be fiscally
prudent, the government has this plan
where if you buy sovereign gold bonds
from the government, digital gold bonds,
>> yeah, you get a you get that ain't
>> gold,
>> but you're also able to monetize
physical gold because you can lend it
out for a certain percentage.
>> But you're still dealing with credit
risk.
>> Okay?
>> So what you're getting paid for is
credit risk, right? So it's not gold.
It's a promise to get your gold back,
>> right? Then that's what money was. And
that's why it would have an interest
rate. You have an interest rate that on
the promise to get your gold back.
That's what everybody believed. And
that's the great trick through history.
The great trick of history and everybody
believed it back then for a long time is
I if I hold the promise to get the gold
then I will get an interest rate and I
could always turn my money in for gold.
So why won't I hold the promise to get
the gold and get an interest rate on it
rather than to hold the actual gold
which wouldn't give me an interest rate.
And that was the trap and that is always
the trap. So when you look at it today,
let's say and you you think okay I I
think it's just arbitrage. Um let's say
I can hold gold that gives me no
interest rate. I can hold Swiss Franks
which don't give me much interest rate.
I can hold US dollars what which will
give me depending on the maturity but
let's say will give me a 4% interest
rate. My basic question is if gold goes
up by more than 4%. Go gold has to go up
by more than 4% then I'm better holding
gold and if it goes up by less than 4%.
Then I'm better holding the bond uh that
that will operate. So I keep thinking
about though you know that question and
the world keeps thinking about that
question.
>> Mhm. When I think of store of value, I
also think of
gold, money, US dollar, whatever
currency be it. If I own equity in
something very basic like a farm for
example, which is producing a certain
good, that makes it more funible almost,
right?
>> All assets
>> are valued as their appreciation in
price
and their yield. the yield that you're
getting
and the price change and that's a total
return. And so all assets you compare on
that basis. If you're holding a farm,
>> same deal. Okay. Uh in other words, what
is the yield on that farm from holding
it?
>> Generally more than 4%.
>> No, I'm not getting into the specifics.
I'm getting into the mechanics. So when
looking at the markets as a whole, what
I do is I just compare everything.
Right. Okay? Because all I want to do is
I want to essentially borrow or be short
>> those that will have the lower returns
relative to those that will have the
higher returns. So it's constantly
calculations in that way however you get
there. And that's true of your farm as
it is on the other. But I think that the
farm or illquid assets should have to
give me a higher return because I'm not
going to have the choice of easily
selling that farm and buying that farm.
Whereas that choice that flexibility
that liquidity
>> but I'm talking about the public equity
of a farm farming company.
>> Okay. Then you are dealing with the
public liquidity. I didn't know that.
But yeah in terms of that. So then
there's no liquidity premium. Still that
same calculation. Okay. What is the
yield and then what is the price change
relative? What is that? That'll be my
return. And what is that relative to the
other things I could be in? And
basically you start to think when you
think of leverage. You start to think uh
okay it doesn't have to be about zero.
Zero means like no leverage. when you
start to think okay I can be if if the
lesser returning asset
can become a liability meaning I can
then borrow it and get higher here then
I want to get that spread and that's how
I think of the issue of using leverage
and then the issue is how do you deal
with the risk but the ri the risk is not
something that is that like zero
leverage and it's a black and white
thing. It's a continuous thing. Look, I
should say the following. There are two
important ways to invent to invest.
Okay. The first is
what if you can't beat the market?
>> Mhm.
>> Most people can't beat the market.
>> So when they start off, everything isn't
a bet. It's like if I don't know what to
bet on, what is my portfolio? And so you
should start with what is that mix of
assets if you're not a trader and so on.
um what is the right mix and that's for
example why a lot of Indians hold gold
or a lot of people hold gold they don't
want to bet but they just saying that'll
be a sold of wealth
>> once you have that portfolio that
portfolio should be a well diversified
portfolio that assumes you can't market
time
>> then there's the question can you market
time okay
>> so you're asking me a market timing
question I want to distinguish it I
don't think most people should play a
market timing question. And when you're
asking me my t market timing, I view
that question with a lot of
responsibility because maybe I'm right
and maybe I'm wrong. I wanted to preface
answering your question with that
explanation and then I'll go back to
answering your question. I money is debt
and debt is money. What I mean money So
here's mechanics. You're holding a debt
instrument. What you're holding is a
promise to deliver some money. Mhm.
>> And what that money is worth will
determine what the value of what you're
holding is. Okay. You're really you're
holding when they hold that debt, you're
holding money that if it's devalued,
you're going to be sorry. Okay? And
money is debt. And what I mean by that,
when you're holding your money, you're
holding it in a debt instrument. So
money is debt and debt is money. And so
now I'm when I'm answering your
question, to me there's too much debt
and we're producing it too much. And so
when I'm looking at that and I'm looking
at around the world and I'm not just
looking at it in the United States, I'm
looking at it in the UK and in France
and in China and in most countries.
We're producing too much debt. That
means I don't want that kind of money.
So when because I don't want that kind
of money, I look at well that's why I
prefer and have been preferring the
holding of gold to that kind of money. I
think when you think about your
portfolio, you should start to think
again if you don't have how any um what
should you be holding? I think
individuals or if you look at the
quality of money and like gold let's
call it you want to stay I would say I
want to stay out of fiat currencies and
I want to stay out of those things on a
tactical bet not on the strategic asset
allocation bet when I do that um I'm I
think to myself um okay what should I
have and an individual and most
investors should have between five and
15% of their portfolio in a a gold or an
alternative money. Now, it depends what
other assets they have in the portfolio.
>> Even if they're starting today to build
a portfolio after the gold appreciation
of the last year, I
>> I think that they they have to stop even
thinking about the appreciation and
market timing as a starting point. You
have to say what amount am I going to
hold?
>> Okay, what is that right amount? and
it'll be beat. So the answer to the
question is yes, forget about and we can
get into the pricing of gold or what it
might do and what it might not do. But
still you okay I need to hold that
amount because that amount is the right
amount. If you were to go through a
portfolio optimization and you were to
say what um through a mechanical
portfolio optimization and you say what
is my mix of assets to create the right
portfolio. If you're holding stocks and
you're holding other assets because gold
gold is over a period of time a
lowturning asset class like cash. It'll
produce it has produced and for logical
reasons it produces about a 1.2% a year
real return. That's that's that's a low
real return, but it is highly um
diversifying because when the other
parts of the portfolio do very badly,
let's say be because of certain things
like we're talking about stagflation,
you print money and all debt issues,
then the gold does very well. So, it
also has a diversification benefit in
terms of the portfolio. For those
reasons, it is the most fundamental
money that we know of and it is at the
same time an effective diversifier to
other things. That'll get you to that 50
between five and 15% of the portfolio.
>> While we're speaking about currency, how
do you view crypto and the world of
Bitcoin?
>> Um, Bitcoin is limited in supply and its
perception of money. It is a form of
money. It it's perceived as money as a
storehold of wealth that is unlikely to
be significantly held by central banks
and many others because of a number of
problems it has. It can't transactions
could all be followed in Bitcoin. One
can monitor what the transactions are.
governments can monitor what the
transactions are and governments can
interfere with those transactions just
like we talked about earlier when we
talked about you know gold is the only
asset that you can have that they can't
uh mess with and control you've got it
okay that's not true of Bitcoin and then
there are other issues in Bitcoin like
if we talked about the possibility would
somebody make uh synthetic gold like
they would make um uh synthetic diamond
diamonds um as as a risk. Well, in terms
of Bitcoin being cracked, broken, all
sorts of things and controlled, it has
those issues. Okay. So, that's how I
look at Bitcoin. You're not bullish.
>> I have a little No, no. I'm I'm bearish
on fiat currencies
>> and bearish on uh
>> So, when I look at the world, I'm I'm
just trying to say then I say, what do I
hold?
>> Okay. So, I hold a little bit of
Bitcoin. I have a little bit of Bitcoin,
but for me, it's not as attractive as um
uh gold for the reasons you asked me my
thoughts. Those are my thoughts about
Bitcoin.
>> A stable coin um is attached to the fiat
currency. So, it goes down like the fiat
currency goes down and it doesn't give
an interest rate and and they're toying
around with what whether it gives
interest rates or not, but there's not a
model that I've seen. So, so far um it's
used largely for immediate quick
transactions and not a storehold of
wealth but immediate quick transactions
and it may be an efficient way to have
that but it's not my storehold of wealth
yet I don't see the merit of it. So if I
were to build your portfolio array of
storehold of wealth, just that
component, let's say 5 to 15 goes to
gold. How much goes to uh you said you
have a little bitcoin. What percentage
would that be?
>> I'm not going to give you what I've got,
but I'll give you just general
guidelines. Um it depends on
um the type of equities.
You you can't talk about equities as
equities. Mhm.
>> Because they're too divergent.
>> Mhm.
>> As we're seeing for example now, it's so
contrary uh the magnificence of it and
and AI and tech is such a dominant
thing. So in order to think about
portfolio construction,
you have to think what type of equities,
where do you hold those equities?
>> I'm not talking about equity. I'm
talking about the assets that you hold
with relatively lower risk like gold and
treasury and bitcoin which is not you
taking a bet on a particular industry
but someplace to park money. What else
would you
>> I see. In other words, you're you're not
asking whether there's equities in the
portfolio or bonds or what country or
anything like that. You're just saying
that piece of equities. Okay. Then you
think about
um that on that storehold of wealth, you
start to think about what that nature of
that thing is. There aren't many. Some
might say there are gems. Some might say
there are works of art. I mean basically
when they say these things they're going
through criteria which is uh can I move
them around?
>> Um are they storeholds of wealth that
are recognized in different places?
They're not like real estate. Real
estate is something that's nailed down
in a location. It's easy to tax. It's
not transferable and so on. So, it's
the, you know, th those kinds of things,
>> right? Do you think real estate should
be taxed? Like we have very low property
taxes.
>> I think I think what should be taxed?
I mean like if I was to create up
priority list, first tax this, last tax
this and so on. And I would say in real
estate, um I think there's the question
of what does it mean for the economy or
what does it mean for those who are
being taxed or what does it mean for
those who are taxing? I think the
practical aspect of real estate in terms
of taxing is because the individual
owner of real estate can't take it with
them. It is a very practical asset asset
to tax for the government
>> because they they can always
>> tax that and you can't take it with you
versus the other. So I think uh while uh
you know what should be taxed is a
dependent on who you're asking should
it's a for the government it's a very
effective thing to tax for an individual
um it's another in terms of its economic
um impact I think it's fine to tax real
estate there's nothing you got to tax
something I I think now do you want to
have such a tax burd burden on any one
thing that it's crushing to to the
economy. Then just generally taxes I
would say you know I want to spread them
out and then I would tax things that are
harmful you know like um what I I don't
know if they call them sin taxes. Okay.
If I don't know maybe cigarettes or you
know um I don't know those things or and
then some things that are harmful and
you the least things you would tax are
those things that are helpful.
>> Yeah. I make a case for taxing real
estate because I think a lot of the
benefits of corruption and the bad
money, the black money in a way sits in
real estate and that might be a good way
to bring it into the tax system.
>> Okay.
>> Personally, if you go back to your life,
you spoke about going to college after
you began trading, after you were a
caddy and after.
Do you think there are roles today like
the role of a caddy where you work
around influential people and you can
learn by virtue of being in their
proximity?
>> It's always it's always of course great
to be about around smart people if they
don't want to be an entrepreneur
whatever it is uh be around a smart
entrepreneur and talk. Yeah, that's
great. Sure.
>> What was caddy the job of a caddy back
then? What do you think it would be
today?
>> Well, they do the same. And they can't
they carry bags or they put them on golf
carts and but they walk there and it if
you're walking with people who are it's
an entrepreneur or if you were a
physicist and you're walking with want
to be a physicist and you're talking
with a physicist
>> any suggestion of other jobs like the
caddy job today cuz
>> whatever gets what whatever gets you two
things I'd suggest
>> first play the game if you have an
opportunity to play the game you can
play the Well, the one of the beauties
of the markets is it doesn't take a big
portfolio to play the game. I I had $50.
I went into the game and I and because
the market pieces can be broken up into
small sizes. You can almost play the
game the same as a huge investor can
play the game. Ease of access, you've
got that in terms of those. So, the game
that you get into at an early age will
influence you a lot. If I look at um
like age 12, I'll give you that example.
There's some people who say the
psychologists will say prior to 12
people learn differently um because
puberty at the age of puberty prior to
that you learn if you're learning a
language or learning a sport or learning
things. Anyway, the earlier you start
learning the better it is, the more
internal learning that you have. And so
play play the game, whatever it is. Bill
Gates um and a lot of uh the you know
key tech people like to play gaming.
They were in gaming and they would hack
the games and they would play in the
computer and that'll affect them. So
play the game, find a game that you love
and ideally one that makes money. Wow.
If you can do those two things together,
that's a terrific thing. Play the game
and then be around people who are pros
at playing the game so you can chat
about it. That's a good path.
>> Leverage in speculation, especially
around equity markets.
Across the world, many people seem to be
coming down on qualify a investor more
before you allow him to speculate, buy
futures or options. U
do you think that should happen or
should a young kid who's 18 and has that
$50 be allowed to speculate?
These are questions about I mean they're
they're broader questions about um
being taken advantage financially versus
learning experiences. I I don't mind any
kind of risk something that becomes a
tolerable amount of risk. That's
different from exploitation. Okay. And
so, um, I think that it's incumbent, it
should be incumbent on anybody who's
selling any investment product to be,
uh, dealing with it at a certain age to
be thinking about am I exploiting that
person or not. Okay. So, that's but
that's a balance for regulators to deal
with,
>> right?
>> Uh, do you have a view on uh, prediction
markets? Like I know Shane Shane
>> I like them. I like them.
>> Yeah.
>> Shane and Taric are friends of mine. and
they both live in New York. Kalshi and
uh poly market u in the future does a
lot of what is happening on stock
markets move there cuz you can speculate
on just about anything
>> mostly different act events to bet on
and I think events affect companies but
they're two different things so I would
say um it'll be something to speculate
on um but and It' be something that
smart people may use as a hedging device
against owning an equity. Like if this
event happens, that event that you can
speculate on, and that might have an
adverse effect to the stock I'm holding,
there'll be all sorts of engineering and
so on. I would imagine you'd see
something like that happening. Um, but
uh, we'll see, you know.
>> So, you would use it like a leading
indicator to make stock decisions.
>> I not a leading indicator. I wouldn't
view it as a leading indicator. I mean,
you might think about it. It gives you
information, but um uh it's a vehicle to
speculate. It's a vehicle to use to
hedge. Um it gives you some notion of
what those who are, uh speculating on
it, um is there are certain things that
I'd like to try to get across here in
our interview that I'd like to, you
know, what what is the difference
between wealth and money? Mhm.
>> There's certain things that if I can get
across to your audience, I'd like to get
across.
>> Yeah. Do you want to go wealth and money
first?
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> Bubbles and wealth and money.
>> People are not used to dealing with the
difference in them and it's very
important. Wealth can easily be created
the way we [clears throat] account for
wealth. For example, if you're you start
a company
and
let's say you want to make a unicorn,
you sell $50 million worth of it. You
value it at a billion dollar. You're now
a billionaire and it counts in wealth as
a billion dollars and there's but nobody
would pay a billion dollars for that
issue combined. Okay? And that's a lot
of what's happening now with wealth and
and and if you look at the 1920s bubbles
or you look at those what you see in one
way or another is that wealth goes up
and people feel wealthy but the wealth
isn't worth anything if you don't sell
it convert it into money to spend.
Right? So people should know that okay
that when they have this wealth they
perceive they have the wealth and so on
you it's not worth anything unless you
can uh convert it into money and spend
it other than it's utilitarian value but
it's not worth what it what it is and
that's how bubbles are created the
mechanics of how that bubbles are
created in one way or another that
happens okay then there comes along the
need for money so what happened and how
does that work for one reason or
another. Somebody's got to get that
money that money who and they have
wealth. So they sell wealth in order to
get money and then the bubble comes
down. So if you look at the 20s and
there or you look at any of the bubbles,
the Japanese bubble or you look at the
2000 bubble and so on, you can see this
dynamic because it can be created
without money. Money is the means that
settles transactions. It's very
different from credit. Okay? When you
get credit to buy something, um you have
an obligation to deliver money. But when
you get money and you buy something, you
have no obligation to deliver anything.
You've paid for it. You've settled your
transaction. So now when I when we look
at this, we have right now a very high
ratio of wealth to money. And this is
particularly important now. Okay. And
there's a and we have a very large also
wealth gaps and values gaps. But when
you have such a large wealth gap and and
you have populism of the left and the
right and so on and you have the notion
of wealth taxes, you can have wealth tax
as wealth taxes come in. What? And and
the wealth is so large relative to the
money. um if you're not taxing wealth uh
wealth then people can get very wealthy
and no money can be raised for for the
taxes. So there's a real pressure to tax
wealth and if you tax wealth then people
have to sell in order to get the money
to pay the taxes and that creates a
dynamic that can pop a bubble. So in my
opinion, we're in a bubble, okay, by
various measures of it being in a bubble
and uh and people feeling very wealthy,
but you have that vulnerability. So that
is largely the dynamic of when we see
these wealth booms and then the wealth
bumps. I wanted to convey that. Okay. So
that's the first thing I want to convey.
>> Is there a way to calculate wealth to
money ratio which you
>> Yes, I do. I do. Right. wealth to money
ratio right now in the United States is
about 8 12:1 and and so on and when you
look at it um and then also then there's
what it's in the stock market um is is
right now about 3 to one and uh and
that's very high if you were to go back
to 1929 or 2000 it's at about the same
level uh as it was in those times
>> is it higher today than 2008 and 2000
>> well 2000 2000 was the peak.
>> Mhm. How much was it?
>> Uh same same as today. The same same uh
same levels. If you take 1929, 2000 and
now it's all right now. If you look at
that chart, you can you can see that
chart. So, um we have a lot of wealth
and a lot of equity wealth relative to
money. Do you think it could be possible
that tomorrow wealth tax is collected in
equity and not money?
>> No. Because they have to spend it and
they have to pay it. In other words, the
liability that it's going to fund can't
be paid by I'm going to give you a piece
of my farmland. You know, you get a
piece of the farmland.
>> The government gets a piece of the
farmland.
>> Yeah, that's what you're suggesting. I
don't think that's realistic. You get a
piece of the farmland,
>> right? [laughter]
>> Okay. You're not going to feed people in
inner cities with a piece of the
farmland,
>> right? If that were to happen, people
will have lesser incentive to work on
the farm cuz eventually the government
will own too much.
>> I don't think so. Um, so I want to talk
about the five big forces that that
drive things. Yeah. If I can. Um, first
there is a debt, money, economy, markets
dynamic. Credit creates buying but it
creates debt. And when it creates debt,
there's an obligation to pay back. And
then the and and so how that dynamic
works. The second big force happens
simultaneously is the internal political
force. You experience it India, every
country does, we experience here.
There's an element here of that
political force that there is left and
right. In other words, the rich and the
poor and the conflict and how to run a
country and so on. So that political
force and there's a cycle uh just as
there's a debt cycle that means that you
cannot increase your debt past a certain
point and that changes that monetary
order cycle lasts something like a
lifetime. Um and that that's the debt
cycle. There is a political cycle that
goes with that that has the left and the
right and the political and we are in
the middle of that. So the nature of our
governance system and the nature of
democracy, the risk of do you we're past
the point of um saying that we'll abide
by the rules. Okay, it's a it that when
you have populism of both sides, it's a
win at all cost type of approach. Will
you accept election results? Can you can
the government compromise? Can it govern
in that way? That political cycle is
number two and it matters a lot that all
these cycles relate to each other.
Number three is the geopolitical order,
the world order. In other words, we came
out of 1945. You come out of the you end
a war and then the dominant powers
determine how the world order works, how
who has what power, what the rules are.
that was dominated by the United States
because of the power it had and then you
have changes in relative power the
emergence of China the um relative
decline of the United States India's
role and other places role that world
order has changed that world order has
gone from a world order that it was a
multilateral world order sort of with
rules like the United Nations and the
world trade organization and the world
uh health organization and the world
this is you know the world bank and the
world this and the world that in terms
of multilateral governance and that is
over. Okay. So we no longer have that
kind of a world order. We have a world
order which is dominated by uh power
power struggles and as we deal with
that. So those three cycles, that money
cycle, that debt money cycle, that
internal order and disorder cycle, that
international world order cycle, they
tend to coincide. And throughout
history, when you have that that
convergence, you almost have a perfect
storm of that. The fourth influence
through time has been climate um acts of
nature. Droughts, floods, and pandemics
have killed more people than wars and
changed more orders. And number five
always through history is man's
inventiveness particularly of new
technologies. So everything that we're
we would ever talk about in the markets
in the economy will fall under those
things practically everything. And it's
the inter relationship of those things
and the arc through history that one
needs to see in order to understand
what's going on. So my basic view is
that there are many things that happen
over and over through history that
haven't happened in our lifetimes that
are very educational, very valuable in
being making decisions.
>> I'm going to ask you a question Ray. How
does a youngster, this is a very candid,
pragmatic question. How does a youngster
in India who's 25 years old say his name
is Nikil and he's living in India in
Bombay
u how does he make money using all this
information and framework cuz that's his
objective
play the game
>> how do I use this information to play
the game better I I think I think
there's cerebral learning and there's
visceral learning you know and um so I
can tell we could talk like this, but we
are it's a different thing. Once you
start to get into playing the game,
whatever the game is, little
entrepreneur on um street corner selling
something. Okay, that's you play the
money game.
>> Okay, whatever way you play the money
game. Maybe it's in the public markets,
maybe it's in you buy a little piece of
real estate or you have a hot dog stand.
I don't know what it is, but you play
the game. And as you start to play the
game, you'll start to learn the
fundamentals of the game. You, and we
talked about this, be around people who
also play the game. So while you're
playing it, and you will learn through
your experiences and your reflections
and the help of other people.
I think everybody wants to play the game
and they're attempting to play the game.
But what would be really cool is if we
can get an insight from you of how to
play the game. Like if I were to be
looking to begin today, should I look at
is value in public markets, in private
markets? Should I be
>> I I I I think it's more like the
opposite. What happens is
you find your thing.
>> Okay. There are many different games.
Look, if you look around you, there are
many different games. You know, it's um
I have my grandchildren um sell um hot
cider in the winter in a park and then
what and then they understand capital
formation. I have to buy the f the the
flask. I have to buy the table. Okay,
that's capital formation. Then they
understand when they go out that okay if
I can uh produce it what's my
incremental cost unit cost for producing
it relative to I I could sell it at this
I have a margin of this then they
understand margin and then they
understand that they make money when
that overcomes their capital cost okay
the playing the game they start to think
about that way then they start speaking
with others gee can I where can I get
the cider cheaper or whatever and and so
on. So there are all these games around
you, okay? And start to play. Then
you'll ask the questions, then you'll
dig and so on. Uh or yeah, you can find
somebody or help you. They might say,
"Hey, here's this little job that you
can do." Whatever it is, it is that
little germination that then creates
um mo empires that that that's the
process of going from wherever you are
in India to or wherever you are for me
catting on a golf course in the United
States that's the process that allows
that to grow and develop over a period
of time. It's very helpful to understand
your nature. Okay, people have different
pulls. Some people are more riskaverse.
Some people like to pay attention to the
big picture. Others
will handle risk. Others will pay
attention to the details. What is your
nature? So I created online, it's free
online a test called principles you. I
recommend you take it. everybody take it
and they'll look at you and through
answering questions you'll learn about
yourself and if you also have other
people that you know you have
relationships you'll look at them to
help to identify their nature what is
their inclinations and I think that what
what really is the journey in life is to
try to know about your nature and find
it connection to the right path right so
there are many right paths for all your
audience I want you to know your nature
and try to match it up with what the
right path is for you.
>> Um, for the trader in me, uh, if I were
to go back in time and be 18 years old
again,
if I were to specifically ask you,
you you model people a lot in the sense
that you psychoanalyze them. You let you
have them go through different kind of
testing to figure out what psychology is
suited to what. What works for a trader,
Ray? What makes a trader successful?
>> There are many way when when you use the
word trader, it has an implication of a
certain way of operating that may that
is only a small percentage of the total
way of investing. Right? So, uh it's the
person who um the it could be buys this
from here and sells it from here. It
could be the form of you know you buy a
bracelet here and you sell a bracelet
here and you do it or it could be a
stock trader and so on so forth and that
implies like buy sell and so on. There
are many other ways. I think you have to
if you're understanding let's say
investing then you have to understand
the various ways of converting one thing
to another thing and making a profit and
that's why I give the example of the
cider case and and so on uh for being
able to do that. Uh a trader I say think
biases it too much to the guy who's
flipping. But I think for this example,
let's say what is the archetype of a
trader, bar, investor that would help
him succeed psychologic.
>> First,
you're going to go into it and you're
going to get hooked on it like getting
hooked on a game. Okay? And you're not
going to know anything. And then through
those experiences, what you need to do
is be curious to understand mechanics.
Okay? What are the cause effect
relationships? What are the things that
make the market go up or down so that
you can in whatever it is whether you're
a day trader or whether you're investor
you have to get into the mechanics and
you have to learn the mechanics right
and through that experience and you if
you think and you're curious and you
could research then you can do that. I
am creating a platform that anybody can
use to help them do that. In other
words, there's information and the way
you make decisions is your brain brings
in information and it puts it through
criteria that determine action. Okay,
that's how the brain works. That's all
the decisions. And so you have to learn
what are uh what is the criteria that
are and the criteria is cause effect
relationships because causes happen
before effects. And if you understand
cause effect relationships and you
understand the causes, you can bet on
the effects that it will be have
happening from that. So you have to be
curious and you have to be analytical to
understand those cause effect
relationships. You begin a journey.
Okay? Because if you're just gambling
and you don't understand the cause, you
won't have an edge. You need to have an
edge. Okay? And that is by knowing those
cause effect relationships and playing
your bet and how to organize your bets
so that there's a diversified group of
bets because the power of
diversification means that you can
greatly reduce risk without reducing
returns.
>> Right? What else do we have? Curiosity
understanding cause effect relationship
then
>> on uh being addicted to the game and
getting the best guidance you can get.
>> Right? How does one get guidance?
Oh, guidance is all around you. I'm part
of the guidance here today. There are
courses you can take. Okay. Once you
have the curiosity,
>> then you will dig and you will learn and
you will experiment.
>> Is that what worked for you? You still
>> you still come across as a very curious
person. It almost feels like you're
trying to answer the question of life.
>> Yeah.
>> That can't be answered in a way. I I'm
learning more every day,
>> right?
>> And I can't answer it all understand it
all, but I I understand a lot more and I
get a kick out of it. You know, um
Albert Einstein supposedly on his
deathbed was still trying to figure out
problems. Um I can imagine me doing that
because I love the problems and like to
learn, you know. Um, so yes, I have that
addiction to learning and and then uh
one of the great things about this game
is you bet on it and you get a score. So
you you can measure my performance down
to three decimal places and so on. Yeah.
>> Has this taken a lot of time changing
world order, the research, the amount of
effort that
>> Yes. But it's a passion,
>> right? What do you hope to achieve at
the other end? for me now.
>> Yeah.
>> My main thing is can I pass it along?
I've got a journey and I learn and I
love it and and all of that, but so it's
still a passion. But what I'm really
also trying to do as I approach this
stage in life is to pass it along. I
think there are three stages for me.
There are three stages in life. There's
the first stage where you're dependent
on others and you're learning. You go to
school, you're not really doing it.
You're just learning right and and you
have that dependency. Second stage is
you begin the second phase of life very
different stage is you're working and
you're trying to be successful and
others become dependent on you and in
that phase you're dealing with the real
world in terms of being able to do it.
It's no longer academic
>> and then you and you have your career
and I started Bridgewater um largest
hedge fund in the world. I started uh
the two-bedroom apartment. I ran it for
50 years and I'm then I passed it along.
Okay. Wow. What a great journey and I
learned a lot. Okay. But now I'm at a
phase in my life where what I want to do
I'm in the transition to my third phase.
And this in this transition I think that
there's an instinctual
uh desire to pass along what you've
learned to mentor. Why am I doing your
show? Okay. Because I have that desire.
So that's what's important to me.
>> And why do you have that desire? I'm
just asking you.
>> I think it's instinctual and it's
intellectual. It's instinctual almost.
Um we learn uh you know man's subliminal
understanding goes back millions of
years even though man only was 250,000
years old and so on because of what
becomes why do we love our raise our
children? Why do we do many things? It's
sub there's a lot of subliminal things
that enter into why we do things. Uh and
and then there's and it's intellectual.
What do I want to do? It's the most
valuable thing I can do. Um karma. Okay.
Karma. What goes around comes around. In
other words, that notion that so I I
believe it, I feel it, and I want to do
that. So, it's both intellectual and
emotional.
>> You've spoken about karma and meditation
and
Does that play a role in your investor
career? It makes you a better investor.
Oh,
>> it's a it's a these are dominant things.
Meditation has been the biggest source
of success that I um have. It's given me
an equinimity. It's given me um when you
transcend, I do transcendal meditation
this and that. When you transcend,
you're going into your subconscious. And
as you go into your subconscious, it
helps align your subconscious with your
conscious it brings back a creativity
bring back a flow because like
creativity if you go take a hot shower
and you you're relaxed and so on ideas
can come to you not much better perhaps
than if you try to muscle them out. So
meditation has played an important role
and then karma I I I believe in the the
reality
is um is that um by people mutually
helping each other or and not just
people but operating in a way that's
also helpful to nature and the world
that there is this greater um there's
this greater good and that what happens
is it's very functional because a little
things that won't take much for me to
help somebody else can make a life
difference to them and then they um when
they do something whether it's to me or
whether others you create an environment
like that you create a better
environment. So not only is it practical
it also has the effect of creating this
wonderful uh environment. um that you
look at um studies of history and you
find in studies of history uh what
brings about happiness and health past a
certain amount of money uh of basic
subsistence life there's no correlation
between the amount of money you have and
the amount of health happiness you have.
Um the greatest source of uh health
happiness excuse me across uh societies
is community. if you have a good
community and that's that's a source of
helping it and well-being. So I think
that these are laws of nature and
they're just reality when I look at them
that way. So yes, your your question was
does meditation and karma play a role
and it plays a role in everything. Yeah.
>> You spoke about community ray you're
spending time in Abu Dhabi for example.
U how do you find that place culturally?
>> Oh I love it. I uh I uh I uh I started
going there uh 32 years ago um because
their large wealth fund uh hired me and
I Bridgewater as an an investment. I
think that they understand karma. Um
each society has may call it different
things and so on but they understand um
the most important things and I'll and
I'll to create a a a successful society.
What it is required to to create a
successful society is basically three
things. If you do this well then you
have a successful society. The first is
teach your children, educate your
children well so that they are capable
of uh succeeding, earning money and so
on and living a life and also that uh
they're civil,
>> they understand civility.
Have them come out to a civil society in
which people work well together to make
good things happen.
and stay out of wars. Stay out of a
domestic war and stay out of an
international war. If you do those three
things, well, you will have a successful
society.
Okay. So now if when I look at the the
places you could almost look at that is
is there harmony?
Is there do you educate the children
well? And and do you have broad-based
prosperity?
In other words, that it works well for
most people,
right?
These are these are fundamentals. And
so, um, in the Gulf countries, uh,
particularly Abu Dhabi or the UAE and
Saudi Arabia and so on, even there's a
bedawin culture and so on that has
elements, uh, a lot of elements in in
those things. It exists in other places
in in various places.
success is their version of it. If you
go to um Asia and and you go to
Singapore, you go to China, they do it
in their confusion way. Okay, in terms
of harmony, how do you do harmony or
what is common prosperity? How do I um
make it that most people are benefiting
and that if you look at the
accomplishments within India in terms of
the development and and so when I say
that civility certain basics do you earn
more than you spend do you have a good
income statement and a good balance
sheet
okay these are basics you have these
basics you will have a successful not
I'm not saying not challenging but
you'll have a successful life and you
have a successful society.
>> You've had a very eclectic experience in
terms of China, Russia, Abu Dhabi,
Saudi. Uh how are they like
how are these people to talk to or can
you tell us something about them?
>> Well, the best uh um the best leaders
are reflective.
They go above it.
It being how the world evolves, where
they are in the cycles.
They understand human nature
and they care deeply about uh the
well-being of their people and they're
practical
that those are, you know, the
characteristics. So we have
conversations that are quite like this
and then you get into this particular
like what to do you know that you know
how do you deal with the conflict okay
so there's the conflict and like a a
general rule um be neutral
okay because if you look at the history
of wars and so on there are
winners of the wars losers of the wars
and neutral country countries.
The winners of the wars lose,
meaning they still get deeper in debt
and they have the consequences of the
wars. The losers of the wars get wiped
out. They lose everything. And the
neutral countries prosper from the wars.
Even that's how they accumulate money
and they don't have that problem. And so
it's it's always better to operate that
way. Now if you look at history and you
then say we apply it today.
>> Okay. So the conversations are like
that.
>> You've liked China for many years. I
think one of your kids went to live in
China. How do you see the global dynamic
playing out between China, America,
Russia, maybe you can opine on India as
well.
>> What do you think will happen next?
>> Now we have the changing world order.
the United States and other countries
have a different mentality about
fighting and so on so forth. There may
be that dynamic. So now you have a great
the change what power matters power in
all of this not it's not the rules of
the game it's not etiquette it is power
matters and that is the dynamic that we
have what's most important is how
healthy the country is each country more
important than the international if
you're strong you're strong and that's
the most so be strong and healthy and so
there uh the United States is going
through its challenges we could we
talked about that. We could talk about
that more. And then the and then uh
China is going through its challenges.
India is going through its challenges.
But how it goes through those challenges
to do the things that I just said are
effective to make an effective country
is the most important thing. So I don't
think we're going to there is a greater
risk that we can have um I'll say
military war. We are certainly in the
classic wars that happened before a
military war. We're in a trade war.
We're in a technology war. We're in a
geopolitical influence war. All of those
are in that and that's the dynamic
that's happening. If you're asking me uh
what it means, I think that it's
probably that they're not it's lower
risk of, you know, a big it can happen.
You have to be careful. But um I think
then it's how each country takes care of
their own and becomes strong and healthy
that matters most. And how do you think
the dynamics between them will change?
If I were to get more specific as a
proportion of world trade, who will do
better? Will it be 10 years forward?
Will it be China or the US?
>> I think
>> and also how does India fit into this?
What can we do better?
>> Um
I think the technology war is the most
important war that almost whoever wins
the technology war will win almost
everything. I think that right now you
have a situation where they recognize
that the each side can do harm to them
and actually is using techniques and so
there we're now in a period of time of
inter eliminate or reduce
interdependencies
that there's a list that both countries
or all countries are going on and they
say how can I squeeze the other what
dependency do they have that I can use
to squeeze the other or what dependency
do I have that might be used against me
to create squeezes and that's in capital
as well as trade and so on. So
everybody's now going to kind of this
independence and you know minimizing
interdependence because that's the smart
thing to do whatever because I will be
squeezed if I can be it'll be used
against me. So that's where we are on
that and then compete to become most
effective most powerful most rich most
powerful they're both doing that and
technology will be important. So I think
that over those periods of time you're
going to see um that dynamic. Um I think
China um they're ahead and behind in
different ways. Um for example, the
inventiveness of new chips um and the
most advanced chips. Um the United
States is a bit ahead is is ahead. Um
and then uh but the application to use
the chips whatever AI there is to be
able to integrate it into life and
making it for the society most
applications and most effect China's
ahead. I think that um India is um at a
wonderful
um arc in terms of um its circumstances,
its potential and and what and what it's
developing. And I think that um uh
President Modi is very much like uh Deng
Xiaoping for China. Um and what I mean
by that is that um he's creating changes
and when you are have a country that um
can build its infrastructure and can
build on that so that you and you don't
have much debt and you have a large
talented population in many ways um that
um um for these reasons I have um I've
created a u indicators leading
indicators of what countries ries have
their ingredients to project the next 10
years growth rate. India is best India
is going to have probably the has the
best fundamentals to have the best
growth rate in that because you're going
from not having enough money to having
that has infrastructure. You have to
build infrastructure. When you're
building infrastructure, when you're
creating this the things that are
happening in in the not only um all the
different infrastructure including the
ability to get credit and the ability to
do transactions and so on um in that
that produces a growth curve
particularly if you don't have very much
debt um and you have talented people. So
I for those reasons I think India over
the next 10 years has all the
ingredients to really be the strongest
growth rate and and improvement.
However, it's it still has development
to do. It is more akin to where China
was um you know uh 30 years ago maybe
than where um China is today. So it has
that that growth. it the actual power of
it is not as great as the uh those other
two countries.
>> Ry, I'm going to ask you the last
question of today. If you were 25 years
old and in India and you had either $100
to
if you had $100 to invest somewhere,
where would you put the money? The first
thing I would do
um is ask myself what do I need most to
be most successful and I would secure
that right it's not just return on
investment does that mean that I can
take a little bit of that $100 and I
could start my little business or do I
secure that $100 to have my education
that I'm being able to operate whatever
is going to as a young person invest in
their own success to be able to learn.
Do I how do I learn? Do I listen to your
podcast? What is it that is going to
allow me as that young person to be able
to invest in myself and learn and get
better? So, that's the most important
thing. That's the best investment I can
make.
>> Super. Any last words for our audience?
>> No, just thank you. Um I would say if
you are interested in staying in touch
um you can uh do that online um through
LinkedIn and various uh media. Um and
it's my pleasure. Thank you. Thank um
them to be able to communicate this way
and I hope it's of some use.
>> Thank you. I hope you come visit India
someday soon.
>> I look forward to it.
>> Thank you so much. [music]