The ARM architecture has existed now for
almost 30 years and that started from
early investments from companies like
Apple, early adopters of the ARM
architecture that made it the stalwart
that it is were companies like Nintendo,
companies like Nokia back in the 80s and
90s as these smartphone revolution all
that kind of stuff really started around
ARM and then that's what's driven us to
be where we are today. We have big CPUs
and little CPUs and we're actually
moving the workloads back and forth
because certain times you need the
performance, certain times you don't.
And so that's really the way these
devices work where you to your doorbell
example, you're looking for maybe some
motion, you're looking for something and
then once you trigger that event, okay,
now let's fire up some more computing
elements.
>> In business, they say you can have
better, cheaper, or faster. But you only
get to pick two. What if you could have
all three at the same time? That's
exactly what Cohair, Thompson, Reuters,
and Specialized Bikes have since they
upgraded to the next generation of the
cloud, Oracle Cloud Infrastructure.
OCI is the blazing fast platform for
your infrastructure, database,
application development, and AI needs
where you can run any workload in a high
availability, consistently high
performance environment and spend less
than you would with other clouds.
How is it faster?
OCI's block storage gives you more
operations per second. cheaper. OCI
costs up to 50% less for compute, 70%
less for storage, and 80% less for
networking. Better in test after test,
OCI customers report lower latency and
higher bandwidth versus other clouds.
This is a cloud built for AI and all
your biggest workloads right now with
zero commitment. Try OCI for free. Head
to oracle.comonai.
Ionai all run together. Eye o n ai.
That's oracle.comonai.
So
>> it's great to be here Craig. Thanks for
inviting me. Um, so my name is Chris
Bergie. I'm a senior vice president,
general manager of the client line of
business at ARM. Um, and that means I
very much focus on all of the rich rich
edge devices that ARM um, is so
prominent in. So, um, things like
smartphones, but also we're obviously
making quite a bit of inroads into
things like PCs. uh we participate all
parts of your house whether that's your
TVs, your smart speakers, um all kind of
rich endpoints that that you have
powered and and are quickly becoming AI
enabled and I think that's what we're
going to talk about today. Craig, um
just a little bit about my background.
I've spent almost 30 years in
semiconductors
um various big companies started out of
school at AMD and and and moved to
Broadcom for almost a decade and and
also did some startups in between. So,
uh, a long I can't believe it's gone by
this this quickly. But, uh, I guess, you
know, semiconductors have never been
this cool as, uh, it seems like
governments and, uh, everyone really
cares about semiconductors. So, I guess
I I was very fortunate in my career
choice.
>> Yeah, that's kind of funny, isn't it,
how things happen that way. Uh, yeah,
and it's uh, and particularly uh,
semiconductors on the edge. That's like
the the where everything's at right now.
Uh so ARM and and we're talking about
chips for AI inference. Uh so ARM's uh
ARM version 9 edge AI platform has a
couple of new uh processors
uh designed to enable complex AI models.
Uh, can you talk about those? Uh, or is
there something even more recent that
you want to talk about?
>> Well, I I think that's a good starting
point, Craig. And, you know, and and
we've actually been on quite a journey
um, you know, in the edge evolution, not
just actually at the sorry, in the AI
evolution, not just at the edge, but
also um, we're actually a big part of
the infrastructure buildout as well in
data centers. it, you know, really
leverages a lot of our business model
and capabilities and and so we're doing
quite well there as well. Um but but I
I'd like to spoke probably most mostly
about the edge today. And so we we did
create we did a Lumix um our Lumix
platform
um which is really around kind of
high-end smartphones, high-end
multimedia experiences at the edge. Uh
we launched that back in September and
already there's uh several products um
chipsets that have been launched and now
phones that are being launched by um
different leading phone manufacturers
based on Lumix. Um and what's cool about
it is it is the first um it's it's it's
addition to the platforms of V9 as you
mentioned that starts rolling outme
which is the matrix extensions to the V9
architecture um and and starts pulling
that into the ecosystem to allow people
to um really take advantage of AI at the
edge in these devices and do so with the
traditional CPU programming model. Um so
obviously there's a lot of discussions
around accelerators. Accelerators are
great um and and are quite dominant in
data center um and are also finding uh
their home in the edge. Uh but it's it
is always this balance of you know
accelerators have gate great metrics
around maybe tops per watt. Um but they
definitely are a bit more challenging to
program and versus let's say a CPU. And
so you really got to get the reality is
we we talk about heterogeneous computing
because I think the answer is everything
right I think you know in the AI world
it's about CPU capabilities it's about
GPU capabilities it may be about
dedicated accelerator capabilities and
then it's about memory bandwidth um you
know quite frankly um and really AI is
putting stress on that whole system
>> okay and let's back up a little bit for
listeners that are not deep in the chip
space. Uh uh and I' I'd like you to talk
a little bit about V9 and what that is.
uh but uh when when you talk about
heterogeneous uh computing what you're
and and and the programming language
uh Nvidia one of the reasons it has such
a strong position is very early on it
developed a very uh userfriendly
programming language called CUDA and and
everyone has adopted that uh for uh
programming AI on to uh GPU uh
processors and that has become the
standard and so a lot of new chips are
arriving but you need to learn a new
programming language uh and that's a
barrier but uh you in this heterogeneous
particularly at the edge uh what I
understand is that you still use a a
traditional processor with a programming
language that you're familiar amilar
with and then there's some sort of a
conversion that sends some of those
workloads to the edge uh chip uh and it
it could all be packaged together but is
is that right?
>> Yeah, I think so. You you you you got a
lot wrapped up into there. So, let me
just first start with V9. So, um the ARM
architecture um has existed now for
almost 30 years. Um and that started um
from early investments from companies
like Apple. Um early uh early adopters
of the ARM architecture that made it um
the the stalwart that it is were
companies like Nintendo, companies like
Nokia back in the you know 80s and 90s
as as kind of the these like you know
the smartphone revolution all that kind
of stuff really started around around
ARM and then that's what's driven us to
be to be where we are today. So V9 is is
is an architecture that we launched
about five or six years ago now um which
was the next generation of architecture
um which was focused on a couple
different things. One was security um
another was performance and third was AI
and um you know we are very much at the
forefront of looking at what these next
generation systems are going to require.
Um, and so that's really what V9 is
about. And at this point in time, um,
you know, a large percentage of both iOS
and Android handsets, um, ship with V9,
um, CPUs. Um, and you'll see that
continue to accelerate, um, over the
next couple years. And so and now V9
also is getting perforated across the
other markets that that ARM participates
in whether that's data center whether
that's automotive um and then kind of AI
IoT as well. So that's that's that's V9.
Um so let's talk about the the
programming uh comment that you made
there. So you're right CUDA is an
amazing language. Um, I've actually had
the pleasure of working very closely
with Ian Buck, who is the I guess, you
know, who basically was the Stanford
student that really kind of started this
and has obviously now uh, you know, has
been a a very important part of the
NVIDIA story and where they're at today
and still still is there today.
um you know but and and it is um a great
program for you know basically
programming um GPUs and especially
taking care taking advantage some of the
capabilities um in the accelerators
there but you know it is a accelerator
language right um versus a CPU language
and um you know what people do is that
you know you basically have to start
making things like driver calls and you
have to move your workload off of the
CPU to that now it makes a ton of sense
if you're going to get, you know, I
think, you know, Ian and I actually used
to work on on quite a bit of um high
performance HPC stuff for high
performance computing, big government
labs, and we would have these kind of
rules where it would almost want to have
a 100x uplift when you kind of move that
workload over. Maybe at least you'd have
to have 10x, but you'd really want to
have that versus the convenience and and
and keeping it on the CPU because you
really need to load that and then you
stream that workload on an accelerator.
And so that's kind of as you think about
this heterogeneiality of you're really
moving these workloads around based
upon, you know, what's required. Is it
latency? Is it, you know, is it high
performance? Is it lower power? All
those kinds of things. And so this is,
you know, what I would say the ecosystem
is doing, what ARM's focused on is we're
really focused on making all of those
pieces, the CPU be as performant as
possible on AI workloads and be super
developer friendly, which it is. also
moving some of those workloads to GPUs.
ARM is actually, many people don't know
this, but ARM is actually the highest
volume GPU out there. We've shipped over
9 billion um GPU cores um if you because
of the mobile handsets and so much in
the mobile industry that's based on ARM
GPUs. Um and then also in support of
accelerators through um ARM's extension
of our uh architecture and so many of
those accelerators hang off of things
like chai buses or um that are kind of
part of the ARM architecture.
>> Yeah. And and when you say uh the ARM
ships GPUs
uh where does the uh uh NPU sit in in
fit into all that?
>> Yeah. So, so in a mobile handset, let's
talk about that since that's when we
started. Um, you know, there are, you
know, traditionally there was two large
computing elements or, you know, there
was the CPU and the GPU, right? Um, and
their main function CPU was to run the
OS and then eventually apps. The GPU
function was to display and and play
games and and and do all of those kinds
of things. Well, as these other
workloads become important, whether it
was, you know, camera imaging is
obviously become super important and the
amount of video that you take, well,
then we start putting little
accelerators that are maybe doing um
some of the compression for the
different video codecs and and those
kinds of things. And so MPUs have kind
of evolved um as a way to efficiently do
matrix multiplications or CNN's and
different kinds of models um in as an
accelerator. And so the system can
choose to send that um but what really
happens in the real world and this is
the heterogeneous is you actually end up
kicking off the job usually on the CPU.
You may actually run it to the GPU. you
may send it to the MPU and then it comes
back to the CPU usually to kind of
conclude and so that's tends to be how
these workloads actually work in a
system. It's all uh obviously not seen
by the user. Um but it is the developer
has to make some of those decisions as a
software developer thinking about you
know one kind of capability is in the
handset. They're also making the
decision of do they want to do it on the
cloud or the edge and we should have
that conversation as well today. Um, so
these workloads move around and there's
a whole set of reasons that they move
around, but um, we're making the the CPU
at the edge be as AI friendly as AI
performant um, and power with with a
good power envelope as possible.
>> Yeah. And are these all packaged
together, the CPU, GPU, and NPU if
you're using the NPU
>> or are they Yeah,
>> it depends on the system. um in today's
um cell phone chips, yes, they are
largely all in a single SOC. So all
these computing elements exist in an
SOC. Um as you get into, you know,
things that have let's say larger, you
know, larger battery windows, you know,
in PCs, many of the NPUs are integrated
in the SOC. We are seeing trends around
people adding accelerators. Obviously,
people are also using the GPU that's in
a um in a in a um laptop or something
like that. And again, that may be
integrated. It may be um discrete. Um I
would say there's a trend towards
integration in many of these markets.
And um that is because of the memory
pressure and the memory size
requirements for for AI. And so I think
if you look at some of the latest, you
know, I'm going to say put it on your
desk kind of computing platforms. Um
we're especially proud of our
partnership with Nvidia on the the GB10,
the the product they've actually just
started shipping last week. Um it's
puts, you know, I I think um Jensen
likes to say it puts puts a
supercomputer on your desk, right? where
they're actually um providing I think
it's a pedaflop of AI performance um on
your desk and it is because of you know
you've got these ARM CPUs again um you
know 20 of them coupled tightly to this
accelerator with a single memory system
um that offers up to 128 gigabytes of
DRAM and very high bandwidths and so
you've got this whole system that you
can put together uh or that developers
can use and and we're seeing this as a
trend And whether you look at, you know,
the latest V9 M5 that Apple just
announced uh this week as well or I
think it was last week. Um again, you
see amazing AI performance leveraging
the ARM CPUs, uh GPUs and other
accelerators and then a tremendous
memory system um for for that. And so
that's really what we're seeing
happening. And those are integrated. But
some of them as they get a little bit
bigger, they get discrete. Yeah. But the
problem with discrete is then you have
to split the memory system and it it
gets it.
>> Yeah.
>> AI is so memory heavy that it just it's
a it's a whole balancing act.
>> Yeah. And again I'm mindful of listeners
who are not uh deep in the chip space.
SOC is system on a chip and that's where
you you combine uh different kinds of
chips into one. From the consumer's
point of view it's one looks like one
chip, right? It's all compressed in
there with
>> a cover. U and the uh the reason this is
important is that increasingly I mean
right now I have an app that I built for
myself. When I drive around it talks to
me about the history of the places I'm
in. Uh, and and it the voice drops out a
lot of time because it's got to, you
know, read my GPS and send the data to
the cloud and then, you know, do a a
lookup in in the model, whatever model
I'm I'm using, you know, get the the
text from the model, convert it to
speech, send it back to the the uh
phone, Maybe the the text to speech is
on the point. I'm not sure. But but that
whole chain uh gets there's a million
ways that it can get interrupted. And if
you have that all happening on device,
you don't have those problems with
connectivity and and things like that.
Can you talk about how you see uh
you know V9 or or these uh these SOC's
uh changing the way we uh we interact
with AI?
>> Yeah, absolutely Craig and and you're
you're at the forefront here. I it um
you know it's it's it's it my job's
super fun because I get to talk to many
of the industry leaders and and
visionaries whether that's both on um
you know companies like Google that we
work so closely with and all the chipset
companies and and then all the the um CE
companies the consumer electronics
companies that are actually putting
these things in your hand. Um, and you
know, it's it's it's fun because you
know, I always I'm an I'm an edge guy. I
think, you know, I want edge computing.
That's kind of that's the business I
run. And so, you know, I you know, of
course, I want edge computing to happen.
And so, but I I do often go to these
partners and say, hey, you know, okay,
why can't you run it in the cloud? You
know, why why can't we do it? You know,
it seems to work just fine. People love
Chad GPT. They love Gemini. You know,
they're starting to really utilize these
services.
And you know they they basically said
you know what what gives me reassurance
is all these companies are like no no no
we need to put these in devices and and
and one of the reasons is what you just
said Craig which is you know we the what
the goal of AI is that you know we're
seeing some of the early cool use cases
real time translation
um you know some some smart some agents
that are starting to do some things but
we're we're in the early early innings
here. And you know, one of the analogies
that I like to use is um touch. And if
you take a child, let's say less than 10
years old, and you give them a screen,
they just start touching it because they
don't know anything that's not a touch
screen. Um and and you know, whereas you
know, you and I, you know, like the
mouse was a big thing once once we you
know, we thought that was cool. Um, but
and I and I use that analogy because
that is how AI is going to be. If
something doesn't have AI and you can't
interact with it and it can't start
figuring out what you're trying to do,
it's going to be that like that child
that says this thing's not have a
touchcreen. I don't know how to use it.
I don't want to use it. Right? And so,
so first off, you need to just believe
that that is that is how essential this
is going to be. It's it's the you know
it's how annoying it is when it takes a
long time for the app to boot up and
it's how annoying it is if you have an
app die or you know those kinds of
things that we we work out the edges and
they don't really happen as much anymore
but as technolog is new and so it's the
same thing with AI where you know in
talking to one of these partners you
know they said hey Chris we you know
okay yes maybe the AI in the cloud works
great you
90% of the time, but you know, you're
driving up 101. I'm I'm here in in in
Silicon Valley in San Jose. You're
driving up the highway, there's a dead
spot. And you know, and basically,
you're going to get a bunch of latency
that you know, it's not going to become
conversational. You're going to be
waiting. Um, and the reality is is that
people aren't going to comp complain
about to their carrier saying, "Hey, you
got this dead spot on 101. When are you
gonna fix it?" They're going to say,
"Hey, Craig's app. I don't like that
experience. It's frustrating. It doesn't
work. Hey, you know, three times a day.
I'm I'm trying to use it." You know,
it's it's like doing these video calls,
right? When it doesn't take long for
somebody to have a shaky connection,
you're kind of like, "Hey, let's just
talk next week or let's talk [laughter]
in the office, right? It's just too
frustrating." So, that's just one
example. There's privacy, there's
performance, there's all kinds of other
things that is um that really is going
to drive this to the edge.
the the counter side is the models have
to get smaller. there is a real cost
because of the computing and the memory
computing um pressure it puts on it and
so it's a balance but it is happening um
and again training and there'll still be
quite a bit of inference that'll happen
in the cloud but as much as we can move
to the edge um I think it's pretty
unilateral whether you're a hyperscaler
whether you're an app developer whether
you're a device manufacturer
all are quite incentivized to try to
make it run very very well on the edge
in the device.
>> But there are challenges and there are
trade-offs as you said. Uh one is uh
that uh there's a power issue
uh and uh a heat issue as a result of
that. Uh how do you manage that? because
and that was I mentioned this company
Brain Chip I had a conversation with
that's using neuromorphic chips that
only uh fire when the when
there's enough activity to wake them up.
So, for example, in a in a
doorbell camera, you don't
[clears throat] want the doorbell
absorbing the the the video, sending it
to the cloud, computing, and sending it
back when when there's nothing happening
in the scene. But that's in fact what
happens. Uh, how do you manage that?
>> Yeah. So I I think that I mean we we we
have these management techniques that
get used in you know in almost every
aspect of a a computing device right I
mean we get we have very clever
engineers who figure out how to kind of
fool you that the device is running full
power yet we're we're obviously very
aggressively changing things in the
background and that that was actually
one of the ARM innovations um over 10
years ago we came up with this big
little concept around we have big CPUs
and little CPUs and we're actually
moving the workloads back and forth
because certain times you need the
performance, certain times you don't.
And so that's really the way these
devices work where you to your doorbell
example, you're looking for maybe some
motion. You're looking for something and
then once you trigger that event, okay,
now let's fire up some more computing
elements. Let's go figure out, oh, it's
a face. Okay, is that a face? We know we
don't. Let's let's trigger the cloud or
whatever. And that's the way these
systems work. Um so you know I think it
is about um really these more
intelligent computing platforms um and
getting smarter on how you do these
accelerators and that's you know that's
for example our our the theme I
mentioned that's part of this theme 2
that's part of V9 um it is this kitely
coupled accelerator but we do it in a
very very efficient manner um where it's
actually shared across multiple CPU
cores so you're also being very area
efficient um which really drives cost.
Um so I mean those are things but the
other thing is there's tons of
innovation. Um I I again don't want to
get too technical but your your your uh
listeners maybe have heard about HBM
right HBM memory is stacked DRAMM with a
very high bandwidth interface and it's
become a huge en enabler for
um AI in the cloud right because we have
to have all this memory bandwidth and we
put these HBM stacks next to these
accelerators we're looking at very
similar things um at the edge relative
to you know if where where is the power,
right? Is it in the computing element?
Is it in the jewels per bit of memory
transfer? All of these things are
opportunities for innovation and there's
a ton of research and a ton of
investment that's going into them. So I
I don't worry about the power. I
actually think the power is fairly
manageable relative to uh inference. I
think the bigger pressure we have right
now is actually memory uh memory size.
Um so the model size and um and how how
big it how how do we make it small
enough because at the end of the day
that drives um it drives cost it drives
power and other kinds of things. So it
it's happening and the good news is
we're in this innovation cycle where you
know there's two things you can do. You
can shrink the model and get the same
performance and and that seems to be
shrinking you know almost you know 50% a
year if not faster than that. And on the
other side, you can say, hey, I want a
three gig, you know, gig, three billion
parameter model, and it's just getting
more and more intelligent every every
six months, every year, right? And so
there's different ways to solve the
problem, but this is that's really the
enabler, I think.
>> Yeah. And again, I'm just thinking about
listeners so that so we don't lose them.
is scalable matrix uh extension and
that's a a way to optimize the the math
operation correct uh that's that's used
>> um and uh are you you know on the models
uh are you guys exploring state space
models uh that optimize memory usage I
mean that have a different uh way of
handling uh uh memory
Um so I'm not as familiar personally
with states spate. I I think I
understand the general concept of it. Um
I would say that you know we provide
this platform that many of these
innovations sit on top. So you know many
of the um what we've basically done with
for example our our matrix extension
engine that you just talked about uh we
basically built what we call clidy
framework on top of it which is these
libraries that now developers can
basically leverage so it just does the
right thing in the hardware relative to
taking advantage of which you know do
you have the latest RMV9 etc. So a lot
of those how the model works and states
fates and and what you know are they
using a KV cache or how are they doing
the different updates those actually sit
at a little bit higher level in the
stack where we're kind of more of a I
guess a plumbing enabler is kind of the
way that I would say it. So we we
support all of that and we're making it
super easy for developers to um to
explore that and and to build their
innovations on top. But there's nothing
unique at least at this point in time
that we're necessly doing from a state
state point of view in in our CPUs
>> and can you talk us about some of the uh
the current applications
uh and where you see this going this
move to the edge? Uh I mean obviously
uh
you know uh self-driving cars is is one
where you you can't afford to risk
connectivity and latency by sending data
to the cloud. It's got to be computed on
uh on the platform or on the on in the
car. uh what are some of the other
applications that you're currently
uh putting chips into uh and or current
devices I should say and and where do
you see that going I mean how another
the form factor of these chips how small
can they be uh so that they're they're
sitting I mean I was talking to a guy
the I wear hearing aids uh that uh you
know you'll be able to have these chips
in the hearing aid uh you know filtering
or or isolating sound and that sort of
thing. Uh so can you talk about that a
little bit?
>> Yeah, I mean that's a great question. I
I mean I think the scalability is almost
everywhere, right? I mean your your
hearing aid example is a good example
and and and this is one of the reasons
why ARM builds the the huge set of
portfolio that we do because we are in
many of those those hearing aids and
those kinds of things and we've we've
actually announced AI across I mentioned
Lumix but we have our edge AI platforms
that we've also announced back in
February. So we are enabling that. Um
and it um it it just comes down to if
you know the task you are trying to do
you can make things quite small and um
and efficient right so in a hearing aid
right in a hearing aid you're probably
not trying to run a large language model
not yet at least um you're doing things
like trying to do you know reduce noise
or picking out you know amplifying only
the the interesting you know what what
are you trying to hear. Now, obviously
adding translation and those kinds of
things are probably going to be possible
soon. Um, now if I know what language
I'm translating to, then I can, you
know, that going to make my model
smaller. Uh, but yeah, everything, um,
you know, one of the things that I like
to think about is how much, you know, we
use apps today to configure things. Like
a good example is like a security
camera, right? So today you probably you
know when you try to install your
security camera in the past you would
have went to your laptop and and
connected it. Now probably use your
smartphone to do that. Well, you know
that is a use model. We've gotten used
to it. But but why can't you just do it
with your voice? Like why can't it talk
to you and have the the camera have a
large language model and you say hey it
asks for what is your SSID? Here are the
ones I see. And you know now again that
may or may not be a better user
experience but we just see the
applicability across the board. Again I
I use that touch analogy because touch
has become so prevalent. AI is going to
be way more prevalent than even touch is
today in changing the use model how you
interact with these things. Um you know
a a great example I'll give you Craig is
we work very closely with Meta um who is
is is really doing a great job. I think
with with the you know some of the
advances in their glasses, right? So the
the XR glasses um and their and the
product they just announced two weeks
ago, three weeks ago um they they now
have a wristband that goes with that
product and and that actually uses one
of our Ethos uh NPUs which is again
super small, super low power that you
can have this wristband that basically
you know has a huge battery life. I
forget how many days or weeks you can
wear it. And it literally just, you
know, you manipulate things just by
moving your fingers like this. And it
senses in your wrist the changes and
what's happening, you know, below your
skin using AI to basically figure out
that, oh, you just did your second
finger, so that's going to do this or
you just did this, so that's or, you
know, you're doing this. So basically
that is the new UI of a wristband that
has AI in it that has you know a long
long battery life and has a tiny tiny
battery. That's that's how small we can
make AI for very specific use cases.
>> Yeah. Uh and and what's the focus uh
with with ARM right now? Is it reducing
size? I mean obviously it's going to be
all these things but but where do you
see the next breakthrough? Is it
reducing size, reducing power
consumption, increasing the model size
that can can be uh on these chips? Uh
yeah, where where do you see it going?
[gasps]
Um, it's a great question, Craig, and it
it is a it is a a very open design space
right now to be honest with you. Um, you
know, definitely there has been a focus
on power in the past and that's kind of
where our ethos product line comes from
and but a lot of that was around CNN
networks and some of the early stuff.
Now you're starting to see the move to
transformer networks. What's next?
Right? I don't think that transformers
are actually the end goal. And so we
also need to allow flexibility as these
models change because you know back to
kind of educating your users. I mean it
takes two years almost at a minimum to
design silicon and get it in a shipping
product and you can see how fast AI is
moving. Um yeah
>> and so there's also this flexibility
piece but I I think most of it is
performance. it's really memory
performance and it's um and it's tops
and and CPU performance and then um and
and trying to shrink that down as as as
the best we can for for whatever the
power envelope is to um you know how
much computing you can get and I think
that's obviously happened in the data
center as well right where it's okay
we're trying to get we're now building
gigawatt data centers but how much how
you know how many tokens can you create
How much performance can you get in
that? So almost everywhere in the space,
it's like, okay, tell me what your power
envelope is. It's a gigawatt here. It's,
you know, seven six watts in a phone.
It's, you know, in my wrist example,
it's literally, you know, a couple
hundred mills.
You know, how much AI performance can
you get? And so it it really is spanning
a a large um space.
>> Yeah. And you guys don't uh
you're you're producing IP, right?
You're not uh building uh you don't have
a fab. You're not uh uh sending your
designs out to a fab to make your chips.
You're licensing this to other chip
makers.
>> That's correct. Yes. Our business model
is we provide IP to uh you know the a
large portion of the semiconductor
ecosystem. Um and um and then our
partners build on top of it and create
uh create silicon solutions that can
span like we talked about anything from
you know a wristband or or your hearing
aid to uh you know your next
self-driving car.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And and where is most of
this? Um I mean obviously most of it's
going into the US, but uh do you have
partners that are are licensing your IP?
Uh where what are the other markets that
you're operating in?
>> Well, you know, I would say that
traditionally semiconductors have been
quite global, right? um you know that
the the cost of developing a
semiconductor is tremendous right um
obviously the foundry cost and I'm not
even saying like put aside the foundry
costs um but literally building a chip
um you know if you're example if you're
using u one of the latest nodes um just
the mass costs alone of of when you're
done your design and getting that
manufacturer is in the tens of millions
of dollars um the development costs up
front can often be in the hundred
million plus range. So you're talking
about tremendous amount of cost to get
to the first unit. Um but what's made
semiconductor so great is that you can
scale that and because we have these
amazing manufacturing capabilities etc.
And so they tend to be very large
markets and so generally it's been a
global market for us. Um and yes, um you
know, obviously, um there's many great
IC or semiconductor companies in the US
that do designs. Um we work very closely
with with European semiconductor
companies, uh in Taiwan, in Korea, um as
well. And um we also have had a um armed
China, a JV where um semiconductors get
built in China based on our IP. And so
it we get uh it's pretty global market.
Yeah. Uh I would imagine the Chinese uh
relationship has been strained by the
sanctions. How does that affect you
guys?
>> Well, yeah. I mean, we always make sure
we're following the local uh laws and
obviously where we're located. Um most
of the constraints have been around the
manufacturing process and not
necessarily um some of the IP. there is
some around IP enablement but um you
know it's something that we always are
very careful about make sure we're we're
complying to what is required um and uh
and we'll see as things evolve
>> in that that you guys are uh are
primarily selling IP uh do you work with
a large developer community and what's
that relationship like uh is how much of
this is open source for example and Um,
and then if you could talk about where
you see I mean you mentioned wearables
where wearables are going to be a hot
thing where you see the edge really
exploding the public u uh interaction or
experience with AI.
[snorts]
>> Okay. Yeah. So I mean let's let's start
about developers. So you know ARM is um
you know developers are super important
to ARM and in fact we now have uh the
world's largest developer ecosystem. We
believe we have over 22 million software
developers that are developing software
on ARM. Um and that's just because of
our our footprint um that spans all the
way from you know iOS to now Windows on
ARM and then of course things like um
Chrome, Android and Linux. um you know
we've been a longtime supporter of so um
you know really the the world's largest
software ecosystems are um quite uh you
know work work closely with ARM um and
we we support them and uh and we really
focused on that developer experience and
and how do we improve that developer
experience I mentioned uh CID before in
this in this conversation that's really
about again trying to make it seamless
for developers to use AI because you You
talked about CUDA AI is not um simple
from many of the programming elements
and I would say we're still seeing
not necessarily the hardware abstraction
that we've gotten other software
ecosystems to. We still see a fairly
tight coupling to today's models to
actually the hardware that they run on.
Um whether that's the operators they
support, whether that's you know the way
they kind of assume the model is going
to propagate and those kinds of things.
So um you know but we are we're clearly
focused on the supporting those
developers and uh and and seeing what
they can build right and I think that
kind of goes to your second question of
you know what's kind of on on the
forefront uh and that's why what makes
my job so fun because I get to to to to
interact with so many of these super
innovative folks u both startups and
establish established companies on kind
of what is next or what what's the art
possible. Um, and and if I was just to
use a general concept, it would just be
intelligence. The idea of something is
capable of interacting with you in a way
that exceeds your current expectations,
right? And you maybe I'll use another
product example. Um, I'm a huge Amazon
fan. Um, but one of the things I've
noticed is that before I upgraded to
Alexa plus, you know, because of the way
I was using a chatbot or chat GPT or
Gemini,
I started talking to it in a in a more
conversational manner because that's
what I could do. But then when I would
come home and use Alexa, it wouldn't
necessar it was expecting more of kind
of a search kind of give me, right? you
know, really break it down pretty, you
know, I'm giving you three words and try
to contextualize those three words, you
know, and so and I think, by the way,
Amazon's done a great job with Lexa Plus
and I think they're they're on the right
path here. But that's just a change in
expectations and I and I think that's
going to only go, you know, just through
the roof relative to, you know, the idea
of, you know, the things that we think
are how you interact with a device for
it just to be smart. Um, you know, one
of the things people ask me about is
like what's a gentic AI or how's that
going to feel, right? And and one of the
things I like to use and I think I think
Microsoft has done an amazing job of
really integrating AI into their
products as large as a company they are,
you know, the way they push copilot, all
those kind of things. But what I like is
a is a a silly example of settings. So,
when you use Windows in Windows
settings, we've all done it and you have
to figure out, okay, I want to add a
screen or I don't like this resolution
screen. How many like windows do you
have to click in to kind of say figure
out how to make this change, right?
Well, they've changed it to be more of
an agentic experience in Windows 11
where you just say, what do you want to
do? I want to add a screen. I want to
reduce this. And it just says, okay,
well, here's how you do it. or I'll do
that for you. And so, you know, to me
that's a touchyfey thing of how many
times do we, you know, click through
three apps. Oh, I'm going to cut this
now. I have to go to my flight app. Then
I have to go to my rental car app. Then
I like, you know, so many of these
things that we're just trained to think
like, oh, it works good enough. I you
know but like this idea of things are
just so smart that you know when you
call an Uber it of course knows where
you're going to go and it's already told
people when you're going to show up and
and all these kinds of things. So you
know those are and of course those are
consumerry examples. There's huge amount
of enterprise examples of you know teams
that are not you sharing data or people
don't understand or they're looking for
information they can't find. Um, and so
I think it's just going to be the
general idea of just how do we make
things just super smart um, and really
kind of exceed expectations of what
technology limitations are today.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And robotics is is another
one. I'm not a great believer in
humanoid robotics. I think we're a long
way from that. But uh what you're
describing I mean it's u you know the
day will come when uh our children or
grandchildren will will look back and
can you believe that you know any object
that you use daily
uh was a dumb object back then instead
of being able to talk to it and and have
it like configure itself or or whatever
it is. And that that's pretty exciting.
What about robotics? Uh I mean obviously
you guys uh are involved in that.
>> Yeah, I mean it's pretty amazing the
what's what's happening there. Um and
the ability to train the robots in
virtual worlds as well as real worlds.
Um and we are a huge believer in that
and and and we're quite involved with
many of the ecosystems. Um, you know, I
think it is really taking the advantage
of all, you know, the camera sensor has
been an amazing enabler, right? If you
just look at what our cell phones are
able to do in capturing images, but
really the the camera sensor has now
unleashed this idea of physical AI and
how do you, you know, because we can use
vision systems and AI is so good with
vision systems, right? whether that's
looking at an MRI and or you know maybe
and and augmenting a doctor's reading of
that or in a system and trying to
understand what's going on. So it is it
is a huge area. I think we're going to
see a lot of um innovation. I think you
know to your robotics example you know I
think I don't know go back to the
Jetsons or whatever. I mean people said
we're gonna have flying cars and they
were going to be able to do all these
autonomy things. It's taken a long time,
but you know, another great ARM powered
device, my Tesla, you know, it has
gotten pretty darn good relative to
self-driving and and and I really enjoy
having that augment me in in many, many
scenarios. And so, it is, like you said,
it's going to just be an expectation and
you're just going to be disappointed
when it doesn't do something that they
clearly can't do today. But these things
are hard. I mean, you know, I think that
that blend of physical um and and
you know, is going to be a hard thing,
but like anything, it's probably, you
know, I go back to I was involved with
Bluetooth in the early days and and you
know, oh, it's going to be amazing.
You're going to have all these Bluetooth
devices and just and and it it didn't
work great in the beginning. The
experience wasn't great, but just look
at how fundamental Bluetooth is today.
Again, when I walk up to my Tesla, it
just unlocks. It just like it locks.
and that's all over Bluetooth and
augmented by UWB or you know so it's it
it's just these technologies you know
sometimes the hype cycle gets a little
bit ahead of expectations and that's
that's our fault as technologists but at
the end of the day the technology
delivers and uh and it's going to be an
exciting future for um our children and
grandchildren.
>> Yeah, absolutely. And yeah, with moving
into physical, the challenges aren't
really uh the AI, it's the it's the
mechanics, the actuators and and the the
wear and tear and the dust and the
grease and all that stuff that people
kind of forget about.
>> Uh that that's that's it's still got a
long ways to go. Um yeah. Okay. Uh so so
is ARM on the verge of announcing
anything uh new or is this uh is it
really the uh the V9 that you're
>> well you guys are focused on
>> we we've got quite a broad product set
of products right so yes I you know I
have my responsibilities but we have a
whole automotive and and robotics group
we have a whole group that focuses on
data center same thing with edge AI and
and additional intelligence So, uh, I
think you'll keep seeing quite a bit
from us. Uh, lots of great stuff going
on and, um, and again, we're just super
excited about the partnerships that we
get to partner with and how much
developers,
um, and hopefully some of your listeners
are inspired to, uh, build things on top
of the ARM architecture and uh, and help
make the future what it's what's what's
show us what's possible.
>> Yeah. And and on that note,
[clears throat] we'll end on that. uh
developers if they're interested uh do
you have a a portal developer portal?
>> We do. developer.arm.com.
Um great great resource to uh to find
out more figure out how to um you know
build and and uh and explore many of
these new technologies. Um obviously
many of the makers are familiar with
Raspberry Pi. That is a uh also
ARMPowered and something that many um
you know kids and and ele uh educators
start um start their journey and and
those things are getting super excited
now with robotics and and beyond.
>> In business they say you can have
better, cheaper or faster but you only
get to pick two. What if you could have
all three at the same time? That's
exactly what Cohair, Thompson, Reuters,
and Specialized Bikes have since they
upgraded to the next generation of the
cloud, Oracle Cloud Infrastructure.
OCI is the blazing fast platform for
your infrastructure, database,
application development, and AI needs
where you can run any workload in a high
availability, consistently high
performance environment and spend less
than you would with other clouds.
How is it faster? OCI's block storage
gives you more operations per second,
cheaper.
OCI costs up to 50% less for compute,
70% less for storage, and 80% less for
networking. Better in test after test,
OCI customers report lower latency and
higher bandwidth versus other clouds.
This is a cloud built for AI and all
your biggest workloads right now with
zero commitment. Try OCI for free. Head
to oracle.comonai.
Ionai. All run together. Eye o n ai.
That's oracle.com/
Iion AI.