2018 2019 in fintech was late spring.
You get into 2020 and COVID and that was
utter insanity of a of a story.
>> Like 25% of all venture dollars in that
period went into fintech which is
>> Wow. 25%.
>> The stat after that is not a good stat
which is um starting in like the second
half of 2022 like basically 0% of
venture dollars went into
>> drought maybe.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Fintech winter was the
second half of 2022. Most of 23 and 24
things started to thaw a little bit and
like now we're very much back in spring.
It turns out the biggest use case for AI
is fraudsters committing fraud against
financial services companies. Financial
fraud is growing at like like 18 to 20%
a year uh which is insane and it's
already a huge market. I mean the cattle
win long term, but the mouse is winning
right now.
Zach, David, uh, we did this podcast, I
believe, seven years ago, and it's great
to have the the gang back together.
Thanks for joining.
>> Thank you for having us.
>> Great to be here. Of course, a lot has
happened since the last conversation in
our personal lives, and a lot has
happened in in fintech more broadly. I
was listening to the the episode that we
did um the last time we spoke and we
were talking about what has changed in
fintech, you know, from early 2010s to
to just before 2020. And I'm curious if
we could just sort of um check in or
reflect back as to, you know, since the
last time we spoke to to to now, what
have been some of the major themes in in
in fintech? C catch us uh catch us up if
someone was in a coma after listening to
the last episode and just woke up and
said, "Hey, what's changed in in
fintech?" What would we say?
>> Let's see. So, the last last time we
talked was probably 2018 2019. Is that
right?
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. So, let's see. um a a lot. There's
been like a bunch of different eras or
like maybe we can think of it as like
almost seasons in some sense. Um 2018
2019 in fintech was I guess like kind of
late late spring. Um lot of lot of
really good growth like the industry had
a name. The name probably came about I
actually think that David you created a
name but no one will give you credit but
I will give you credit. I think you
created the name in like 2015. Um but we
we we now had a name for this industry.
We had gone past like oh some people are
maybe building financial services
products to um all right we like it is
an industry and there are a lot of
things being built. Um you know we
started to see the the million flowers
bloom to to really overextend this
analogy the million flowers bloom bloom
from call it like 2014 2015 up until
2019 2020 like zillions of uh first time
hey can I take this thing outside of a
physical bank branch and deliver it to a
consumer digitally. Um so you saw
applications like Robin Hood come up and
grow incredibly well. you see all sorts
of neo bank neo bankank for x or y or z
subm market. Uh those are everywhere. Um
uh you saw crypto like the first crypto
apps really start to emerge and and grow
a lot. Um and then kind of from 2019 you
get into like 2020 and COVID and that
was kind of just utter insanity of a of
a story. Um you know first the first few
months of 2020 were totally normal. Uh
then you get into early COVID where
everything froze. Um basically every
business um kind of locked up including
all the fintech companies. Um but within
you know two two and a half months you
then had this total inversion of
fintech. So you went from late spring to
like big EDM pumping uh summer uh really
fast like the EDM music turned on very
loudly very quickly. Um and uh so you
just had this insane growth period for
fintech uh from kind of mid 2020 through
um kind of like the end of 2021 and even
into early 2022. And yes, a lot of new
companies formed, but um every investor,
whether venture or public markets or
whatever it was, wanted to push money
into fintech. Um and so you had just
this this huge boom in funding, tons of
new stuff grew. It was it was like
really fun and very chaotic time
honestly like a hard time to manage
because uh you know the feature chase
the things we had to build were going so
rapidly.
>> I think like 25% of all venture dollars
in that period went into fintech which
is insane.
>> 25%.
>> It's a crazy stat actually. I think it's
a great stat. The stat after that is not
a good stat which is um starting in like
the second half of 2022 like basically
0% of venture dollars went into
>> drought maybe.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So um summer uh went into a
very very short fall. So that was kind
of like mid 2022 and then immediately
into winter. Um and fintech winter was
the second half of 2022.
Most of 23 and 24 things started to thaw
a little bit and like now we're very
much back into spring. Yep.
>> Um different format, but it's been it's
been a fun cycle of the seasons.
Totally. I you know and I think even to
describe maybe what drove some of the
seasons like you know the the rate cycle
was a big part of that as like a from
like a macro perspective you know having
very low rates you know kind of drove
Zer obviously not unique to fintech but
a lot of you know technology broadly but
certainly a lot of lending volume in the
space grew massively in those periods um
you know the one benefit that I think
has shown up more recently in fintech
you know in the in the thaw period is
that rates went up and it it it sort of
shifted the mix of revenues for for any
of these fintech companies from lending
driven kind of origination you know
oriented stuff to you know deposits um
you know so many of these fintech
companies decided I forget the exact
timing but to go kind of full stack you
know so you saw you know uh fintech
companies like SoFi you know buy banks
you know lending club uh I think square
got an ILC charter um you know Robin
Hood Mercury many of these companies are
generating very significant percentages
of their revenue and profits today from
deposit flows as rates have gone up And
so that I think has helped thaw the
market you know to some degree more
recently
>> usually. Yeah. And in in in 20 um 2018
2019 um fintech was a startup industry
um having gone through this entire cycle
um yeah some ups some downs um but a lot
of maturation um a lot of expansion.
We've ended now with fintech is in my
opinion synonymous with financial
services.
>> Um and it goes beyond just financial
services as well. So you you've seen a
few themes emerge. Um one thing that
that uh we said for a long time that
Andre Horus also likes to say is that
every company is a fintech company and
that was kind of quite common from 2018
um kind of onward. Um now you see the
emergence of embedded finance. So you
know some apply customers are like Ford
and John Deere and these companies that
like you know yes they do have captive
financial services uh embedded within
them but you do not think of them as
financial services companies um or you
know large billers or it's expanded
quite a lot. Um and then you see the
banks themselves saying um historically
they said oh we need to be fintech
companies too. Now they're saying we are
the biggest fintech companies like we
invest heavily in technology. And so
you've seen the startup industry now
become mainstream and the firmament of
financial services but also powering
experiences well beyond financial
services.
>> Let's go deeper into where we are today
and and and and where we're going um g
given that we're kind of in a you know
exciting period. um you is it still like
macro in terms like is it still early in
terms of lot of things to be built um
and some of the spaces you're you're
excited about when maybe Zach you take
the first plaid ourselves have have gone
through a few phases and we're lucky
that we have this really broad view of
what's what's happening in fintech I'm
going to keep calling it fintech but at
this point realize that I mean financial
services plus+ um so we have this really
broad view of what's going on in fintech
um and like the the things that we're
seeing today are, you know, very
different and much more varied than um
they were before. So um V1 of Plaid was
how do we create access for everyone?
And I would say largely um the fintech
industry was focused on the same thing.
So um instead of making you walk into a
bank branch to open a bank account, how
can you open a bank account on your
mobile app? um instead of um you know
making you carry money um and go to an
exchange when you're trying to cross a
border, how can we create a digital way
to do remittances so you can actually
move money across the border um a little
bit more easily. Um and and and apply
that across kind of every every subse
basically every product uh that that the
banks were building at the time. Um
we've solved the access problem not
completely not in every little niche but
but for the most part we as a collective
industry have solved the access problem.
So, um, you know, I grew up in a small
small town, uh, you know, only one bank
in our town. Um, and if you didn't
happen to be a member of that bank, you
you couldn't get a loan easily. Um, now
if you live in that same town, you just
go online and you apply for a mortgage
and you get, you know, 30 mortgage
offers in an hour. Um, or you can do it
with Rocket and, you know, be done in 5
minutes. And, um, these are awesome
experiences. That said, what we've done
is we've taken traditional financial
services and we've made it digital. We
haven't necessarily made it excellent.
Um that's that's like the next horizon
for us. And so a lot of things that
we've been investing in now are things
like credit scoring. How do we make
credit scoring more logical and
something that a consumer can
understand? Um if you get a new job and
your income goes up but your expenses
don't go up, you were a better loan
risk. However, that doesn't show up in
your credit file for like many many
years because your credit file is long
history of your your your repayments. Um
it's not necessarily indicative of your
your free cash flow. Um and so like that
that is the next horizon that a lot of
the fintech companies that I'm seeing
are starting to solve. So that's that's
kind of like one big area. It's it's um
kind of solving those endemic problems
that are longlasting things like like
fraud, things like credit scoring, so on
and so forth. Um the second is um you
know making financial services really
easily available in places that you
might not have otherwise thought it to
be. Um so you know putting BNPL on kind
of everything.
>> Yeah. um uh or or you know issuing a
card kind of everywhere or issuing a
wallet kind of everywhere. Um and so now
now we're we're entering this like
fintech is everywhere. Not every company
is a fintech company but like every
every consumer is surrounded by fintech
and in in all the places they might want
to go. Um and like you know the the
future horizons are always like you know
looking at the the next few things that
are happening like we look at AI and
Agentic Financial Services and right now
it's mostly hype and people talking
about it and there are a few interesting
use cases but you know fast forward two
years and the way that you get a
mortgage is going to be talking to you
an AI application um because that is
just the most efficient fastest way to
do it. So that's that's been a
fascinating one to watch and then like
seeing what's going on with stables is
of course fascinating as well. So, um,
lots more to come.
>> Just on that note, it is crypto
basically just fintech or, you know,
people said is the new version of the
internet. Maybe hopefully it still
happens, but in terms of where it is
right now, is it, you know, mo mostly
just a subset of fintech?
>> Well, David, you're an investor, so you
probably know better than me. My my take
is
sometimes like ultimately I don't think
that consumers
um change all that much over time and so
the kind of things that a consumer would
want to do 5 years ago are similar to
the kinds of things that they might want
to do today but the form factor in which
they can do it uh is very different. So
um you know 5 years ago um a consumer
might want to speculate um and you know
you can speculate on gold, you can
speculate on a few of these other things
and u bitcoin and and and other uh coins
made it very simple for consumers to
speculate. So great you can pull up an
app, you can speculate on things,
speculation continues. Um the form
factor has changed. Um another thing
that consumers like to do is make
predictions. Um so you know in the past
you might make a bet with some friends.
Um uh now you might go on Cal Street or
Poly Market and uh you know enter
prediction markets or you might do that
via Robin Hood or or whatever it is. Um
other things that consumers like to do
are like you know spend money, save,
invest so and so forth. And in as much
as consumer behavior doesn't change it's
a question of like how and where does
crypto and fintech fit into the existing
set of consumer behaviors.
>> So I think if you look at again what a
bank does like they're roughly tailored
to what consumers want. Consumers want
to save money, invest, get loans so and
so forth. Um and I think the wisest
product development strategy is to kind
of like take um take the things that
consumers already do and just like make
them newer, easier, more accessible, so
on and so forth. Um and so I suspect
that there will be a convergence of uh
one side of crypto um and core financial
services um be that exchanging um you
know like checking accounts with dollars
in them for checking accounts with USDC
in them wallets with USDC in them um or
or or similar like I think there's a a
convergence that'll likely happen there
but then also crypto does some crazy out
there stuff and really pushes the bounce
on innovation and like totally
>> I'm not sure that that's necessarily
going to end up merging with banks but
who knows
>> totally. Yeah. Yeah. I I mean I totally
agree with with what what Zach was
saying. I think part of it is um you
know culture, right? And how people to
Zach's point, you know, um you know,
want to interact with financial
services. I think part of this has been
driven from a regulatory perspective.
And I think maybe the more meta theme as
I've sort of watched fintech evolve and
I think this is permeating into crypto
is just how the large incumbent
financial institutions are are embracing
this innovation and technology, you
know, at large. I think a lot of the you
know I'd refer to my you know crypto
colleagues who are much deeper in this
space than I am. A lot of the enthusiasm
I I would say here is about uh you know
the existing kind of financial system
adopting you know things like stable
coins or maybe even tokenizing kind of
real world world assets and um I think
that's that's different in you know from
a lot of the more frontier stuff that
that I think the team had had talked
about internally which was kind of more
purely decentralized and and kind of
owning the internet but but I think you
know for crypto to go very mainstream
and kind of plug into the broader
financial system that probably is and
will continue to happen with with Zach
and the team PL have done you know over
you know the last 14 years 13 years uh
is is remarkable. I mean you know you
you know from my vantage point like you
won the hearts and minds of the
developer community. You built this sort
of foundational infrastructure that
really catalyzed like you know I I can't
take credit for creating the fintech uh
term. You like created the enabling
infrastructure to like create the
industry in many ways. um you know now
have I don't know hundreds of millions
of accounts you know connected and and
you're to your point now bringing kind
of this whole ecosystem of kind of value
added services and analytics you know to
make financial products better um and I
think while we saw different seasons
kind of over that period you know uh you
know hay fever and and long winters and
uh uh you know euphoria in some moments
um you know many of these companies are
now bigger than ever I mean Robin Hood
is now I don't know hundred billion
dollar public company you I I looked up
SoFi's stock price. You know, they're a
$35 billion public company. A firm is a
$20 billion company. Like these are
these are outcomes that you couldn't
even imagine.
>> Revolute.
>> Yeah. I mean, Revolute $75 billion, you
know, for new investors. And and that
phenomenon is not just US- ccentric to
that point. It's it's become a global
one. I mean, new bank, you know, hundred
billion dollar, you know, you know,
company, you know, in Brazil, you know,
my good friend Pier Paulo who runs WAN
in Argentina, you know, Colombia,
Mexico. um you know so these these
companies have worked and they've kind
of proliferated and brought access of
financial products you know everywhere
um uh and I think that that trend will
continue you know I think while they
started often with point solutions and
they kind of perfected whatever their
wedge product was you know many of them
have now rebundled right they want to
become kind of the full you know
financial picture for their for their
customers whether that's through cards
or accounts or lending um again many of
them have gone full stack and actually
bought banks and actually hold deposits
and are generating significant revenue
you know from from that float.
I think the other meta theme which has
been um been interesting and and I think
it's accelerating now with AI is just
again the um the posture of a lot of the
incumbent financial institutions you
know to fintech and technology broadly.
Um, you know, I saw this kind of
firsthand, uh, certainly, you know, as
an investor back at Spark, as a founder,
and then inside of Goldman, just even
their own sort of evolution, uh, and and
posture to technology, you know, for a
long time, many of these institutions,
like if the technology wasn't built
there, they weren't interested. I mean,
Goldman had literally created their own
email client. Like they they they didn't
operate on Outlook or on Gmail. They had
this thing called Orbit. I don't know
why Goldman Sachs needs to create their
own email client, but you know that that
was that was like a window into the
psychology from a technology
perspective.
>> Don't they still use like secd
internally like they they have their own
database that they built?
>> That that makes more sense to me because
it was like a centralized risk system
for managing all their trades but
outlook equivalent like makes no sense.
Um you know then I think there was this
period where you know many of the large
institutions were like we want to be the
fintech companies ourselves and you know
Goldman went very aggressively and you
know into Marcus and and others followed
suit. I think there's a bit of a
humbling that has happened. You know,
may maybe I'm using them as one one
lens, but but more broadly, I think the
the positive impact of that experience
um made them more open to adopting the
best technology that exists in the
market and and no longer are building
everything in house. And so a lot of
where I've been spending time the past
several years has been in, you know,
fintech companies that lead with
software that, you know, ideally have
the potential for a network effect and
are selling into these financial, you
know, larger financial institutions and
solving, you know, real real workflow
challenges for them. Um, and I think
we're at this interesting moment where
because the software itself can actually
do the work, you know, with AI, there's
sort of this bottoms up momentum and top
down pressure that's happening that I
think is accelerating this cultural
change. you know, many of these
institutions are beginning to adopt
products like cursor or, you know, even
GitHub copilot or a broader ecosystem of
kind of AI products in their in their
employee base and people are seeing the
productivity gains and then unlike I
think prior periods of of kind of
product cycle or platform shifts, if you
were the CEO of a big bank and you said,
you know, do I need to be in the cloud?
Like that was sort of an esoteric
question. Now it's like any CEO, any
board member can plug a prompt into one
of these models and sort of intuitively
understand the impact that it could have
on their business. And so I think that's
broadening the aperture at least from my
vantage point of what fintech is.
>> And it's really I think to your point
just financial services and I think
software in large part sold into
financial services as well.
>> Yeah. And and and David say more about
sort of that that change around when you
know it went from 25% to you know
significantly less than that. what what
was changing in these businesses that
that that caused that you you mentioned
sort of the macro environment. Is there
anything else we could learn from it and
and more around now where are you
particularly excited to to to invest or
what what are the sort of different um
you know sort of subspaces that you're
you know looking at or excited to
>> I think 2021 period was sort of wild for
lots of reasons. I think um you know
financial services is and remains
obviously one of the biggest parts of
our global economy and so I think people
you know often get over excited maybe by
TAM you know and and and so every
venture firm created a fintech team had
you know was deploying a lot of capital
you know to that market um uh you know
and again many of these companies have
have continued to succeed but I think it
it was probably um too much euphoria
going into that space relative to the
amount of dollars um
>> no I think it was the exact right amount
of euphoria Yeah, just the pullback
afterwards that was the issue.
>> Uh exact exactly you know again part of
that was that companies you know when
rates are zero you can lend money and
and grow very quickly and there's a lot
of you know margin to capture there. I
think when rates go up your cost of
capital goes up and that margin you know
shrinks and there's a natural ceiling on
on borrowing that people you know both
from a regulatory perspective and a and
a kind of consumer appetite perspective.
So you know the business model of a lot
of on the lending side I think you know
kind of compressed
>> but you also have to look at like the
underlying growth rates of these apps
were insane.
>> Totally.
>> Like you you you look at the number of
consumers that were you know signing up
to invest or signing up to take a loan
or signing up to buy Bitcoin or whatever
it was. Totally
>> like we just looked at the the charts
and like you know if if the app was
growing at what 25% a month it was
actually a great venture investment. I
mean, yes, you might know that the music
at some point is going to slow down or
stop, but um 25% a month's growth is
insane.
>> Totally.
>> Yeah, totally. I mean, yeah. And this
was like stimulus and there was there
was a lot of
>> helicopter money everywhere. Yeah. There
were a lot of reasons they were growing
that fast.
>> 100%. And look, I think like from a I
don't know industry health perspective,
like I think things have normalized, but
the the companies continue to grow and
succeed. I mean, again, now they're, you
know, bigger than they've ever been. the
the great ones. There was a wash out and
and um there were a lot of fintech
companies that um died or shut down in
the second half of 22 in the first half
of 23. Um there were a lot that you know
kind of went sideways for uh for quite a
while. Um and a lot of lenders
especially who just like basically
closed up shop or merge or things like
that.
>> Um but the ones that succeeded coming
out of it across all of fintech they
were much much stronger for it. Totally.
So, as you said, like if you started off
with a neo bank and all they did was
have a a checking account and a savings
account and maybe a card. Um, well, in
this period, if they wanted to survive,
they needed to to to build the lending
side of of their offering. And so, um,
you know, they they expanded there or
build the investment side of their
offering, so they expanded there. And
so, now you've come out with these like
much more full-fledged like longlasting
uh companies. So, the winners became
even more so the winners. Um, and yeah,
there was an unfortunate number of
companies that also didn't make it
>> totally. And and David, I'm curious h
how you or how we look at the sort of
investible universe or or sort of
divide. Is it you know that there's
certain type of form factors and it's
you know each region is going to have
their their their new banks so to speak
or is it um you know by sort of sort of
form factor or value prop to to the how
do we think about the the universe? How
do we map it?
>> You know it's been interesting. I mean,
I would say from our from our vantage
point, we haven't made as many consumer
fintech investments in recent years as
we have historically. I think um part of
that's just it's it's more expensive to
acquire customers and and hit the kind
of scale you need to really be, you
know, kind of venture venture scale
outcomes. And I think that's a function
of, you know, um just, you know,
consumer acquisition channels getting
more expensive and some of these
companies starting early and it was
easier to acquire u and then build
massive LTV with their existing customer
bases. that that does change around the
world. I think um you know in some
markets people were entering the formal
financial economy for the first time and
so offering a fee free mobile first you
know bank account and a and a debit card
you know literally gave them access to
you know e-commerce and and things like
Netflix and Spotify and and Amazon for
the you know for the very first time.
Credit doesn't exist you know equally in
in every market around the world nor do
credit bureaus and credit data. Um, so
there's, I think, still, you know, tons
of interesting kind of macro opportunity
from a financial product perspective. I
think especially in emerging economies.
Um, I think AI could be an interesting,
you know, kind of catalyst for a new
resurgence of consumer fintech. I mean,
there there's always been this promise
of, you know, kind of self-driving money
or, um, you know, PFMs that actually do
the work for you and help you make, you
know, not not just give you advice, but
actually, you know, help you earn, you
know, save and and spend better. And I
think like we've yet to see as many of
those companies today, but I think
there's the technology might be ripe.
I'm curious if you're seeing this, you
know, uh on your side like to actually
deliver on that promise.
>> Yeah. You know, it's funny when when we
think about pro prospective apps that
like, you know, the app that I wish that
existed. Um, you know, I wish that there
was a self-driving money app that I
could just say, hey, you know, my
paycheck goes in here. Like, you know,
sweep enough money into my checking
account so that I can pay my daily
expenses, but put all the rest into this
like high yield savings account and you
invest this percent of it in the market.
And, you know, I wish that this thing
existed.
>> I don't actually know that that's
necessarily a very good app to build
because I'm a weird power user. I have
insane trust in fintech companies to do
all this stuff for me. Like I understand
all the actions that the agent would
take and I have uh you know enough
background in the space that like the
actions seem logical to me. But if I
gave that to my mom, she'd be like
where's my body? What's going on? Like I
don't trust this thing. Like wait, why
did it move body over there? I have all
these questions. And so um you know I
I'm not sure that I'm necessarily the
best this like so I I have all these
visions of like the the the prospective
apps that should exist out there. But
then you know for us as plaid and and
and in a lot of senses for for you as an
investor um like certainly for us as
plaid like our job is like we need to
build the platform and then figure out
what emergent behavior starts to exist
on it and then go optimize for that
emerging behavior as uh as as as new
interesting companies start to emerge.
Um and so that's how we think of our
job. So like our job as it relates to AI
is like let's build tools that allow
consumers safely to link their data with
agents. Um then let's build tools that
allow those agents to take the proper
actions. Be that just analyzing data or
be that actually moving money or
something else. Let's let's build tools
that allow those agents to to to to take
those actions. Um and then let's see
what happens and like have a team that's
just like constantly looking at like the
emerging behavior and figuring out oh is
that a good thing? Do we want to
optimize for that? Oh, like has that
enabled some new vector of risk that we
need to we need to avoid? And that's
kind of the the the thought process we
take across all the things that we do.
So, um a lot of it is like if you build
it, they will come. You just don't know
who will come and what they'll look like
and like what exactly is going to be the
next big thing. Um but we have to be
very prepared to react when we see it.
>> Yeah. And I I think as a result like
we've we've been focused on maybe more
known problems like there's so many
there's so much work that happens inside
of all these large financial
institutions that it's just done
manually by expensive people you know
frankly across risk compliance legal you
know vendor onboarding treasury
management I mean you know I can go on
and on and on um and and now you have
again AI to actually you know solve many
of those problems and so that's I think
you know largely where we've been
spending time you know, you know,
companies like, you know, moment that
had built, you know, fixed income
trading infrastructure. If you're a
wealth management client of of JP Morgan
today, you know, building a bond ladder
is still a manual process. You're
picking, you know, individual securities
one by one. That's insane. Like that
hasn't existed for, you know, at least a
decade in in equities. And so, you know,
there's a ton of opportunity to solve,
you know, kind of basic problems like
that. and and I would argue build you
know very large uh you know kind of
software and kind of platform style
businesses on the back of that and so
whether it's you know things like you
know um you know a company like salient
which is doing you know bringing voice
agents to uh loan servicing and
collections right the idea that you know
a voice agent can speak in 50 languages
you know fully compliantly track UDEP
you know do welcome calls and payment
reminders um you know and actually
deliver on a better customer experience
because it can speak their native
language uh and and get better results.
It's infinitely patient, right? Um you
know, that is a really interesting
opportunity for the moment, you know, in
large part because it's unlocking
markets that were never particularly
interesting to soft suffer into because
it budgets were small and now, you know,
the TAM is largely labor. And so that's
been I think kind of one of the
reorientations that we've seen the last
few years from kind of financial
productled companies largely to uh you
know software businesses and and kind of
financial services we're at large.
>> Zach you you wrote about your
predictions for 2026. Maybe share one we
we haven't uh gotten to yet around where
things are going where you're
particularly excited.
>> I was at a dinner a couple weeks ago and
so this might not be a prediction. This
might just be a recognition of of of
current truth. Um, but I was at a dinner
recently and someone asked the table a
question. Um, and the question was,
"What's the biggest use case um, of AI
in financial services?" And some people
had answers and then it got to me and
and I I kind of flippantly uh said doing
fraud. It turns out the biggest use case
for AI is fraudsters committing fraud
against financial services companies.
Um, and I said it jokingly and then
realized half like as I was saying it,
oh no, this is actually the correct
answer. Um, the entire table was like,
yeah, okay, that's that's the correct
answer. sadly. Um, and so, you know,
we're at this this point in the
ecosystem where AI has so much potential
to change things. And who's using it the
most? It's the fraudsters. Um, and I
like right now we're at a point where
financial fraud is growing at like like
18 to 20% a year. Uh, which is insane
and it's already a huge market. Um, and
so I guess in that in that vein, um, one
of my predictions for, um, 2026 is
unfortunately, um, financial fraud is
going to continue to accelerate in a way
that we don't quite understand and
probably can't quite feel out and
predict yet. Um, because, you know, it's
it's a cat-and- mouse game, but the
mouse is winning right now. I mean, the
cat the cat will win long term, but the
mouse is winning right now. And so, um,
it's kind of a depressing prediction,
but, uh, I think likely.
>> What What are you guys doing about it?
>> Well, so we we we build an anti-fraud
product suite. Um, this I promise this
was not me teeing up bragging about why,
but I will I I will gladly brag about
it's a hard it's a hard problem to
solve, but if anybody can kind of try to
figure it out.
>> Well, we we can't solve it all. We can
solve pieces of it. So, we build an
anti-fraud product suite. It's called
Protect. Um within that we have this
analysis of every user and every user
action that uh we can assign a score to
to say what's the trustworthiness of
this user this this account this user
action that they're taking. Um and we we
pull this data and build it based on
looking at every user action that's
taken across every fintech company that
we work with. Um plus uh the data that's
coming from the bank account plus device
data plus a zillion other data sets that
we that we match it all with.
>> Um and so it's the first kind of network
linked like cross fintech crossbank uh
type of anti fraud tool. And it's
awesome and and it adds some amazing
signal to to to the companies that we
work with. Um but this is like one of
very many solutions that need to exist.
Um we're starting to get good at
fighting deep fakes as well. I mean like
as an industry and and and plaid
specifically, but like still very early
there. Um but you know this the stuff
that that freaks me out is um you know
have you heard of pig butchering? Um,
for those listening on a podcast, I'll
explain it briefly cuz it's kind of a
gruesome uh term. Um, but it is
basically um when you get a text message
that says, "Hey, how you doing, um, and
that that and you respond to it, don't
ever respond to those, but if you do get
one of those and and and you were to
respond to it, um, they would then
strike up a conversation with you and
eventually they would like find some
complex way to like ask you to give them
money. Um, and when you go up and
execute that transaction, um, you have
just sent money to a total stranger on
the internet and yes, they've stolen the
like that's that that is like in 100% of
cases what happens. Um that used to be
done based on these like like uh human
factories in like Malaysia where they
would like have these people like locked
in rooms sending text messages to to
unassuming people in the US mostly but
but around the world. Um now that's all
AI. You don't need these human factories
anymore. The AI can do all that. Um
India is just getting better and better
and better. Um and like
>> how do we fight that? like because it's
it's a human taking an action that they
think is sending money to a friend and
they've been tricked, but it is fraud,
but it's very hard to to fight that kind
of fraud. So, um
I mean there are so many more tools that
we need to build as an industry
collectively and of course as as plaid
specifically. Totally.
>> We were talking about the different eras
of of fintech. I'm I'm curious what have
been sort of the the different eras of
of plat of of course there was the you
know um sort of the acquisition that
that didn't go through with with with
visa and sort of the ups and downs that
that you guys have had you know
alongside the the macro and obviously
you're in an incredible position right
now is the is talk more about the
different eras of plaid or how the plaid
vision has has evolved or or or you know
or stayed true to the original. So
started Plaid uh started working on the
a thing that wasn't plaid but pivoted
into Plaid in the very end of 2012. We
we launched um we pivoted into what we
were doing in kind of mid late 2013 and
launched to the world in 2014. So um you
know it's it's been a good 11 to 13
years depending on how you you count
that uh series of bad products that we
built first. Um David actually was a
friend and knew us then. Um but I'm not
actually brief aside. Um David, I don't
know if you know this. Um David uh found
Plaid. He was the first investor, led
the seed round uh at Spark.
>> Um actually like sourced the deal as
like you were an associate I think at
Spark at the time. Um then he went to
Goldman uh around the time that Goldman
invested. You weren't involved in the
investment specifically, but you were at
Goldman at that time and like probably
helpful in the background. um then came
to Andre and Andre invested um and has
been like a huge friend and supporter of
of plot over the years. So if we owe a
lot to David and a huge amount of thank
you and he also creates all the
important industry terms.
>> Um so you know the fintech industry owes
a lot to David.
>> I don't know. Um anyway so uh plaid
started started call it let's say 2014
we launched and then 2014 to like 2019
that was all about linking bank accounts
like how do we enable you to link a bank
account so that you can um gain more
access to financial products broadly so
link a bank account so you can pay a
friend on vend link a bank account so
you can get a loan on lending club um
that was kind of phase one kind of 2019
2020 um you know we called this what
like like late um uh like late spring,
like looming spring um continuing to
grow in that vein. Um in 2020 um January
2020, we signed paperwork to sell the
company to Visa. Um and you know, still
late spring, uh we didn't know that CO
was coming. We didn't know that the EDM
music would turn on. Um
>> I remember chatting with you, I think it
was like February or March, you know,
like it was probably March, right when
CO was just beginning. I was like, "Wow,
you really timed that well."
You know, and then and then the business
starts ripping and I was like, "Oh,
that's a very expensive free call
option." Yeah. You know, on the business
and so walking away from that is pretty
>> in an acquisition like at least in our
acquisition, you sign paperwork that
says we're in exclusivity and as soon as
everything is uh cleared, like all the
check boxes are are checked, then the
deal will close. Um, and so we had a
year of exclusivity and and it started
in January of 2020. Um uh and yeah, like
in in call it like late March of 2020 or
maybe early April, we were talking and
it was like, yeah, we have this deal to
sell the company for just over $5
billion and it's fixed price. Um uh Visa
stock price goes is going down. So like
all of the the stock compensation that
we're going to get out of this deal,
man, that's worth a whole lot more as a
percentage of Visa. Like we own a large
chunk of Visa. That that that that seems
interesting. Um uh and then we looked it
through the docs and like they have this
things called like material adverse
event. Um uh so you can get out of a
deal if something crazy happens. And
there was a provision in there that says
you cannot get out of the deal even in
the case of a global pandemic. And like
some lawyer somewhere in some room had
like come up with like oh let's let's
just like add this in. Um and I don't
know we were like oh man this is great.
We got we got everything set. They can't
get out of it in case of a pandemic.
Like we're going to get a huge chunk of
visa. We're going to be off to the
races. Um, and then like the deal took
forever to close because the DOJ was
investigating Visa for being a
monopolist and like all this overhead.
Um, and like kind of for the next the
next phase the EDM music just like
started getting louder and louder and
louder and like summer started happening
and like fintech started growing and
people were stuck at home. They needed
to use digital finance to to live their
financial lives. Um, and so at the end a
year later we looked at and we said um,
for a large variety of reasons it makes
sense for us to part as friends with
Visa. Um, and uh, we'll go our own way.
we'll we'll keep running plat as an
independent entity. Um and then we
raised a big up round and um you know
off to the races. But um you know
through that you tell the company, hey,
we're selling. Okay, great. That's
that's a really hard thing to convince
everybody to still be excited even
though you're selling the company. A
year later, hey, we're not selling. Um
and another very very hard thing uh
because you're telling everybody um you
know, you're not going to get all that
cash that you thought you were going to
get. Like you can't buy the house. I'm
sorry, but we'll try to do a secondary
soon so maybe you can buy a car. Um,
and you have to like really change the
culture. It's like almost a reounding
moment at that point. Um, then you go
through uh the rest of the summer and
that was great. Lots of growth, but then
into like fintech winter and that's
another like like we got we got to all
come together like like our customers
are growing more slowly. Yes, we're
producing great products. Yes, like the
plaid is is growing. Um, but like you
know it's not the growth that we're used
to because we're in in in in fintech
winter. Um, and it's nice to finally be
back in spring, but like there's
definitely a lot of ups and downs on
that journey. Like, um, I think it was
like multiple like refounding or like
multiple crucible moments along the way.
>> Was was there a period in that where you
found your I maybe you always had it uh
but like your second win because at
least from the outside it's felt like
your product velocity really increased
at some point in the last like you know
two and a half years.
>> Yeah. Yeah, it has. I mean I I shifted
my role quite significantly. So like I'm
I'm our chief product officer like I am
in all of the product stuff.
>> Um and a lot of it was like for us
really it was like building the data set
to the size that we can actually run
analytics on it. So we build fraud
scores that look at um your actions
relative to every other user that we see
in our platform and identify if you're
anomalous. If we didn't have enough data
to identify if you were anomalous then
it wouldn't be a relevant score for us
to build. we got to one enough data and
then two we finally figured out how to
like build and watch products quickly.
Um and so that's been like one of the
most fun things for me actually. Weirdly
like
>> I think I was like like not as happy in
the period of like EDM pumping like fast
growth everybody's like throwing money
at fintech like that industry. I think I
was like a little less happy because I
was like I don't think I'm adding
differential value. I think I'm just
like, you know, running as fast as I
possibly can and um, you know, maybe I
make some good decisions, but like, you
know, it all doesn't matter cuz
everything's up and to the right.
>> Um, like I think I was like happier in
that like winter period.
>> I'm like, oh man, like this is this is
where we become an amazing company long
term. Like this is where like, you know,
we prove ourselves and and we really
step up and help our customers. We
launch the next next wave of products
that really matter. Um, but I think I
felt similarly to be honest like you
know having done fintech since I don't
know 2011 like people
you know, that felt early, you know, to
to be investing then and then it's like,
okay, everybody like, you know, found
out that this thing existed. Every
everybody became a fintech investor
from, you know, 2019 to, you know, 2021.
And then everybody's, you know, some of
the best fintech investors in the world
like came out on podcasts and were like,
fintech is dead.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm like,
>> fintech is dead. Everyone should go home
except for people that are building fint
making
people that use it.
>> You guys can leave and just stop
investing in fintech. We we will
continue. the fintech team is still
here, you know, despite the uh the
naming con
um
>> the brand
>> and uh I think that's that's actually
benefited us, you know, and I mean
selfishly, but
>> but I think it's it's tested the people
like the true believers and um yeah, I
in some ways it's brought the community
together, I would argue.
>> Yeah. And and you know the the the
tourists go home like the like and we
saw it on our team even like there were
people that joined Plaid in 2020 when
the the music was loud and it seemed
like the industry to be in
>> and you know then they then they they've
gone and chased the next trend and the
next trend and um well while well we'll
miss them and they're nice people. Um
the people now that are focused on it
are like these are the people like who
really want to be here in the long term
like they deeply believe in the mission
um and you know they're they're in it in
the way that we all want to be in it.
Totally feels great.
>> Where are we now in the in in the cycle?
H
>> how should we think about this moment?
>> Early to mid-spring, I would say we see
like green shoots like lots of
emergence. It's been a pretty good year
for for many parts of fintech and it's
been a shaky year for others. I mean, I
think if you look at the lending
markets, you know, it's it's not as bad
as last year, but it's not as good as it
was. And um
there are elements of the economy that
are pretty scary and parts of like a
large part of of consumer spending is
being propped up by a small number of
people. And so like there are all these
things that are scary but for the most
part um you know you continue to see
companies that are building very solid
products. Um you do see like great uh
startups emerging um but they they look
a little different than they used to.
Like they're thinking more responsibly
about markets in the long term. like
they're more thinking about uh you know
profitability and growth and um you're
also seeing like the insanity of of of
AI funding go on kind of like in AI land
and some of this starting to bleed into
fintech because you're seeing these like
fintech AI uh products start to come. So
um I would say spring like lots of green
shoots, lots of exciting stuff. Um still
some you know still some snow in the
background that's snow melt is still
happening. Um but uh looking pretty
optimistic right now.
>> Awesome. Okay. So let let's let's wrap
on just what does 2026 and the near-term
f future look like? Uh David, how we're
approaching an agency.
>> It still feels like we're in early
innings, you know, uh even spring in and
AI land as well. Um uh you know, so just
incredibly excited and enthusiastic by
the momentum we're seeing, you know, for
again largely software companies selling
into financial institutions. That's kind
of been our orientation in the fintech
ecosystem. Um, you know, again, I sat on
the on the board of a a company called
Moment, which we, you know, described
earlier that is uh now bringing some
largest wealth management platforms
online. You'll see them, you know, they
announced LPL. We have another a number
of other large institutions that we'll
be announcing uh early next year. Um,
you know, companies like Modernify,
which have built uh, you know,
bank-to-bank deposit marketplaces that
are really starting to to grow and see
significant volume in that in that
network. Um and again just more more
broadly um you know really excited by
the opportunity for AI to actually do
the work you know within within these
institutions and and the momentum and
excitement you know you know there to
adopt you know new products
>> and and are we excited David they're
they're because they're they're such
great customers or because they're so
they're so underserved because they're
or they're finally transitioning or or
why have we narrowed in on on that focus
as one we're particularly excited about?
I mean, look, the the industry is still
massive, right? Like if you if I look
back at at even just Goldman Sachs, and
I know use them as a as an example
often, but like the the entire firm was
uh you know, they called the the kind of
middle and back office the the
federation. You know, again, these were
were folks living in Excel largely, not
using Excel as a modeling tool, but
using Excel to track work. And so
there's just such opportunity to build
amazing software products to solve
everything from, you know, compliance to
payments to treasury management to again
all of the kind of uh, you know, manual
work that goes into making the financial
services industry tick. Um, and I think
AI is again creating kind of a new
window and wedge opportunity for
entrepreneurs to kind of, you know,
build software companies that that
couldn't have existed years ago. And and
again, I think the the appetite, you
know, for adopting new products and new
software to solve some of those problems
is is more real than ever. Um because
again, the most senior people at these
institutions, uh, you know, can
intuitively understand the impact that
AI is having on their business. And so I
think there's just a lot more
conversation and momentum happening at
the board level. um you know and it's
making the enterprise sort of sales
cycles you know for for many of even our
early stage companies happen a lot
faster than than I've seen in in you
know my experience you know investing in
this space. Zach, how about you and h
how you think about things things at
Plaid and more broadly?
>> We
this past year launched, as I said, the
the anti-fraud suite on Protect uh
called Protect and um tons and tons of
acceleration behind that. Uh we launched
a credit score uh a modern consumer
credit score that's based on your
income, your expenses, the things that
you do in your daily life. So your score
goes up if you have a higher income. Uh
your score goes down if you start having
way higher personal expenses, like the
logical credit score. So we launched
that, it's called Lens Score. we
launched that last year. Like these two
things are going to be major drivers for
us in the coming year. So um
distributing this this this new version
of a credit score um into all the
lenders and then of course on the
protect side like helping fight this
this AIdriven financial fraud that we're
seeing. Um and then for us like you know
we're we're we're back to back to like
hiring and recruiting and and and
growing and um so you know despite the
fact that fintech has been through these
waves like I still think that plat is
like one of the most amazing places to
work. Please tell tell all your friends.
Um if you want to work with big data, if
you want to have have a hu huge impact
on consumer's lives, um again financial
freedom is the the core focus of uh of
what we do. Um uh and then you don't you
want to have an opportunity. We we try
to think of ourselves as like the most
cons consumer sorry the most customer
centric employer where you know we put
engineers in the customer so they're
actually talking to them like we think
it's an incredibly fun way to work. Um
so like not forward deployed to
engineering but Ford deployed company.
Um, so you know, tell all your fans.
We're hiring lots of people and uh I
think it's going to be a great 2026.
>> Zack, David, you guys are pioneers in in
in in the in the space in the category
and I can't wait to have you both back
in 2030 and we can talk about how the
how the space has evolved. Uh, thanks so
much.
>> Do it sooner.
>> Yeah, it's so far away.
>> Exactly. We don't want you to wait, you
know.
>> That's true. We don't have to wait every
5 years. Uh, Zack, David, thanks so much
for coming to the podcast. Great. Good
to see you both.