In the past 10 years, I think the
question about the intelligence or
artificial intelligence has uh captured
people's imagination. Uh I'm one of
them, but it took me about 10 years try
to really understand uh can we actually
make understanding intelligence a truly
scientific or mathematical problem to
formalize it. You probably will get some
of my opinion and also the the facts
about it and probably will change your
view what is intelligence is which is
also a very so certain process for me.
How do we clarify uh some
misunderstandings the common
misunderstandings about the
intelligence? Through this journey uh
maybe we'll gain a entirely new view
about what we really have done right in
the past 10 years. The practice of
artificial intelligence the mechanism we
have implemented the all the mechanism
behind all the large models deep
networks and the large models are truly
are and uh the true natures and uh hence
understand their limitations and also
what it takes to truly build a system
that has intelligent behaviors or
capabilities. I think we have reached
the point right we'll be able to address
what's the next for understanding even
more advanced form of intelligence
what's the difference between
compression and abstraction difference
between memorization and understanding I
think of future those are the big open
problems for all of us to study
MLST is supported by cyber fund link in
the description
>> the idea of having to traffic and
squishy people in order to make our
systems go is not immediately appealing.
Let's put it that way.
>> This episode is sponsored by Prolific.
>> Let's get few quality examples in. Let's
get the right humans in to get the right
quality of human feedback in. So, so
we're trying to make human data or human
feedback. We treat it as an
infrastructure problem. We try to make
it accessible. We make it cheaper. We
effectively democratize access to this
data. Professor Ma, it's amazing to have
you on MLST. Welcome.
>> Thank you for having me.
>> So, normally I ask guests to introduce
themselves, but given your your stature
in the field, I think it's best that
that that I give you an introduction.
So, um, Yimar is a worldleading expert
in deep learning and artificial
intelligence. He's the inaugural
director of the school of computing and
data science at Hong Kong University and
director of the Institute of Data
Science at the University of Hong Kong.
He's also a visiting professor at UC
Berkeley where he previously served as a
full professor in electrical engineering
and computer science. He's an ITE E
fellow, ACM fellow and CM fellow whose
pioneering work on sparse representation
and low rank structures has
fundamentally shaped modern computer
vision and machine learning. His
recently published book learning deep
representations of data distributions
proposes a mathematical theory of
intelligence built on two principles
pasimony and self-consistency.
This framework has led to whitebox
transformers known as crate
architectures where every component can
be derived from first principles rather
than empirical guesswork. So um
professor mah tell me about your book.
>> You know about you know uh eight or
seven years ago you know you know deep
networks uh deep learning has been
pretty you know changed the practice of
machine learning or artificial
intelligence uh in the past decade. Um
about uh eight years ago I had a chance
to get back to Berkeley and um gave me a
chance to look into this uh topics more
deeply try to understand it from more
principled approach and hence uh the
book is kind of a summarizing the kind
of progress we made in the past uh you
know eight or beyond years myself my
group as well as many colleagues uh
trying to understand uh the principles
behind Um the deep networks explained it
uh from our first principle and uh in
that journey we also seems to embark on
um a little bit beyond that uh find uh
something probably more general behind
that is the uh the intelligence at a
certain level of intelligence and hence
um when I get back to joined Hong Kong U
about two years ago had a chance to
design or redesign some of uh curriculum
to reflect those uh some of the progress
updates in our field, the rapid progress
in our field. Um so my students and
colleagues decided that maybe it's time
to uh systematic organize uh this body
of knowledge
and uh reflect as a as a textbook as
well as a new course uh which I'm
teaching this semester and uh likely
will be offered as well at Berkeley next
semester. So this is actually a first
time probably we try to uh provide a
more principle approach to explain the
the deep networks um as well as some
principle of uh intelligence
>> and these principles are panimony and
self-consistency.
So it's it's an ambitious idea that
these principles could explain natural
and artificial intelligence. What do you
mean by that?
>> Intelligence artificial or natural uh or
whatever uh adjectives you add to
intelligence uh we have to be very
specific. It's a very loaded world,
right? I mean, even intelligence
itselfves may have different levels um
different um stages, right? So, it's
high time we clarify that concept
scientifically or mathematically, right?
Um then so that we'll be able to talk
about uh study intelligence the
mechanism behind it at each level. uh
there are some more unified principle
behind even different stages of
intelligence there's there's something
in common there also s are different so
it's high time we we we do that one of
the intelligence at the level is that
common to animals are human right human
we are animals that int level of
intelligence is what we think are very
common to all life which is how memory
how we learn knowledges about the
external world and then memorize as part
of our memory and use that to predict to
react to the world help us make
decisions predict and make better
decisions with for survival and so on so
forth that's very very common and this
is the level of intelligence we're
talking about very much for the book as
well right and um hence for this level
of intelligence uh how our memory works
uh today we also have a fancy word for
memory we call it a world model Okay. Um
and it's how this how we develop such a
memory such a world model and how the
model gets evolved and uh how we use it
that's actually this is the level of we
talk. So we actually believe that uh for
this level of intelligence for how our
memory formed and how they work is
precisely the two principles are
incredibly important. um and we believe
they're necessary uh is that
me memory or knowledge is precisely try
to discover what's predictable about the
world. Hence um for all understand all
such information are have intrinsically
very low degree of freedom. we call the
lowdimensional structures and uh hence
the way to pursue such knowledge is
precisely through uh trying to find the
most simple representation of the data
and uh hence compression denoising
dimension reduction is actually all just
different words to pursue such knowledge
such structure and hence that's the word
captured by the word parimony
finding you know explain making things
as simple as possible but not any
simpler right um so this is Einstein
says this word uh this the sentence
Einstein used to describe science
actually this is also what the
intelligence at least at this level is
precisely doing the same thing um the
second part of the sentence not any
simpler precisely says consistent
consistency make sure your memory is
actually consistent with be able to um
recreate simulate the world just right
um not any similar. If you're simpler,
you may lose part of the um the uh
predictivity uh predictivity uh and also
ability to predict it well. And so
that's actually the those two actually
uh coexist we believe and those are two
principles parsimmony and the
consistency or subconsistency are
actually the two characteristic about
how our memory works. So we want to have
understanding which carves the world up
by the joints which represents the
important invariances in the world and
the thesis is I think that compression
might be necessary for understanding. My
possible concern with that is that what
we are doing with machine learning is
representing extent examples of a long
phoggenetic
tree of evolution. Mhm.
>> So to what extent does knowing their
representation now help us? Do we also
need to know how they evolved and where
they might go in the future?
>> The the process to acquire knowledge
to gain information about our side world
that's a
compression. Uh find what is
compressible,
what has orders, what phenomena has
orders. uh has low dimension structures
that allow us to predict to rule out uh
variabilities to predict world uh
tomorrows or predict world better in
that sense. Um so in a sense that uh
that is ability we uh believe is really
what intelligence is all about uh at
least the the common intelligence we're
talking about right we can talk about
the more higher level intelligence later
uh um and if you look at the the history
of life how life was developed um um so
we actually come up to believe right uh
uh you know you know the the the
mechanism that we laws that governs the
physical law world we call the physics
right but what is the mechanism governs
the evolution of life I think it's
intelligence right even the process you
mentioned that uh through evolution and
um life evolves um precisely they they
learn more and more knowledge about the
world and they encode them through DNA
to pass it on to next generation and
that is a compressing that's a that's a
process to compress logic
that learned about the world through our
DNAs. But the the the the mechanism to
update it is actually very brutal, very
brutal force and um through you know
random mutation and the natural
selection. Yes, it does evolve. It does
advance but at a huge cost of resource
time and also very unpredictable
which if you if you're acute you
probably observe there's some similarity
with how current big model evolves right
um many many groups try uh without
principle try and error empirical and um
the lucky one survive and gets advocated
uh you everywhere and become very very
popular right dominate the practice so
so in a sense that you can make the
allergy right I think to the people you
know students ask me at which stage our
artificial intelligence uh is at today
um then there's already a allergy in in
nature right we are very much at the
early stage of the life form right and
so hence that is a compression process
that's a process that also gain
knowledge about the world But of course
later on we develop uh individual
animals to develop the brain develop you
know neural systems develop uh senses
including visual and touch and so on. So
we actually you start to use a very very
different mechanism to learn to compress
our observations to learn knowledge and
to build memories of world and even
individuals start to have that ability
rather than just inherit knowledge from
their DNAs. So that's a different stages
uh about uh and then that part of the
knowledge is not no longer encoded in
our genetics in our genes but also in
our brains.
Um and that's actually that's actually a
level of intelligence we talk about most
of the time these days you know which is
common to animals which is common to to
humans and the le the knowledge the or
the intelligence we talk about what
brain functions. Yeah, I mean I I think
we would definitely agree with the
statement that intelligence as a system
produces artifacts. So Shallay's example
is a road building network. It produces
roads and the system has adaptivity
because it can create new roots where
they weren't there before.
>> And then there's the question of well
there are many ways to compress a thing.
>> So some ways of compression represent
the world at a deep abstract level and
some don't. So we might argue that LLMs
today even though they do compress the
data they only compress it in a
superficially semantic way.
>> And then there's this notion of well
maybe we agree that intelligence is
about the synthesis of new knowledge. So
it's the acquisition of new knowledge
but we can only do that if the knowledge
we already have represents the world at
a deep abstract level. So rather than it
being random mutations in evolution,
it's very very structured because the
processes are physically instantiated
which means rather than just doing
something completely random, it's guided
by the process which created the
manifold hypothesis comes to mind which
is this idea that all natural data falls
on some lowdimensional you know
structure you know with a low intrinsic
dimension. And the other thing that
springs to mind is I mean I'm a fan of
geometric deep learning which is this
idea of you know we should imbue
inductive prior in the system which
represent symmetries and and geometric
structures in in the world and and I
think as a principle that's deeply
embedded in in this idea.
>> Exactly. Um if if you look at my my
whole life I have written four books
right. uh my early interest is studying
is computer vision um and the first book
is vision and from that work I study
multiview geometry from that work I in
my whole book the the all the four book
is actually about the one theme I
realized that it's about structure in
the data especially all reflected know
them the first book of sweet division um
the last chapter I realized precisely
about what importance the symmetry plays
in our perception right and we perceive
object we naturally has a so human being
we remember our vision
we only recognize a long time ago right
these days people oh it's about the
vision is about recre 3D absolutely not
right all the people says we just
multiple images we create a whole point
clouds mesh sign distance function lurf
gion splatter right we We create a
scene. See, I can see from multiple
angles.
Is this 3D understanding or you create
some videos like Sora look at it looks
good for you know absolutely not. Right?
This is not the representation
or understanding of a world model.
Right? Our understanding is far beyond
getting a whole bunch of you know point
clouds or goshes better we can view from
different angles.
Right? Have you noticed that when we see
something, we get excited because we
understand the 3D, we understand the
content, we parse it already in our
brain, but the machine has no idea what
the heck is in there. Okay, it's just a
bunch of point clouds. It's a depth map.
Okay, we when we see this change angle,
we saw 3D. We already automatically
recognize this is a hand, this is a
body, this is a cup, this is a this is
apple, right? We do that. We fill in
that information with our brain. We
think machine once they can recruit the
3D they all understand that this is
completely wrong. Okay. Many many work
they say we're building 3D model by
creating something for people to look
at. That's complete out of purpose. So
look at our vision. Our vision model
right we have hypoc campus we have our
ID code is highly structured. We
understand the relationships
between our view ccentric, object
ccentric and aloscentric reputation.
Right? Neuroscientists understand this
very very well. Right? Scientists
understand this very well but not
computer scientists. Right? Not computer
vision scientist. Um some do. See for
example I give you example right in
order to do spatial now we actually did
a test with you on the corner about a
year ago. Test all the you know top
multi-model models you know huge models
GPT you know that uh GMI right to do
very simple test the the title of the
work called a eyes wide shot right
and it's a very simple test just test
the given images for the those language
model or a big model multimodel highly
trained highly commercialized models
that do they understand the reasoning
spatial reasoning what is on the left of
something
how many objects there is in space right
what is beh behind something, what's on
top of something very simple spatial.
The question requires a little bit, not
even very deep spatial understanding.
But all the models fails miserably and
the majority of them actually even worse
than random guess right only I think
only Gemini and uh GPD uh is a little
bit above human a little bit about the
random guess far below human
understanding. Right? So that's that's
the status right if you do those meaning
that you know those act 3D understanding
is very very difficult but human we do
this effortlessly right so I can easily
point to you right please hand me the
the the bottle to your left if you want
to find let's say a shopping center
right say go through the door turn right
go to the once you get outside of the
building um head south right so through
this this Remember just through this
simple sentence
already we switch from viewcentric to
object centric to alocentric right so
our bra if we don't have this kind of
model this kind of highly structured 3D
models forget about you know people talk
about embodied AI or world model right
we cannot conduct this very simple
spatial references
interacting we have this world model is
not to visualize.
We build a 3D model to interact, to
manipulate, to influence,
right? We're not building a 3D model
just to, oh, this looks like I can
change my view, look at it from this
view or that view, right? Just
visualize. No, turn 360 degree to
visualize. No, we don't do that. That's
not our purpose. Okay. Unfortunately,
but there, you know, it gets distracted
for that kind of uh visualization. It
looks cool but uh almost to to to us if
you really work on robotics uh for all
kind you know navigation local motion
manipulation they're actually pretty uh
the usage is pretty limited. I won't
necessarily say they're useless but they
are actually pretty limited.
We should introduce the coding rate
formula. I did have a question about
that which is there is a there's an
epsilon on there. So there there's a bit
of a question of how how do we tune that
and and what does that mean? We should
also bring we've been talking about this
a little bit this um this concept of an
LDR so a linear um discriminative
representation and just more broadly
with these inductive prior there's
always the question of when we do
abstraction to model regularities in the
universe there's always a little bit
left over isn't there so to to what
extent can we think of these things as
natural
>> actually you touch upon about the deep
stone you touch upon a very very deep
question uh we actually uh it actually
took me almost 30 years to understand it
to be honest right we did mention that
early on when we do try to differentiate
different measure different volumes it
turns out lossy coding is necessary it's
not just something that uh is something
hacky it's actually turns out to be
necessary and to do lossy coding in fact
we recently we start to realize that
noise actually be you know plays very
different roles and uh yet it's very
confounded very confusing to many people
Even um this is something actually my
students will see to realize we actually
probably will have some papers about it.
I can elucidate this a little bit. If
you think about the whole diffusion den
noiseis and model right people very
popular right now to do um why do we add
noise to data right and to the whole
world because we don't know where the
distribution is right so there is a
phrase everybody knows all roads to Rome
right so why is that has anyone give a
thought to why all roads to Rome
because very simple at some point in
history Rome builds the road to reach
the whole Oh, right. That's a diffusion
process.
Then if you want to know Rome, then you
do the den noise. You follow the same
way back you get to where the no room
is. So that's the no dimensional
structure. That's where the knowledge
is, right? That's the osis is right. So
hence it's a very natural process that
we add noise is adding noise to the is
precisely we building roads and the
noising brings us back remember where we
come from and so on and that's a big
slope we have to add noise to reach the
whole earth there's another actually
there's another noise
right remember we only have isolated
sample even we talk about manifolds
Right? But how many points you have on
the manifes? How many points you
observe? They're always finite. Right?
But why do you call it a continum?
Why do you collect dots as lines,
planes, surfaces? When do you do that?
Hence, noise plays another role within
the manifold. Even you have finite
samples,
if you allow lossy coding, if you allow
packing spheres in that things start to
connect. You start to connect. Noise is
very important to help to connect the
dots, right? We all know the phenomena
of percolation, right? We see raindrops
on the floor. You only see two phases,
right? One phase is all the dots are
isolated. Another phase is all things
gets wet. You never see anything into in
the middle because there's a sharp face
transition. Once the the the sphere once
the dots the density gets high enough
they collects everything. Right? Maybe
that's a phase transition we reach we
realizing a connected plane is a better
solution to explain all the data more
parsimmonious more economic.
The cost to memorize all the dots versus
memorize other plane start to switch.
Maybe abstraction has something to do
with that. I don't know. But from a
compression point of view, this can
already allow us to explain when do we
go from zero dimension samples to prefer
a low dimensional manifolds
and also how go from that low
dimensional manifold to reach the rest
of the world. Right? So you can see even
in this process noise is already playing
this epsilon plays different roles and
as at some point they gets collected
right around the surface and that's we
still try to figure out what happens but
at this big two phases uh we already
know right the role of epsilon actually
plays different roles right um and I
think the the definitely in the past
many years uh our understanding about
the subject how do we compress how do we
uh pursue the lowdimensional structure
from finite samples. It's a quite our
understanding about this problem has
truly advanced dramatically. I'm very
happy honestly this is a question
baffles me when I was a graduate
students. uh you can see even my early
work about the lossy coding lossy
compression reflected my bafffulness
about it and I'm really feel very uh
thrilled that I recently start to
understand those things in a more
unified more not only theoretical way
but also even algorithmic way
>> yeah it's so fascinating that we can
look out the window
>> and we we ignore so much detail we don't
look at the leaves on the roads we we
just find that structure and that's why
when I watched your presentation I was
very intrigued when you said that
denoising iterative denoising is is a
form of of compression. I wanted to
mention your ICML 2024 so last year it
was in Vienna right with with Wang and
you found that when you have loss
surfaces using using this technique they
are dramatically different they're very
smooth there's no kind of harsh local
minima and so on what's the intuition
for that
>> in fact the phenomena our understanding
about those phenomena is actually going
back when we early days we study
sparsity
um you know when your data lies on very
low dimensional uh sparse surfaces uh
planes right low dimensional planes also
of the planes or low rank matrix right
and in there we learned a very big
lesson the object function to evaluate
those sparity or low dimensionality uh
those function are highly nonlinear
nonconvex
um but yet you know traditionally in our
orthodox understanding about the l
convex optimization is they're always
hard right and the general class is n
hard and there's a lot local spirus uh
local minima you get stuck with local
minima you there's some stagnant
critical points flat surface so
basically the worst picture is very
worse right it's a nightmare
uh but through the study of those low
dimensional structure uh sparse
structure and that's was actually
featured in our my previous book right
high dimensional a low dimensional
structure of high dimensional data
analysis we actually realized that if a
lot of long convex problem even the
optimization problem had long convex
landscape. If those problem or if those
measure arises from nature very natural
resource those structure actually are
very highly regular highly has symmetry
the landscape actually are extremely
benile
right quite contrary to our common
understanding about linear optimization
at all right this is complete 180°ree uh
flip of views In fact, even the higher
dimension helps. The higher the
dimension, the better. We call it the
blessing of dimensionality. So those
regularity, those symmetry will tell us
the landscape of this object function
are actually beautiful, right? And uh
first of all, they're highly regular.
There's no staging. There's no flat
surface. There's no too many spirits
local minima. And even the local minima,
they already have very clear geometric
or statistical meaning. And hence those
landscape are very aminable for very
simple algorithm to find the optimal
solution such as graded descent which in
almost indirectly explain why even we're
doing even more than training neuronet
networks and many more we're searching
uh low dimensional distribution in very
high dimension spaces but somehow greed
always end up with somewhere nice. Okay.
Yeah, fine. You can run a long time but
somehow you always end up those land
landscapes are not that hard to traverse
traverse right. So it actually be
precisely because those object function
are highly regular. Hence now get back
to the rate reduction object function
right if you look at the object function
it's not something arbitrary right it's
counting the volume of the whole minus
the parts right it's something extremely
objective right it's not like a loss
function people come up with randomly oh
add this term weighted sum add different
weights you know if you use this you
know sort of a empirical penalty or
empirical even some kind of ad hoc So
all the terms are describing physical
volumes of the data right. Hence you
should expect those are the quantity
arise in nature. Then from our lesson we
realize indeed actually that actually
those object function has very benile
landscapes uh even the local minima not
only the global minima corresponding
solutions that are give you authoral
subspaces even the local ones right
there not the global optimal ones they
have similar geometric structures right
and there's no other weird
critical points that will slow down the
search for those minimas so that's
actually quite interesting So you can
see this this revelation allow us to
understand right where maybe
intelligence is precisely exploit and
harnessing those things. So there is
actually a misunderstanding about you
know last 10 years when we understand
intelligence more and more
there is a very big misunderstanding
about intelligence right in machine you
you you you study you know maybe machine
learning theory right we have a tendency
to believe intelligence especially
intelligence and nature is designed to
solve the hardest problem the worst case
I actually beg to differ intelligence is
precise the ability to identify what is
easy to address first, what is easy to
learn, what is natural to learn first.
Then only when that has been done and
the resource permit, they start to get
into more and more advanced tasks.
Not everybody needs to learn advanced
mathematics to supply animals don't.
Right? Nature find what is the easiest
things with minimal energy, minimal
effort to learn the most logic so they
survive the best. Right? Again this is
the principle of parimony at play.
There's another level of resource
parimony at play here. Right? Hence once
you realize this you realizing
understanding intelligence should be
really understand what's really most
common.
Right? the low dimensional structure
most easy ones smooth ones benile
distribution easy to get get away with a
few samples fewer samples right uh and
very easy to formulate in fact that's
what how science progress you know a lot
of the physical models you know Newton's
law they're very simple they discover
the simple ones then we reach gradually
reach to general relativity and then to
quantum mechanics those equation gets f
more complicated later right so this is
h the same process we identify what is
the most common first right what is the
most easiest task first hence we don't
want to many of the machine learning
theory try to tend to so derive a bonds
for the worst cases I think that's we
probably should think twice right
>> I love that character characterization
it's um similar to the least action
principle in in physics
>> exactly in in a sense we solve problems
by taking many many steps in different
directions I think we still leave a
little bit of entropy open we don't do
pure hill climbing but collect
Collectively we acquire these stepping
stones and the totality of that process
as we solve very complex problems. But I
wanted to touch on you raised a very
interesting point which is um we notice
that when we have very large deep
learning models they tend to almost
self-regularize and they they learn
better and there's this phenomenon of
double descent and and all of this. Tell
me about that. Fascinating question
actually you uh this question actually
needs to um really u bring me back to
early days when I try to understand deep
learning um when deep aris there's a lot
of phenomena we try to understand I'm
I'm one of those right try to understand
those phenomenas u you know some
something there's some good about
dropout something about the you know
thresholding different thresholding
there's something about uh normalization
then also come to somehow the model are
very big um and parameters a lot somehow
the deep network course has uh do not
have a tendency to overfit somehow they
still generalize okay right and then of
course people realize and there's a sort
of a uh rather unlike the re you know
the traditional classical bias um virus
trade-off but there's tier double
descent
I actually wrote a couple papers about
it and um about the normalization about
around 2000 um or late uh uh 2019
I I really told my student we should
stop not to explain those isolated
phenomena we only see we're like the
blind mental elephants each one say a
little piece each theory try to explain
a little bit I think there should be a
total total explanation to this if we
get the big picture all those are just
the consequences or implications of that
suddenly you know at that time We start
to touch upon the the the concept of
maybe that the the proc of deep network
are optimizing something
the layer wise is realizing optim
they're optimizing objective that
promoting parimony promoting no
dimensionality once we realize actually
I was quite thrilled so then I told my
student from now on we will no longer
write any papers or about overfitting
why
Because if the neuronet networks is try
to the operators try to compress try to
realize certain contracting map
compressed volume then you will never
overfit right even I over parameterize
it will never overfit simple example if
I have data lies on a straight line a
one-dimensional curve whatever I can
embed this one dimensional line in a two
dimension three dimension or a million
dimension But if my operator is always
layer-wise at each iteration, my
operator is always just shrinking
my solution towards the line in all
directions.
I would never lower it. Even I
overparameterize embedded the line into
a billions of dimension. I have a
billions of parameter. But collectively
all those billions of parameter are all
shrinking my solution, pushing the
solution, denoise it, compress it
towards the line, right? like a power
iteration just like a PCA right power
iteration is in regardless of what the
dimension embedded computing the first
singular values right it's always
powerful converge with the same speed
you never over so compression by nature
if the operator are performing
compression or denoising which means
this process will no longer overfit
anything right if you conduct it right
if you converge the solution will
converge on the is the structure you
desire for.
>> That raises a natural question. We were
interviewing Andrew Wilson from NYU and
he's got this, you know, several papers
about implicit biases where you kind of
have a combination of, you know, hard
biases of symmetries and and everything
in in between. And if what you're saying
is true, then why do we need inductive
biases at all? Could we not pair back a
little bit and just have really big
models?
>> No, I think see this is the thing,
right? Exactly. So, this is the thing.
Um um I was uh you know early on people
don't understand deep networks and
there's a lot of empirical uh trial and
error people try to tends to use this
the phrase inductive bias to either as
some kind of magical sauce that either
explain the failures or success of you
do certain way to the neuronet networks
design or how do you train the neuronet
networks to be honest for for a long
time I never understood what the
inductive bias is um and maybe some
regularization Some people is learning
some structures about network about the
data. Um but nowadays in my recent work
I said that probably from at least from
what I understand um all the inductive
bias should be uh formulated as first
principle right at least from we were
able to for example deduce uh all the
different network architectures
including the recent white box crate or
transformer-l like or redunet like uh
reset like architecture or mixture of
expert like architecture all from the
only inductive bias
is assuming your data distribution you
are pursuing are low dimensional. Okay,
you can already get the form the the
main architecture or form of operator of
for each layer as a red structure
mixture of expert structure and and
those operator per layer are precisely
conducting denoising compression or
contrasting. Are there additional
assumption you can make? Yes, you can.
For example, if I my job is not just to
compress the data as it is. I also
wanted to induce I wanted to for example
in object recognition I also want to
enforce make all data I want my
classification to be translational
environment which is symmetry right if
you allow my task will be environ action
I want to compress them together voila
what do you get you can then you still
through compression then you get a
convolution naturally as the structure
for the compression operator so
convolution is not what we impose upon.
is actually results from the first
principle the the quote unquote
inductive bias assume you want to
compress your data also you want your
compression to respect translation
environment or rotation environments
that's the result that is the
characteristic of the compression
operator for you to achieve that task
right so there's a lot of um so we don't
want to build in the the the inductive
bus While we are searching for the
solution, the inductive bias in my
understanding is should be the very
assumption we make in the very
beginning. The rest should be deduction.
The rest should have no induction
anymore. Otherwise, we're doing trial
and error, right? The inductive we so
basically when we build the theory, we
should have done all the inductive
observations, experiment and assumptions
already. The good theory should start
with the very few inductive bias or
assumptions or axioms then the rest
should be deductive. I call that first
principle. We've been speaking about
pasimony which is what to learn and
self-consistency is about how to learn
and we can sketch out a journey I
suppose from control theory to learning
and and also this this methodology has
some interesting um results I think
around um you know the continual
learning problem so let's sketch that
out
>> you can see right so the the compression
um um or the the even the rate reduction
to try to pursue the data distribution
and also So transform it and that's the
one way direction. there's almost
there's no
theoretical guarantee either your data
is sufficient to identify that you know
you may started with very very few
samples there's no way the data is
sufficient I mean may the apple there
are five types maybe I only say four
types right so and then but that process
goes on you do compress what you have
and the reach a memory right and there's
no guarantee the even during that
process you may not get stuck Maybe
there's not enough iterations you may so
memory you get may not be accurate may
not be correct hence how do we check how
do I further develop evolve improve my
memory or make sure my memory actually
be able to authentically predict this is
a work model the model is accurate right
so you actually have to decode it you
can think about the memory formation is
a encoding process then from my memory I
want to decode I want to predict what's
going to happen next second from what I
observe right now or at night I may want
to dream what happen right so that's
actually the decoding is actually allows
us to check if my memory serves to be
right right how accurate I can predict
next step so hence this actually already
form a sort of autoenccoding framework
now of course autoenccoding if I have
access to both the observation and my
memory just like our training our big
data models I have control on both ends.
I can just force auto encoding back end
to end, right? The people like to talk
about it. But in our natural um in a
natural setting, in animal human
setting, we don't have control on both
ends, right? We only have control
probably control of our own brain,
what's inside our brain, right? We never
really quite have access to measure if
my prediction of the 3D world for
example, right? the the the frame of the
picture is rectangular. Do I ever
measure it?
Right? You don't have to measure it, but
somehow everybody believes, you know,
the model is correct. How do we do that?
Right? Hence, there's actually a
self-correcting process. In fact, you
know, this is actually probably the idea
goes the idea actually goes back to
Noble Veer, right? And how animal be
able to correct its error without see
cats can capture something very
accurately. or even make one single
mistakes, they can correct that very
clearly. Right? So somehow they're
they're be able to build a world model
very consistent, self-consistent with
the world without actually physically
measure their errors, right? So hence
this is the idea about you actually loop
it back to your brain and close the
loop, right? and allows you to constant
predict and based on your prediction and
your observations check if there's a
difference still difference between your
predictive prediction and your
observation within your brain
very if there's error and using that
error to correct turns out um this is a
work with my student turns out you
cannot do this of course the our
observation will lose information right
why uh we introduce noise or lose loose
dimension, loose information. But turns
out as long as the distribution of the
world, the data, the distribution of the
world is low dimensional enough. Even
your encoding process, your observation
pro perception process is no you this is
still doable if the precisely when the
distribution of the data outside world
has enough structure is highly low
dimension and hence your brain has
enough degree of freedom to discern any
differences. So this is actually quite
interesting revelation to for us to
realize that the low dimensionality is
not just some or technical assumption.
It's actually necessary for this kind of
closed loop learning to be possible and
once you be able to close loop then you
actually constantly observe constantly
predict hence you can constantly use
your memory to predict and correct it.
Hence support continuous learning even
lifelong learning right our memory Rome
is not built in one day our memory is
never built in one day we constantly
improve it constantly revise it and this
is the mechanism of intelligence
hence this mechanism is itself is
already generalizable hence you don't
need to add the adjective general
general in front of intelligence there's
no point of calling general intelligence
if If you implement the intelligence
mechanism correctly, it's already
generalizable. The knowledge learned by
this mechanism at any point of time may
not be generalizable. The mechanism
does. Right? This is a very big
confusion. We think if I accumulate
enough knowledge, it's generalizable.
No, it's not. Will never be. Any
scientific theory by definition being
scientific is falsifiable, which means
it's limited, right? can only explain
the world up to certain point or certain
accuracy. There's always room for
improvement. The scientific activity,
our ability to revise our memory to
acquire new memory,
that is a generalizable ability. That is
intelligence, right? Through natural
selection early days, through our
feedback control, feedback correction,
through the human history of trial and
error, imp accumulating empirical
knowledge, through scientific discovery
is all doing this, right? That is common
behind intelligence, right? Not the
memory accumulated up to a certain
point. So even we manage to memorize the
whole world the knowledge we have in the
whole world we will no longer be able to
apply when we find oursel in a new
environment in a new situation observe
some phenomena we have never seen before
right hence that's the limitation of you
know you try to gain general general
intelligence through just accumulate
enough knowledge right
>> we should talk about your crate series
of architecture so crate stands for
coding rate reduction transformer and
you made some very interesting
discoveries So for example multi head
self attention can be derived as a
gradient step on rate coding and also
MLPS as spifying um spification
operators and and also you were talking
about how something like a transformer
could be described in a principled way.
There there's this interesting thing,
isn't there, that we we we designed the
well, we didn't even design them. We we
kind of empirically tried with lots of
different things and we happened upon
the transformer. But something like that
can actually come about from a first
principles approach. If you look at the
past decade also evolution of also it's
kind of natural selection process for
the big models right from early days
Alex let l Alex letter VGG or um then
reset or uh transformers by the way this
is just one of those for survivors right
as I said just like le selections right
remember don't people don't forgot
there's a there's a time there's a very
popular areas called AutoAs, AutoML,
right? People tends to do random search
for better architectures, right? Somehow
why only a few survive? There must be a
reason, right? They must capture certain
structures. They must did something
right. Now from our understanding so
far, the resonate actually capturing the
the fact that each layer should be doing
compar doing optimization.
The resonance precisely reflect the
iterative optimization architecture.
Right. And
precisely capture fact. We're trying to
cluster compress what's similar and
discern or classify what's different or
contrast what's dissimilar. Right? And
you want to develop different experts,
right? We call them experts, we call
them as cluster, we call them group. So
be it, right? And the transformer again,
right? Let's capture what is the
correlation self attention. is precisely
compute what's what is the correlation
in the data coariance in the data what's
correlated and using that to further
spify further classify things to
organize the the the distributions they
must do something there some somehow
close to something right right so also
it's almost like a belief for us right
if we believe there's something right
then we should be able to derive create
from first principle have a very clear
unified understanding I think we're sort
managed to do that at least. So for the
law structure we discovered so far
provide rather unified explanation to
what they have done to be honest the
early even maybe our early earliest mo
motives try to explain to understand
what we have done but once we understood
it we realize that we can go much
further right and realize even the
current architectures there's a lot of
room for improvement not only we can
dramatically simplify them you can see
in the past after the create um in the
last yes last year and this year there's
a series of work from my group right
really just showcase people right uh you
can actually you once you understand
what is done with the principle you can
dramatically simplify you you can even
throw with the MLP layer if you only
care about the compression um you don't
care about the final representation and
or you can make the attention head
since we know what is optimizing it's
optim optimizing the rate reduction
object function
Then we can find what is the equivalent
variation form of that object function
which is much easier to optimize. We end
up with a we call the toss right the the
computing the coariance the the self
tension step is only linear in the
dimension no longer quadratic like the
current tension is doing. Of course if
you look at the literature there are
other people have found tried to
identify linear complexity such as uh
you know manga or uh I think there's the
rk or something so empirically but again
it's through trial and error but this is
so now we derive this in the ma purely
mathematical way because we just find an
equivalent varial form of the same
object function they have the same
global optimal but it's that's much
easier to optimize. This is a trick we
do all the time, right? All the tricks
see in the 200 years plus years of
developing better optimization
algorithm. All those ideas can help us
now to design better operator descent
operators or optimization architectures
to
improve the design of current
architectures. Pro honestly we have not
really started that far. Right? There's
many acceleration techniques,
preconditioning, conjugate gradient
which explore different landscape. Once
we understand the landscape, the type
the cost of object function better
there's gazillions of ideas, we can
further improve the efficiency.
Honestly,
we haven't started that far, right? Um I
mean that's actually what got some of my
student uh excited uh to to pursue this
realizing how much how little we have
done. um uh from optimization
perspective how much room there might
still be for improvement uh some of my
students are quite excited. So you can
see you know Neman within last couple
years we already have two two or three
different uh uh uh uh generation of
architectures that um in the past it's
almost unthinkable because new
generation always come from different
group right it's like a random process
whoever gets lucky maybe discover
something works try hard enough get
something to work
>> it's a tantalizing idea though that
through this principled optimization
there could be you know a convergent
evolution towards the optimum
architecture
>> then the search will no longer be random
will be actually guided right there's
still just like back to your earlier
suggestion right this is become
intelligent search is you know guided
search we understand the the structure
of the problems now and hence we can do
science now we are no longer just to do
empirical inductive search process
>> why do open AI they're still using the
transformer even though there are now
superior architectures out there and we
should talk about this token statistics
um transformer. So as you just said it's
a linear time complexity which means in
principle this is something which is
going to scale dramatically better than
the kind of transformers we're using
now. So why aren't we using it?
>> Well there are tempted to try to scale
this up. In fact, even you can think
about uh uh many of of course when you
try to scale the other factor comes in
right in terms of whether or not the the
the the the scalability and so on is all
related to to to all the design. Um and
um indeed we actually tried something
else. uh you know uh for example things
are much more scalable also I also tried
to we also scaled up with all the
resource we have sometimes I don't know
about company right we we are very
limited in resource to verify even our
those architecture scales we can only do
up to probably a you know few you know
couple hundred cars and so on that's
about it uh with our academic resources
and hopefully that will convince but one
thing I think recently we did um to
simplify the current practice in dino
Right? You know the meta has to which is
the pre-trained the state-of-the-art uh
people everybody talk about world model
visual world model and uh that's sort of
the best model and the the meta put a
lot of effort engineer effort to
pre-train the visual representation
model uh which is still the best and
they train on gazillions of images and
they were using contrastive learning but
it's a it's a very uh remarkable
engineering uh feed and now people using
it right um turns thought actually we
found that uh the system can be
dramatically simplified once we realize
what the purpose what they're really
trying to do right we have a work called
a syn deno simplified the deno version
one version two we simplify both version
there the architecture is dramatically
so we get rid of you know dozens of
hyperparameters I have to do and
architecture become you know extremely
extremely 10 times simpler and the
performance is better we managed to
scale up to uh probably few few hundred
millions of scales the appletoapple
comparison were dramatically much easier
to train much efficient everything is
explainable I think that has seriously
draw attention uh from the meta team and
also from the Google team and it's
currently they are there I I know there
are serious effort that they're trying
to scale this the new architectures up
>> yes um we interviewed the dino folks at
the time and we've spoken to people like
Ishan Misra there's there I mean there's
a potential tangent there about they're
using this kind of um uh non-contrastive
um self-supervised learning and also
there's the whole unsupervised thing and
and how useful those representations are
for downstream task. May maybe we could
go there but I should say that Kevin
Murphy I'm I'm interviewing interviewing
him soon and um I know that he reviewed
your your book very very carefully and
he asked me to give you this question.
He said code reduction is great but must
be subject to prediction or
reconstruction loss in data space. How
would you go beyond token prediction
which seems especially weird for images?
So that that's what Kevin asked me to
ask you.
>> So this is actually a great question,
right? Um so in a in a rate reduction
remember the the lossiness is actually
coded through the the EPS ball where
actually uh uh try to capture the uh the
the samples how they connect with one
another. Um right now we actually if we
just minimizing the coding
representation uh through this uh lossy
coding and the error is kind of
controlled by the IPS law but not
enforced right so we respect the IPS law
um through this loss coding process now
to truly ensure remember everything
could go wrong and also depends on the
number of samples you have maybe the
image you choose is wrong because the
data does not have that density so you
may not be able to percolate. Hence the
repetition learn can be very very funky.
So now in order to to to ensure that
your your your your learn the reputation
distribution learn internally actually
authentically reflect the original
distribution up to certain precision you
have to decode right there is a constant
encoding decoding actually our brain do
that all the time predictive coding and
so on so forth
and hence that encoding decoding and to
verify if there's error remain in your
prediction in your recon construction
matters a lot only in that now the
question is if we don't have the oh do I
do we necessary back to our earlier
discussion right do we really need to
measure that error in the data space in
the original token space uh if we have
that option so be it do that right make
the engineering simpler make the but if
we really want to have a system just
like a human to selfarn just go out to
observe right at with two eyes or with
some sensors. Then we have to come up
with a way to make sure that our sensing
process is accurate enough so that we
can do everything internally. We can
predict go back rapid back and observe
compare what we predicted and what we
observed through same
sensing
channel. We compare that locally. In
theory actually prove at least under
ideistic cases this is possible. We can
minimize the error once we correct the
error. Hence the internal representation
will the error in a token original data
space will diminish but under tech
condition under general condition we
still don't know. So we actually have a
paper prove that for the when your data
distribution is a mixture of subspaces
you can rigorously prove that's possible
and if the dimension of the subspace is
low enough compared to the capacity of
the perception process.
Now for general distribution we believe
this is true. This is actually how we'll
be able to learn all the low dimensional
dynamics structure in the natural data
in the motion in the in the predicted um
world. So I think this is something in
the future we can deduct but end to end
works if you have the option to do so or
if you have you don't have that option
you have to figure out how to do this
autonomous under what condition you can
do this autonomously and allows you to
do autonomously to reduce the error to
almost zero. We spoke about Dino, but
another example would be VIT. Um, we
interviewed Lucas Bayer in Switzerland
earlier this year. So, he invented VIT.
And if I understand correctly, crate is
now very very close to VIT, but it it's
so much more principled. It's
explainable and so on. How close are we
to knocking VIT off the off the
leaderboard if you like?
>> In fact, u I think in many of the
comparison, we're already very close. If
you compare, it's hard to compare apple
to apple, but in terms of if you similar
the parameters, we're very much on par.
And also, by the way, we never really
quite put much engineer effort into it.
We just want to verify the concept. Um
indeed there one thing come out of the
vi the crit is that uh what we find is
not only the architecture designs
principled but then once we did the
training right the internal structure
learned
are both semantically statistically and
geometrically very meaningful indeed
each head actually does learns uh you
know similar structures all gets
basically each channel each head be
truly become expert of certain certain
type of visual patterns for example legs
of animals ears of animals faces of
animals so we see that very clearly with
crates but we don't observe that in the
vit of course you can see vit may learn
this is actually the the the interesting
thing right early days people I'm sure
large models if they have redundancy
they definitely learn things internally
but it's very hard to say which part of
that network learn the correct channels
learn the correct operators because it
is embedded in a more some redundant
structure, right? So early days people
call this lottery uh you know lucky
lottery or lock lottery ticket right
it's somewhere in there right then then
people try to distill that that justify
you should distill you should actually
be able to compress even people do this
Laura thing you know all the
post-processing right justify that is
necessary and some people you find after
the post processing not only the network
become smaller the performance gets
better right but and so on so forth Now
probably we don't have to do that. At
least you know the the architecture does
what it's supposed what it's designed to
do right and we can actually at least
explain what each component is doing
something statistically geometrically
very meaningful and there also results
if there's enough data if your
optimization
uh is done training is successful that's
those structure pops up naturally the
the structure will do what they're
designed to do. And and final question,
many um ML engineers and researchers
watch the show. Given everything we've
spoken about, how can they find out more
about your work and how can they get
started building these kind of
architectures? Um I think most of our
actor are open sourced on GitHub um
including create uh uh early reduet uh
there may not be is conceptual but not
very practical uh create and also even
toss all the all the codes are available
but by the way they're sort of kind of
academic implement we don't we never be
able to have the resource to scale them
up most are scale up to GPT2 or image at
21 that that's we can afford deno Simply
den is the one we scale the most. We we
res exhaust a lot of resource and a
little bit higher than that but still no
comparison to all this industrial scale
at all but I do believe that the meta
and Google are doing something about
dino simplified dino and the codes are
there um and also of course if for the
methodology of course um this is one way
why we bite the bullet uh uh to uh wrote
the book in the past two years we
believe that although there's a series
of papers uh but we believe that for
people to get a big picture, the more
systematic introduction. We put together
the the books also we open sourced it um
and we we will post link all the data
all the code as well. We are also
teaching the course. So all the we
actually will have students uh practice
most of the new architectures method. So
all those codes will be made public
available and so I think that might be a
good entrance if you want people want to
learn the methodology understand the
theoretical chain of evidence and also
even the empirical chain of evidence and
I think the book is has attempt to do
that we are already start to organizing
we're not done yet but we are start
already organizing if you find of
chapter seven we're already doing that
uh in chapter seven to collect the
theory seriously to to all the real
world data and the task such as image
classification, image segmentation and
the pre-training and even language uh
GPT2 type scale language models and so
on. Yeah,
>> professor Mo, it's been an absolute
honor. Thank you so much for joining us
today.
>> Yeah, thank you very much.