Formula 1 cars are the absolute pinnacle
of engineering, right? Everything is
perfect, huge top speed. If you used it
as your daily commuting car, you'd have
an absolute nightmare, right? And I
think the same can be said for these
models, right? A model that is
incredibly good on humanity's last exam
or MMLU might be absolute nightmare to
use day-to-day. Most reporting on
benchmarks is done on technical
benchmarks these days, right? Um that is
where you get the model uh you you give
it a set of evaluations uh maybe on one
theme or maybe on an exam and then you
get a score and humans aren't really
involved in that loop. Hey, my name is
Andrew Gordon. Uh I'm a staff researcher
in behavioral science at Prolific. So I
work on the sciences team uh tackling
questions related to humans in research
specifically online research.
>> My name is Nora Petrova. I'm an AI
researcher at Prolific. I'm tackling
questions around how do we include
humans development of AI models and
evaluation of AI models? How do we align
them to human values? And how do we
fully understand what they're capable
of?
>> How helpful do people find models?
What's the communication like? How
adaptive do they find it? What do they
think of the model's personality? And
that when you get ratings on those kind
of factors, what you actually get is an
actionable set of results that say,
okay, your model is struggling with
trust or your model is struggling with
personality. And we had a first go at
this with what's called the prolific
user experience leaderboard. Uh that was
kind of proof of concept with 500
participants from the US uh a
representative set of participants where
they evaluated a single model at a time
and gave their feedback in a like scale
format. You know how helpful did you
find the model 1 to 7 and so on. We've
actually moved now and taken the
learnings from that initial leaderboard
and and built it into what we're calling
humane which is our main leaderboard. Um
and that uses a much a similar approach
to chat arena in the sense that we have
comparative battles between um between
models uh which actually allows us to
much more clearly differentiate which
model is performing better. What if we
could have a a fairer approach where we
actually diversely sampled and
stratified folks based on how old they
are and where they live and what their
values are. What would be a fairer
approach to understand the behavior of
models and to do evaluation? So this is
what Andrew and Nora have been doing at
prolific. How do we know whether these
models are actually good for the humans
that are using them? How can we make
evaluation metrics which are fairer?
This is Andrew and Nora.
>> But the problem is at the moment I mean
the the field of kind of evaluations and
benchmarking these models is incredibly
nent, right? It's only been around as
long as LLMs have been around in the
last couple of years. And because of
that it's a kind of like a fractured
field, right? There's no there's no
standard playing field for how these
labs uh report um data on on on
benchmarking. You know, some may
emphasize with Grock 4 recently, we saw
huge amount of emphasis on humanity's
last last exam, right? And and less so
on other benchmarks and some models will
come out without any benchmarking data
at all. Right? um and without some kind
of essentially there's a lot of
heterogeneity in how these labs report
the results and what it what it leads to
for me is a situation where I think
we're at risk of struggling to actually
compare the models on any even playing
field but there's of course bigger
questions as well about you know models
are often lorded for doing the highest
score in humanities last exam so we know
from a technical perspective the model
has advanced above its rivals but for me
and I guess my kind of core or argument
in this space is if you just rely on
those technical metrics, you miss half
the point, right? Like these models are
designed for humans to use at the end of
the day. Most of the users are humans
and simple performance on these exams
doesn't necessarily correlate to a good
user experience. All the frontier labs
really uh need to start kind of having
uh human preference leaderboards a
little more front of mind alongside all
the technical metrics. People are
increasingly using these models for very
sensitive topics and questions for
mental health for uh how should they
should navigate problems in their lives
and there is no oversight on that and in
any other area where these topics are
discussed there is a lot of regulation
and then a lot of kind of ethical
conduct built into it. Whereas here is
kind of the wild west at the moment and
some companies are taking it more
seriously than others and trying to
study the ways in which humans are uh
using the models for for more personal
topics and and problems and we've seen
some pretty starking examples recently
with with Gro 3 and Mecca Hetler and uh
it does raise questions about how how
thin of a veneer is the safety training
on top of some of these models.
>> Well, there is no leaderboard for
safety, right? like there's no metric
like we we don't grade LLMs by how safe
they are. In fact, it's not really even
in the question apart from some
researchers. So, I mean I I would argue
that that should be just as important as
how fast or smart the model is. You
know, how safe is it for the people to
use? There's been a lot of interesting
research coming from anthropic in that
direction with regards to safety with
regards to alignments of the models and
using constitutional AI and various
approaches that they've um that they've
explored and also around mechanistic
interpretability just peering kind of
behind the curtains of the models and
understanding how an input produces a
certain output which kind of features
concepts which circuits get activated
along the way and kind of tracing
the thoughts essentially of these models
and trying to isolate where potential
problems may emerge. So work of this
kind is very important and raising the
confidence that these models will be
able to handle novel situations in safe
ways. I think the the one other thing
I'd say is um given that chatbot Arena
is the number one and frankly pretty
much the only human preference
leaderboard out there for for LLMs, it's
really important that we actually
understand what's going on behind the
scenes. So obviously, you know, Chat
Bolerina is entirely open source. People
go in, they put in a prompt, they get
response from two different models. They
then say which one is better. And that
paper found that actually what was
happening in the background is that some
companies are getting access to a lot
more private testing uh in the
background than others. For instance,
before Llama 4 launched, we saw Meta
released 27 models on the arena. But of
course, only one was actually reported
in the end, which obviously undermines
the integrity of the arena because the
more comparisons you have for your
model, the more access to prompts you
have, the more data you have to refine a
better model that's better at the arena.
and it adds an element of bias into into
the data which is very very hard to get
around. There are other issues that were
called out and issues that we've seen
ourselves which we think kind of
dictates the need for a more rigorous
and and methodologically sound approach
to doing these kind of human preference
data sets amongst us. I think we had a
pretty good idea um beyond beyond the
criticisms in the leaderboard illusion
paper. We think that it actually that
paper didn't really touch on some of the
other things we we think should be cared
about when you're doing human preference
evaluation. I think for me there's kind
of three big areas I think where where
we've sought to improve. First of all,
as you mentioned sample. So obviously
the sample for uh the chatbot arena is
anybody right. We don't know anything
about them. We don't collect any
demographic data. Uh so they are just
people going there anonymously prompting
the models and giving their preference
data. Now obviously that's great. You
get a huge amount of data which is
fantastic but you know nothing about the
people giving the data which is fairly
suboptimal. Um then in terms of
specificity any for anybody that's used
chat arena all you're doing is saying I
like this response more or I like this
response more right in the real world
that kind of data is is useless in a
sense right it it gives you a really
nice way to make a nice leaderboard of
AI models but it tells the companies
nothing about why that preference um has
been has been uh given. So in in our
approach we sought to um mitigate that
by actually splitting preference down
into its constituent parts. So things
like how helpful do people find models?
What's the communication like? How
adaptive do they find it? What do they
think of the model's personality? And
that when you get ratings on those kind
of factors, what you actually get is an
actionable set of results that say,
okay, your model is struggling with
trust or your model is struggling with
personality. That's where you need to be
focusing to really actually build a
model that is good for real users in the
real world. But there's no QA in the
sense that okay, I could go in and I
could just say hello or I could say
absolutely nothing or I could have a
multi-turn conversation and completely
wander from you know how big is the sun
to how long is a snake you know like
just uh topic wandering which I don't
think is a really good nuance view of
models. So we've built in to our
structure where participants come in and
they have multi-step uh conversations
with models. we built in QA that
actually says, you know, if if you put
low low effort into your question or you
start wondering, we're going to penalize
you and three three of those and you're
out. So, those are the kind of
principles I guess we built the
leaderboard around.
>> I would just touch upon uh the
methodology that we've used, which is
true skill. It's um a framework uh if
you will developed by Microsoft for
estimating the skill levels of players
on Xbox Live. So they take into account
things like randomness in games, um, um,
changing skill levels across time,
whether someone is having kind of a
fluky win streak versus a seasoned
player that consistently performs well.
So all of these things that we thought
would be good to take into account. And
uh it's a very flexible system that
estimates probabilities with basing
distributions with kind of a mean and a
variance that gets narrow and narrow
over time as the system kind of learns
about the outcome of these battles or
these comparisons. Most importantly,
it's based on information gain. So the
way the way we pick the next pair that
should occur in the tournament is based
on how much we will learn from these
models going head-to-head. How much are
how much information are they giving us?
how much are they reducing the
uncertainty and we kind of order the
queue of pairs according to that and
that gets us to a place of minimized
uncertainty as fast as possible as fast
as we can. It's a really flexible
approach. Uh we can run separate
tournaments like we've done with our
demographic groups. We have around 20
demographic groups and we've run
separate tournaments for them and we can
consolidate the findings for each
tournament to obtain kind of a an
overall leaderboards that is much less
uncertain than any of the individual
tournaments or leaderboards that we can
um produce from any of the demographic
groups. So it it really allows us to
slice and dice data in any way we want
and we can easily add more demographic
groups, more models over time. uh we're
yeah developing in in in the open and
welcoming feedback.
>> I think one of the things they pointed
out in the leaderboards illusion paper
was that actually some models are
sampled considerably higher than other
models and the I I believe that the the
folks behind chatbot arena said that's
because people come to the arena to play
with the latest models, right? Which is
all well and good. People want to play
with with the state-of-the-art, right?
Which is great, but it doesn't lead to
an efficient sampling method. It it
essentially means that some models get a
lot more battles than others. They
therefore get a lot more data. They
therefore get a lot better in the arena.
And there's a pretty strong relationship
between the number of battles and the
place on the leadboard. We only ever do
battles based on the need from the data.
So the uncertainty is high for a
specific model against another specific
model. We conduct a battle for that to
lower that uncertainty. So it's all
driven by the data. It's very
computationally sound because we don't
actually make any more comparisons than
we need to. Um, and it allows us to
really get to a point where models are
strongly differentiated based on
uncertainty.
>> If we have a certain goal with regards
to uncertainty, in order to fully
differentiate the models at the
confidence interval that we're
interested in, we can just conduct more
battles until we get there. The control
is in our hands. Uh, in essence, we just
need to recruit more participants in
order to get to that level of certainty.
The way we've sampled for this study,
we're obviously using uh our own
participants from the prolific platform,
but we've sampled effectively in based
on the census data that we have for both
the US and the UK. So, the long-term
vision of this would obviously be a more
global product, but at the moment, what
we do is we we stratify our our sample
i.e. our participants who are giving us
this feedback by demographics like their
uh their age, their ethnicity, their
political alignment. And we have an
awful lot of data from from censuses
that tells us, you know, each country is
made up of this certain proportion of
these demographics, which essentially
allows us to say that when we've
amalgamated all these findings and we
find that leading model, we can very
confidently say that that model is
preferred by as representative a set of
the general public as we can possibly
get. So hopefully in that sense it's a
lot more related to like the the real
world preferences of people in the world
rather than a very potentially skewed
and biased subset that might be uh
responding to the chatbot arena because
we we ran our first one as an MVP a
proof of concept that was a lot more
about kind of um proving that we can do
this in a rigorous and methodologically
sound way. Uh when we actually ran that
we only ran it with 500 participants. It
gave us a lot of insights about how we
build humane which is our leaderboard
that we're working on at the moment. Now
that leaderboard is actually running as
we speak in the background. We're still
having battles. So we expect to be able
to have more uh data from that. But what
I can say about the the first uh the
first round that we did models tended to
perform across the board of the six
models we tested which were leading
models at the time they performed a lot
worse on personality metrics and
background and culture metrics as
opposed to things like helpfulness,
communication, adaptiveness. What that
really signals is that there's there's
some some uh I guess more subjective
aspect of these models which people are
less impressed by potentially just they
were doing tasks that don't elicit a
personality in the model or they don't
elicit the model talking about
background and culture. Also the model
doesn't know their background and
culture so it's very hard to align with
them. But the other uh possibility is
that potentially models are just not
very good at that. And that would be uh
potentially an effect of the data
they've been trained on. Right? Because
we know very little. I mean obviously
models are trained on the entire
internet. But
it when you train a model on the entire
internet, do you get a personality that
really represents what people want?
Right? And and from this testing, we
found that generally people were less
impressed with model personality or its
ability to have an understanding of
their background or culture than with
more kind of I guess objective measures.
>> And obviously a lot of um these models
have undergone extensive fine-tuning to
tailor their personalities or tailor how
they approach answering questions that
are different across the different
companies. But uh we've observed
recently that there has been an increase
in psychop fancy or this kind of
peopleleasing behavior of models and
people generally don't seem to like it.
One thing that this the results of this
experiments or and the later data set
will allow us to answer is what is a
correlation between telltale signs of
psychopansy and a down votes in the
personality metric that um uh does that
uh influence people's decisions on which
model they prefer? uh we can um perform
various types of post-processing and
analysis of the data to identify the
levels of psychopancy that's observed in
the data sets and to try to identify
interesting relationships between the
feedback that people gave kind of uh
more uh model driven kind of LLM as a
judge uh oriented uh analysis of of the
conversations and kind of classification
of various patterns and and and what the
models exhibit. So, it's quite quite
interesting to see what we'll find.