You know that 1.4 trillion you
mentioned, we'll spend it over a very
long period of time. I wish we could do
it faster. I think it would be great to
just lay it out for everyone once and
for all how those numbers are going to
work. Exponential growth is usually very
hard for people. OpenAI CEO Sam Alman
joins us to talk about OpenAI's plan to
win as the AI race tightens, how the
infrastructure math makes sense, and
when an OpenAI IPO might be coming. And
Sam is with us here in studio today.
Sam, welcome to the show.
>> Thanks for having me. So, OpenAI is 10
years old and crazy to me.
>> Chachi PT is three, but the competition
is intensifying. Um, this place we're at
OpenAI headquarters was in a code red is
in a code red. Um, after Gemini 3 came
out and everywhere you look, there are
companies that are trying to take a
little bit of OpenAI's advantage. And
for the first time I can remember, it
doesn't seem like this company has a
clear lead. So I'm curious to hear your
perspective on how open AI will emerge
from this moment and when first of all
on the code red point we view those as
like relatively low stakes somewhat
frequent things to do. Uh I think that
it's good to be paranoid and act quickly
when a potential competitive threat
emerges. This has happened to us in the
past that happened earlier this year
with Deepseek. Um and
>> there was a code red back then too.
>> Yeah. There there's there's a saying
about pandemics which is something like
when when a pandemic starts
every bit of action you take at the
beginning is worth much more than action
you take later and most people don't do
enough early on and then panic later and
certainly saw that during the covid
pandemic. Um
but I sort of think of that philosophy
as how we respond to competitive
threats. Uh and you know it's I think
it's good to be a little paranoid.
Gemini 3 has not or at least has not so
far had the impact we were worried it
might but it did in the same way the
Deepse seek did identify some weaknesses
in our product offering strategy and
we're addressing those very quickly. I
don't think we'll be in this code red
that much longer. Uh you know like these
are not these are historically these
have been kind of like six or eight week
things for us. Um
but I'm glad we're doing it. Uh just
today we launched uh a new image model
which is a great thing and that's
something consumers really wanted. Um,
last week we launched 5.2 which uh is
going over extremely well and growing
very quickly. Uh, we'll have a few other
things to uh launch and then we'll also
have some continuous improvements like
speeding up the service. But, you know,
I think this is like my guess is we'll
be doing these once maybe twice a year
for a long time and that's uh part of
really just making sure that we win in
our space. Um, a lot of other companies
will do great too and I'm happy for
them. But, you know, CatchBT is still uh
by far by far the dominant uh
chatbot in the market and I expect that
lead to increase not decrease over time.
Um,
the the models will get good everywhere,
but a lot of the reasons that people use
a product, consumer or enterprise, uh,
have much more to do than just with the
model. And we've, you know, been
expecting this for a while. So we try to
build the whole cohesive set of things
that it takes to make sure that we are
you know the product that people most
want to use. Um I think competition is
good. It pushes us to be better. Uh but
I think we'll do great in chat. I think
we'll do great in enterprise and in the
future years. Other new categories I
expect we'll do great there too. I I
think people really want to use one AI
platform. People use their phone at
their personal life and they want to use
the same kind of phone at work most of
the time. We're seeing the same thing
with AI. Uh the strength of chatgbt
consumer is really helping us win the
enterprise. Uh of course enterprises
need different offerings but people
think about okay I know this company
open and I know how to use this chat GPT
interface. Um so the strategy is make
the best models build the best product
around it and have enough infrastructure
to serve it at scale.
>> Yeah there is an incumbent advantage. uh
chat I think earlier this year was
around 400 million weekly active users.
Now it's at 800 million reports say
approaching 900 million. Um but then on
the other side you have distribution
advantages at places like Google. And so
I'm curious to hear your perspective if
the models do you think the models are
going to commoditize? And if they do
what matters most? Is it distribution?
Is it how well you build your
applications? Is it something else that
I'm not thinking of? I don't think
commoditization is quite the right
framework to think about the models.
There will be areas where different
models excel at different things. For
the kind of normal use cases of chatting
with a model, maybe there will be a lot
of great options. For scientific
discovery, you will want the thing
that's right at the edge that is
optimized for science perhaps. Um so
models will have different strengths and
the most economic value I think will be
created by models at the frontier and we
plan to be ahead there. Um and we're
like very proud that 52 is the best
reasoning model in the world and the one
that scientists are having the most
progress with but also um we're very
proud that it's what enterprises are
saying is the best at all the tasks that
a business needs to to you know do its
work. Um
so there will be you know times that
we're ahead in some areas and behind in
others but the overall most intelligent
model I expect to have uh significant
value even in a world where free models
can do a lot of the stuff that people
that people need. The the products will
really matter. Distribution and brand as
you said will really matter. Um in
chatbt for example personalization is
extremely sticky. People love the fact
that the model, get to know them over
time, and you'll see us push on that uh
much much more. Um,
people have experiences with these
models that they then really kind of
associate with it. Uh, and you I
remember someone telling me once like
you kind of pick a toothpaste once in
your life and buy it forever or most
people do that apparently. Um and people
talk about it. They have one magical
experience with ChachiPT.
Healthcare is like a famous example
where people put their um you know they
put a blood test into Chachi or put the
symptoms in and they figure out they
have something and they go to a doctor
and they get cured of something they
couldn't figure out before. Like those
users are very sticky. Uh to say nothing
of the personalization on on top of it.
Um
there will be all the product stuff. uh
we just launched our browser uh recently
and I think that's pointing at a new uh
you know pretty good potential mode for
us. Uh the devices are further off but
I'm very excited to to do that. So I
think there'll be all these pieces and
on the enterprise uh what creates the
the mode or the competitive advantage um
I expect that to be a little bit
different but in the same way that
personalization to a user is very
important in consumer there will be a
similar concept of personalization to an
enterprise where a company will have a
relationship with a company like ours uh
and they will connect their data to that
and you'll be able to use a bunch of
agents from different companies running
that and it'll kind of like make sure
that information is handled the right
way and I expect that'll be pretty
sticky too. Um we already have more than
uh a million people think of us largely
as a consumer company but we have
>> we're going to definitely get into
enterprise.
>> Yeah. You know like
>> share the stat.
>> Well actually
>> a million
>> we have more than a million enterprise
users but we have like just absolutely
rapid adoption of the API. Um and like
the API business grew faster for us this
year than even Chad GPT
>> really. Um so the enterprise stuff is
also
you know it's really happening starting
this year. Can I just go back to this
maybe if commoditization is not the
right word model some maybe parody for
everyday users
>> uh because you you started off your
answer saying okay maybe um everyday use
it will feel the same but at the
frontier it's going to feel really
different. Um when it comes to chat
GPT's ability to grow um if I'll just
use Google as an example. If Chat GPT uh
and Gemini are built on a model that
feels similar for everyday uses, how big
of a threat is the fact that you know
Google has all these surfaces through
which it can push out Gemini whereas
Chat GPT is is fighting for every new
user.
>> I I think Google is still a huge threat
uh you know extremely powerful company.
If Google had really decided to take us
seriously
in 200
23, let's say, we would have been in a
really bad place. I think they would
have just been able to smash us. Um, but
their AI effort at the time was kind of
going in not quite the right direction
productwise. They didn't, you know, they
had their own code red at one point, but
they didn't take it that seriously.
Everyone's doing code reds out here.
>> Um, and then
>> and also Google has probably the
greatest business model in the whole
tech industry.
Um, and I think they will be slow to
give that up. Um, but bolting AI into
web search, I don't I may be wrong.
Maybe like drinking the Kool-Aid here. I
don't think that'll work as well as
reimagining the whole, this is actually
a broader trend I think is interesting.
Bolting AI onto the existing way of
doing things, I don't think is going to
work well as redesigning stuff in the
sort of like AI first world. was part of
why we wanted to do the consumer devices
in the first place, but it applies at
many other levels. Um, if you stick AI
into a messaging app that's doing a nice
job summarizing your messages and
drafting responses for you, that is
definitely a little better. But I don't
think that's the end state. That is not
the idea of you have this like really
smart AI that is like acting as your
agent, talking to everybody else's agent
and figuring out when to bother you,
when not to bother you, and how to, you
know, what decisions it can handle and
when it needs to ask you. So
similar things for search, similar
things for like productivity suites. I
suspect
it always takes longer than you think,
but I suspect we will see new
products in in the major categories that
are just totally built around AI rather
than bolting AI in. And I think this is
a weakness of Google's even though they
have this huge distribution advantage.
>> Yeah, I' I've spoken with so many people
about this question. uh when Chetchup PT
came out initially, I think it was
Bendic Devon that suggested you might
not want to put AI in Excel. You might
want to just reimagine how you use
Excel. And to me, in my mind, that was
like you upload your numbers and then
you talk to your numbers. Well, one of
the things people have found as they've
developed this stuff is there needs to
be some sort of backend there.
>> So, is it that you sort of build the
backend and then you interact with it
with AI as if it's a new software
program?
Yeah, that's kind of what's happening.
>> Why wouldn't you then be able to just
bolt it on on top?
>> Yeah, I mean, you can bolt it on on top,
but the
>> I spent a lot of my day in various
messaging apps,
including email, including text, Slack,
whatever. I think that's just the wrong
interface. So, you can bolt AI on top of
those, and again, it's like a little bit
better, but what I would rather do is
just sort of like have the ability to
say in the morning, here are the things
I want to get done today. Here's what
I'm worried about. Here's what I'm
thinking about. Here's what I'd like to
happen. I do not want to be I do not
want to spend all day messaging people.
I do not want you to summarize them. I
do not want you to show me a bunch of
drafts. Deal with everything you can.
You know me. You know these people. You
know what I want to get done. Um and
then you know like batch every couple of
hours updates to me if you need
something. But that's a very different
flow than the way these apps work right
now.
>> Yeah. And I was going to ask you what
ChachiBT is going to look like in the
next year and then the next two years.
Is that kind of where it's going?
>> To be perfectly honest, I expected by
this point Chachi BT would have looked
more different than it did at launch.
>> What did you anticipate? I didn't know.
I just thought like that chat interface
was not going to go as far as it turned
out to go. H like we I mean it was put
up
it looks better now, but it is broadly
similar to when it was put up as like a
research preview. was not even meant to
be a product. We knew that the text
interface was very good, you know, like
the everyone's used to texting their
friends and they like it. Um, the chat
interface was very good, but
I would have thought to be as big and as
significantly used for real work of a
product as what we have now, the
interface would have had to go
much further than it has now. I still
think it should do that but there is
something about the generality of the
current interface that I underestimated
the power of. Um
what I
think should happen of course is that um
AI should be able to generate different
kinds of interfaces for different kinds
of tasks. So if you are talking about
your numbers it should be able to show
you that in different ways and you
should be able to interact with it in
different ways. Um
it and we have a little bit of this with
features like canvas. It should be way
more interactive. It's like right now,
you know, it's kind of a back and forth
conversation. It'd be nice if you could
just be talking about an object and it
could be continuously updating. You have
more questions, more thoughts, more
information comes in. Um, it'd be nice
to be more proactive over time where it
maybe does understand what you want to
get done that day and it's continuously
working for you in the background and
send you updates. And you see part of
this the way people are using codecs
which I think is one of the most
exciting
things that happened this year is codecs
got really good. Uh and that points to
a lot of what I hope the shape of the
future looks like. Um
but
it is surprising to me. I was going to
say embarrassing but it's not. I mean
clearly it's been super successful. Uh
it is surprising me how little CHBT has
changed over the last three years.
>> Yep. It the interface works.
>> Yeah.
>> But I guess what the guts have changed
and you talked a little bit about how
personalization is big uh to me and I
think this has been one of your
preferred features too. Memory has been
a real difference maker. Um, I've been
having a conversation with ChachiPT
about a forthcoming trip that has lots
of planning elements for weeks now and I
can just come in in a new window and be
like, "All right, let's pick up on this
trip." And it it has the context and it
knows knows the guide I'm going with. It
knows what I'm doing. Uh, the fact that
I've been like planning fitness for it
and can really synthesize all of those
things. How good can memory get? I think
we have no conception because the human
limit like even if you have the world's
best
personal assistant
they don't they can't remember every
word you've ever said in your life. They
can't have read every email. They can't
have read every document you've ever
written. They can't be you know looking
at all your work every day and
remembering every little detail. They
can't be a participant in your life to
that degree. And no human has like
infinite perfect memory.
Um,
and AI is definitely going to be able to
do that. And we actually talk a lot
about this, like right now, memory is
still very crude, very early. We're in
like the, you know, the GBT2 era of
memory.
But what it's going to be like when
it really does remember every detail of
your entire life and personalized across
all of that and not just the facts, but
like the little small preferences that
you had that you maybe like didn't even
think to indicate, but the AI can pick
up on. Uh,
I think that's going to be super
powerful. That's one of the features
that still maybe not 2026 thing, but
that's one of the parts of this I'm most
excited for.
>> Yeah. I was speaking with a
neuroscientist on the show and he
mentioned that you don't you can't find
thoughts in the brain. Like the brain
doesn't have a place to store thoughts,
but computing there's a place to store
them. So, you can keep all of them. And
as these bots do keep our thoughts, um,
of course there's a privacy concern. And
but the other thing is something that's
going to be interesting is we'll really
build relationships with them. I think
it's been one of the more underrated
things about this entire moment is that
people have felt that these bots are
their companions, are looking out for
them. Um, and I'm curious to hear your
perspective. Um, when you think about
the level of I don't know if intimacy is
the right word, but companionship people
have with these bots, um, is there a
dial that you can turn to be like, oh,
let's make sure people become really
close with these things, or, you know,
we turn the dial a little bit further
and there's an arms distance uh, between
them and and if there is that dial,
>> how do you modulate that the right way?
There are definitely more people
than I realize that want to have, let's
call it close companionship. You I don't
know what the right word is like.
Relationship doesn't feel quite right.
Companionship doesn't feel quite right.
I I don't know what to call it, but they
want to have whatever this deep
connection with an AI. There there are
more people that want that at the
current level of model capability than I
thought. And there's like a whole bunch
of reasons why I think we underestimated
this, but at the beginning of this year,
it was considered a very strange thing
to say you wanted that. Maybe some a lot
of people still don't revealed
preference.
You know, people like their AI chatbot
to get to know them and be warm to them
and be supportive and there's value
there even for people who in some cases
even for people who say they they don't
care about that uh still have a
preference for it. I
I think there's some version of this
which can be super healthy and I think
you know adult users should get a lot of
choice in where on the spectrum they
want to be. There are definitely
versions of it that seem to me unhealthy
although I'm sure a lot of people will
choose to do that. Um and then there's
some people who definitely want the
driest most effect efficient tool
uh possible. So I suspect like lots of
other technologies,
we will run the experiment. We will find
that there's unknown unknowns, good and
bad about it. And society will over time
figure out
how to how to think about where people
should set that dial and then people
have huge choice and set it in very
different places.
>> So your your thought is allow people
basically to determine this.
>> Yes, definitely. But I I don't think we
know like how far it's supposed to go,
like how far we should allow it to go.
We're we're going to give people quite a
bit of personal freedom here. Um there
are examples of things that uh we've
talked about that,
you know, other services will offer, but
we we won't. Um like we're not going to
let we're not going to have RAI, you
know, try to convince people that should
be like in an exclusive romantic
relationship with them, for example.
got to keep it open.
>> But I'm sure that will No, I'm sure that
that will happen with other services, I
guess. Yeah, because the stickier it is,
the more money that service makes. The
whole all these possibilities kind of
they're a little bit scary when you
think about them a little bit deeply.
>> Totally. This is one that really does
that I personally, you know, you can see
the ways that this goes really wrong.
>> Yeah. Uh, you mentioned Enterprise.
Let's talk about Enterprise. you were at
a lunch with some editors and CEOs of
some news companies in New York last
week and told them that enterprise is
going to be a major priority uh for
OpenAI next year.
>> U I'd love to hear a little bit more
about um why that's a priority, how you
think you stack up against anthropic. I
know people will say this is a pivot for
OpenAI that has been consumer focused.
So just give us an overview about the
enterprise plan. Our strategy was always
consumer first. Uh there were a few
reasons for that. One, the models were
not robust and skilled enough uh for
most enterprise uses and now now they're
they're getting there. The second was we
had this like clear opportunity to win
in consumer and those are rare and hard
to come by and I think if you win in
consumer it makes it massively easier to
win in enterprise and we are we are
seeing that now. Um but as I mentioned
earlier this was a year where we
enterprise growth outpaced consumer
growth. Uh and given where the models
are today where they will get to next
year we think this is the time where we
can
build a really significant enterprise
business quite rapidly. I mean I think
and we already have one but it can it
can grow much more. Um
companies seem ready for it. The
technology seems ready for it. the, you
know, coding is the biggest example so
far, but there are others that are now
growing, other verticals that are now
growing very quickly. And we're starting
to hear enterprises say, you know, I
really just want an AI platform.
>> Which vertical company?
>> Um, finance science is the one I'm most
excited about of everything happening
right now. Personally, um, customer
support is doing great. Uh
but but yeah the the
we have this thing called GDP though.
>> I was going to ask you about that. Can I
actually throw my question out about
that? All right. Cuz I wrote to Aaron
Levy the CEO of Box and I said I'm going
to meet with Sam. What should I ask him?
He goes throw a question out about GDP
val. Right. So this is the measure of
how AI performs in knowledge work tasks.
And I said okay. I went back to the
release of GPT 5.2 to the model that uh
you recently released and looked at the
GDP valid chart. Now this of course is
an open AI evaluation. Um that being
said the uh GPT5 thinking model so this
is the model released in the in the
summer. It ti it tied uh knowledge
workers at 38% of test or tied beat or
tied
>> um GP so 38.8% GPT 5.2 2 thinking beat
or tied at 70.9%
of knowledge work tasks and GPT 5.2 pro
74.1%
of knowledge work tasks and it passed
the threshold of um being expert level
it it handled it looks like something
like 60% of expert tasks uh of tasks
that would make it you know on par with
an expert in the knowledge work. What
are the implications of the fact that
these models can do that much knowledge
work? So, you know, you were asking
about verticals, and I think that's a
great question, but the thing that was
going through my mind and why I kind of
was stumbling a little bit is that Eval,
I think it's like 40 something different
verticals that a business has to do.
>> There's make a PowerPoint, do this legal
analysis, you know, write up this little
web app, all this stuff.
>> And and the eval is do experts prefer
the output of the model relative to
other experts
for a lot of the things that a business
has to do. Now, these are small, well
scopeed tasks. These don't get the kind
of complicated, open-ended, creative
work that, you know, figuring out a new
product. These don't get a lot of
collaborative team things. But
a co-orker that you can assign an hour's
worth of tasks to and get something you
like better back 74 or 70% of time if
you want to pay less is still pretty
extraordinary. If you went back to the
launch of Chat TBT 3 years ago and said
we were going to have that in 3 years,
most people would say absolutely not.
Um, and so as we think about how
enterprises are going to integrate this,
it's no longer like just that it can do
code. It's all of these knowledge work
tasks you can kind of farm out to the
AI. uh and
that's going to take a while to really
kind of figure out how enterprises
integrate with it but should be quite
substantial. I know you're not an
economist, so I'm not going to ask you
like what is the macro impact on jobs,
but let me just read you one uh line
that I heard uh you know in in terms of
how this impacts jobs uh from Blood in
the Machine on Substack. Um this is from
a technical copywriter. They said,
"Chatbots came in and made it so my job
was managing the bots instead of a team
of reps." Okay, that that to me seems
like it's going to happen often. But
then this person continued and said once
the bots were sufficiently trained up to
offer good enough support then I was
out. Um is that is that the is that
going to become more common? Is that
what bad companies are going to do?
Because if you have a human who's going
to be able to sort of orchestrate a
bunch of different bots then you might
want to keep them. I don't know. How do
you think about this? So I I agree with
you that it's clear to see how
everyone's going to be managing like a
lot of AI uh doing different stuff. Um
eventually like any good manager
hopefully your team gets better and
better but you just take on more scope
and more responsibility. I am not I am
not a jobs dumer.
Um short term I have some worry. I think
the transition is likely to be rough uh
in some cases but
we are so deeply wired to care about
other people what other people do. We
are so we seem to be so focused on
relative status and always wanting more
and to be of use and service to express
creative spirit whatever whatever
whatever has driven us this long. I
don't think that's going away. Now I do
think the jobs of the future or I don't
even know if jobs is the right word.
Whatever we're all going to do all day
in 2050 probably looks very different
than it does today. Um
but I but I I don't have any of this
like oh life is going to be without
meaning and the economy is going to
totally break. Like we will find I hope
much more meaning and the economy I
think will significantly change but I I
think you just don't bet against
evolutionary biology. Um
you know I think a lot about how we can
automate all the functions at OpenAI and
then even more than that I think about
like what it means to have an AI CEO of
Open AI. Doesn't bother me. I'm like
thrilled for it. I won't fight it. Uh
like I don't want to be I don't want to
be the person hanging on being like I
can do this better the the handmade way.
>> AI CEO just make a bunch of decisions to
sort of like direct all of our resources
to giving AI more energy and power. It's
like
>> um I mean no you would really put a
guard rail on
>> Yeah. Like obviously you don't want an
AI CEO that is not governed by humans,
but if you think about
if if you think about maybe like
a this is a crazy analogy, but I'll give
it anyway. If you think about a version
where like every person in the world was
effectively on the board of directors of
an AI company and got to, you know, tell
the AI CEO what to do and fire them if
they weren't doing a good job at that
and, you know, got governance on the
decisions, but the AI CEO got to try to
like execute the wishes of the board.
Um,
I think to people of the future that
might seem like quite a reasonable
thing. Okay, so we're going to uh move
to infrastructure in a minute, but
before we leave this section on models
and capabilities, when's GP GPT6 coming?
Um, I expect I don't know when we'll
call a model GPT
6. Uh,
but I would expect new models that are
significant gains from 5.2 in the first
quarter of next year.
>> What does significant gains mean?
I don't have like an eval score in mind
for you yet but uh more enterprise side
of things or definitely both the there
will be a lot of improvements to the
model for consumers uh the main thing
consumers want right now is not more IQ
enterprises still do want more IQ so uh
we'll improve the model in different
ways for the kind of for different uses
but uh I our goal is a model that
everybody likes much better
>> so infrastructure you have 1.4 trillion
thereabouts and commitments uh to build
infrastructure. I've listened to a lot
of what you've said about
infrastructure. Um here are some of the
things you said. If people knew what we
could do with compute, they would want
way way more. You said the gap between
what we could offer today versus 10x
compute and 100x compute is substantial.
Uh what what can you help flesh that out
a little bit? What are you going to do
with uh so much more compute?
Well, I mentioned this earlier a little
bit. The thing I'm personally more
excited, most excited about is to use AI
and lots of compute to discover new
science. I am a believer that scientific
discovery is the high order bit of how
the world gets better for everybody. And
if we can throw huge amounts of compute
at scientific problems and discover new
knowledge, which the tiniest bit is
starting to happen now, it's very early.
These are very small things but you know
my learning in history of this field is
once the squiggles start and it lifts
off the x-axis a little bit we know how
to make that better and better. Um but
that takes huge amounts of compute to
do. So that's one area we're like
throwing lots of AI at discovering new
science curing disease lots of other
things. Um,
a kind of recent cool example here is we
built the Sora Android app using codecs
and
they did it in like less than a month.
They used a huge amount. One of the nice
things about working at OpenAI is you
don't get any limits on codecs. They
used a huge amount of tokens, but they
were able to do what would normally have
taken a lot of people much longer and
Codex kind of mostly did it for us. And
you can imagine that going much further
where entire companies can build their
products using lots of compute.
Um
people have talked a lot about how video
models are going to point towards these
generated real-time generated user user
interfaces. That will take a lot of
compute. Um
enterprises that want to transform their
business will use a lot of compute. uh
doctors that want to offer good
personalized health care that are like
constantly
measuring every sign they can get from
each individual patient. You can imagine
that using a lot of compute. Uh it it's
hard to frame how much
compute we're already
using to generate AI output in the
world. Um but these are horribly rough
numbers. So, uh, and I think it's like
undisiplined to talk this way, but I I
always find these like mental thought
experiments a little bit useful, so
forgive me for the sloppiness. Um, let's
say
that an AI company today might be
generating something on the order of 10
trillion tokens a day out of Frontier
models. Um,
you know, more, but not it's not like a
a quadrillion tokens for anybody, I
don't think. Um
let's say there's 8 billion people in
the world and let's say on average
someone's these are I think totally
wrong but let's say someone the average
number of tokens outputed by a person
per day is like
uh 20,000.
You can then start to and the token you
can to be fair then we have to compare
the output tokens of a model provider
today not not all the tokens consumed
but you can start to look at this and
you can say hm we're going to have these
models at a company be outputting more
tokens per day than all of humanity put
together and then 10 times that and then
100 times that. And you know, in some
sense it's like a really silly
comparison,
but in some sense it gives a magnitude
for like how much of the intellectual
crunching on the planet is like human
brains versus AI brains. And that's kind
of the relative growth rates there are
are interesting. And so I'm wondering
are do you know that there is this
demand to use this compute like
potentially like so for instance would
we have surefires like scientific
breakthroughs if you know open AAI were
to put double the compute towards
science or or with medicine like are
would we have you know that clear
ability to assist doctors like
>> how much of this is sort of uh
supposition of what's to happen versus
clear understanding based off of what
you see today IC
>> everything everything based off what we
see today is that it will happen. It
does not mean some crazy thing can't
happen in the future. Someone could
discover some completely new
architecture and there could be a 10,000
times you know efficiency gain and then
we would have really probably overbuilt
for a while. But everything we see right
now about how quickly the models are
getting better at each new level, how
much more people want to use them, each
time we can bring the cost down, how
much more people really want to use
them. Um,
everything about that indicates
to me that there will be increasing
demand and people using these for
wonderful things, for silly things. Um,
but
it it just so seems like
this is the shape of the future. Um
it's not just like it's not just you
know how many tokens we can do per day.
It's how fast we can do them as these
coding models have gotten better. They
can think for a really long time but you
don't want to wait for a really long
time. So there will be other dimensions.
It will not just be the number of tokens
that that we can do. Um but the demand
for intelligence across a small number
of axes
and what we can do with those you know
if you're like if you have like a really
difficult healthcare problem do you want
to use 5.2 or do you want to use 5.2 pro
even if it takes dramatically more
tokens I'll go with the better model. I
think you will um can let's just try to
go one level deeper. Um
going to the scientific discovery, can
you give an example of like a scientist
it doesn't have to well maybe it's one
that you know today that's like I have
problem X and if I put you know compute
Y towards it I will solve it but I'm not
able to today. There was a thing this
morning on Twitter where a bunch of
mathematicians were saying they were all
like replying to each other's tweets. Uh
they're like I was really skeptical that
LM's were ever going to be good. 5.2 is
the one that crossed the boundary for
me. it did it you know figured out this
it with some help it did this small
proof it it discovered this small thing
but it's this is actually changing my
workflow and then people were piling on
saying yeah me too I mean some people
were saying 5.1 was already there not
many
>> um but
that that was like that's a very recent
example this model's only been out for 5
days or something where people are like
all right you know the mathematic
>> the mathematics research community seems
to say like okay something important
just happened
>> I've seen Greg Brockman has been
highlighting getting all these different
mathematical scientific uses in his feed
and something has clicked I think with
5.2 um among these communities. So it'll
be interesting to see what happens as as
things progress.
>> We don't
like one of the hard parts about compute
>> at this scale is you have to do it so
far in advance. So you know that 1.4
trillion you mentioned we'll spend it
over a very long period of time. I wish
we could do it faster. I think there
would be demand if we could do it
faster. Um, but
it just takes an enormously long time to
build these projects and the energy to
run the data centers and the chips and
the systems and the networking and
everything else. Um, so that will be
over a while, but you know, we
from a year ago to now, we probably
about tripled our compute. We'll triple
our compute again next year, hopefully
again after that. um revenue grows even
a little bit faster than that but it
does roughly track our compute
fleet. Uh so we
we have never yet found a situation
where we can't really well monetize all
the compute we have. Um if we had I
think if we had you know double the
compute we'd be at double the revenue
right now.
>> Okay let's let's talk about numbers
since you brought it up. Um revenue is
growing. uh compute spend is growing but
compute spend still outpaces revenue
growth. Uh I think the numbers that have
been reported are OpenAI is supposed to
lose something like 120 billion between
now and 120 and 2028 29 where you're
going to become profitable. Um so talk a
little bit about like how does that
change? Where does the turn happen? I
mean, as revenue grows and as inference
becomes a larger and larger part of the
fleet, it eventually uh subsumes the
training expense. So, that's the plan.
Spend a lot of money training but make
more and more. Uh if we if we weren't
continuing to grow our training
costs by so much, uh we would be
profitable way way earlier. Um but the
bet we're making is to invest very
aggressively in training these big
models. The whole world is wondering um
how your revenue will line up with the
spend. Uh the question's been asked if
the trajectory is to hit 20 billion in
revenue this year and the the spend
commitment is 1.4 trillion. Um so I
think it would be great just over a very
long period.
>> Yeah. Over and that's why I wanted to
bring it up to you. I think it would be
great to just lay it out for everyone
once and for all how those numbers are
going to work. It's it's very hard to
like really I I I find that one thing I
certainly can't do it and very few
people I've ever met can do it. You
know, you can like you have good
intuition for a lot of mathematical
things in your head, but exponential
growth is usually very hard for people
to do a good quick mental framework on
like for whatever reason there were a
lot of things that evolution needed us
to be able to do well with math in our
heads. Modeling exponential growth
doesn't seem to be one of them. Um so
the thing we believe is that we can stay
on
a very steep
growth curve of revenue for quite a
while and everything we see right now
continues to indicate that we cannot do
it if we don't have the compute. uh
again we're so compute constrained uh
and it hits the revenue line so hard
that I think if we get to a point where
we have like a lot of compute sitting
around that we can't monetize on a you
know profitable per unit of compute
basis be very reasonable to say okay
this is like a little how's this all
going to work but
we've penciled this out a bunch of ways
uh we will of course also get more
efficient uh on like a flops per dollar
basis as you know all of the work we've
been doing to make comput cheaper comes
to pass. Um, but
we see this consumer growth, we see this
enterprise growth. There's a whole bunch
of new kinds of businesses that
have we haven't even launched yet but
will. Um, but compute is really the
lifeblood that enables all of this. So
we, you know, there's like checkpoints
along the way and if we're a little bit
wrong about our timing or math, we can
we have some flexibility, but
we have always been in a comput deficit.
It has always constrained what we're
able to do. Uh I unfortunately think
that will always be the case, but I wish
it were less the case and I'd like to
get it to be less of the case over time.
Uh because I think there's so many great
products and services that we can
deliver and it'll be a great business.
Okay. So, it's effectively training
costs go down
>> as a percentage go up overall. But yeah,
>> and then your expectation is through
things like this this enterprise push
through things like people being willing
uh to pay for chat GPT through the API,
OpenAI will be able to grow revenue
enough to pay for it with revenue.
>> Yeah, that is the plan.
>> Now, I think the thing so the market's
been kind of losing its mind over this
um recently. I think the thing that has
spooked the market has been the debt has
entered uh into this equation. And the
idea around debt is you take debt out
when there's something that's
predictable. Um and then companies will
take the debt out, they'll build and
they'll have predictable revenue.
>> But it's it's the this is a new
category. It's it is unpredictable. Um
is is that how do you think about the
fact that that debt has entered the
picture here? So, first of all, I think
the market more lost its mind when
earlier this year, you know, we would
like meet with some company and that
company's stock would go up 20% or 15%
the next day. That was crazy.
>> That felt really unhealthy. Um, I'm
actually happy that there's like a
little bit more skepticism and
rationality in the market now cuz uh it
felt to me like we were just totally
heading towards a very unstable bubble
and now I think people are some degree
of discipline. So I actually think
things are I think people went crazy
earlier and now people are being more
rational on the debt front. I I think we
do kind of we know that if we build
infrastructure we the industry someone's
going to get value out of it. And it's
still it's still totally early. I agree
with you. But I don't think anyone's
still questioning there's not going to
be value from like AI infrastructure.
And so I think it is reasonable for debt
to
enter this market. I think there will
also be other kinds of financial
instruments. I suspect we'll see some
unreasonable ones as people really you
know innovate about how to finance this
sort of stuff. But you know like lending
companies money to build data centers
that that seems fine to me. I think the
the fear is that um if things don't
continue at pace like here's one
scenario um and you'll probably disagree
with this but like the model progress
saturates uh then the the infrastructure
becomes worth less than the anticipated
value was and then yes those data
centers will be worth something to
someone but it could be that they get
liquidated and someone buys them at a
discount. Yeah. And and I do suspect by
the way there will be some like booms
and busts along the way. These things
are never a perfectly smooth line. Um,
first of all, it seems very clear to me,
and this is like a thing I happily would
bet the company on, that the models are
going to get much much better. We have
like a pretty good window into this.
We're very confident about that. Even if
they did not, I think the
there's like a lot of inertia in the
world. It takes a while to figure out
how to adapt to things. The overhang of
the economic value that I believe 5.2 2
represents relative to what the world
has figured out how to get out of it so
far is so huge that even if you froze
the model at 5.2 to how much more like
value can you create and thus revenue
can you drive? I bet a huge amount. In
fact, you didn't ask this, but if I can
go on a rant for a second. Um,
we used to talk a lot about this 2x2
matrix of short timelines,
long timelines, slow takeoff, fast
takeoff, and where we felt at different
times the kind of probability was
shifting, and that that was going to be
you could kind of understand a lot of
the decisions and strategy that the
world should optimize for based off of
where you were going to be on that 2x
two matrix. Um,
there's like a Z-axis in my head in my
picture of this that's emerged, which is
small overhang, big overhang. And
I I kind of thought that
I guess I didn't think about that hard,
but uh like my retro on this is I must
have assumed that the overhang was not
going to be that massive that if the
models had a lot of value in them, the
world was pretty quickly going to figure
out how to deploy that. But it looks to
me now like the overhang is going to be
massive in most of the world. You'll
have these like areas like you know some
some set of coders that'll get massively
more productive by adopting these tools.
But on the whole
you have this crazy smart model that to
be perfectly honest most people are
still asking this similar questions they
did in the GPD4 realm. Scientists
different coders different maybe
knowledge work is going to get different
but but there is a huge overhang and
that has a bunch of very strange
consequences for the world. I we have
not wrapped our head around all the ways
that's going to play out yet, but is
very much not what I would have expected
a few years ago. I have a question for
you about this uh capability overhang.
Basically, the models can do a lot more
than they've been doing. Um I I'm trying
to figure out how um the models can be
that much better than they're being used
for, but a lot of businesses when they
try to implement them, they're not
getting a return on their investment.
>> Um or at least that's what they tell
MIT. I'm not sure quite how to think
about that because we hear all these
businesses saying, you know, if you 10x
the price of GPT 5.2, we would still pay
for it. Like you're hugely underpricing
this, we're getting all this value out
of it.
>> Um,
so I don't that doesn't seem right to
me. Certainly, if you talk about like
what coders say, they're like, "This is,
you know, I'd pay 100 times the price or
whatever." Um,
>> just be bureaucracy that's messing
things up. Let's say you believe the GDP
valve numbers and maybe you don't for
good reason maybe they're wrong but let
let's say it were true and for kind of
these wellsp specified not super long
duration knowledge work tasks seven out
of 10 times you would be as happy or
happier with the 5.2 output.
You should then be using that a lot. And
yet it takes people so long to change
their workflow. are so used to asking
the junior analyst to make a deck or
whatever that they're going to like it
just that's stickier than I thought it
was. You know, I still kind of run my
workflow in very much the same way.
Although I know that I could be using AI
much more than I am. Yep. All right, we
got 10 minutes left. I got Wow, that was
quick. I got four questions. Uh let's
see if we can lightning round uh through
them. So, uh, the device that you're
working on. We'll be back with OpenAI
CEO Sam Alman right after this. Um, what
I've heard, phone size, no screen. Um,
why couldn't it be an app if it's the
phone if it's the phone without a
screen? First, we're going to do a f a
small family of devices. It will not be
a single device. uh there will be over
time a
this is this is not speculation so I'm
may try not to be totally wrong but I
think there will be a shift over time to
the way people use computers where they
go from a sort of
dumb reactive thing to a very smart
proactive thing that is understanding
your whole life your context everything
going on around you very aware of
the people around you physically or
close to you via a computer that you're
working with. And I don't think current
devices are well suited
to that kind of world. And I am a big
believer that we like we work at the
limit of our devices. you know, you have
that computer and it has a bunch of
design choices. Like it could be open or
closed, but it can't be, you know,
there's not like a okay, pay attention
to this interview, but be closed and
like whisper in my ear if I forget to
ask Sam a question or whatever. Um,
>> maybe that would be helpful. And there's
like, you know, there's like
a screen and that like limits you to the
kind of same way we've had graphical
user interfaces working for many
decades. And there's,
you know, a keyboard that was built to
like slow down how fast you could get
information into it. And these have just
been unquestioned assumptions for a long
time, but they worked. And then this
totally new thing came along and it
opens up a possibility space. But
I don't think the current form factor of
devices is the optimal fit. It'd be very
odd if it were for this like incredible
new affordance we have. Oh man, we could
talk for an hour about this, but um
let's move on to the next one. Cloud.
You've talked about building a cloud. Um
here's a an email we got from a
listener. At my company, we're moving
off Azure and directly integrating with
OpenAI to power our AI experiences in
the product. The focus is to insert a
stream of trillions of tokens powering
AI experiences through the stack. Is is
that the plan to build a big big cloud
business in that in that way?
>> First of all, trillions of tokens, a lot
of tokens. And if you know you asked
about the need for compute and our
enterprise strategy like
>> enterprises have been clear with us
about how many tokens they'd like to buy
from us and we are going to again fail
in 2026 to meet demand but the strategy
is companies
most companies seem to want to come to a
company like us and say I'd like the
name of my company with AI. I need an
API customized for my company. I need
Chach Enterprise customized for my
company. I need a platform that can like
run all these agents that I can trust my
data on. I need the ability to get
trillions of tokens into my product. I
need the ability to have all my internal
processes be more efficient and
we don't currently have like a great
all-in-one offering for them and we'd
like to make that.
>> Is your ambition to put it up there with
the AWS and Ashers of the world?
>> Uh I think it's I think it's a different
kind of thing than those. like I don't I
don't really have an ambition to go
offer whatever all the services you have
to offer to host a website or I don't
even know but uh but I I I think the
concept
yeah my my guess is that people will
continue to have their
call it web cloud and then I think there
will be this other thing where like a
company will be like I need an AI
platform for everything that I want to
do internally the service I want to
offer whatever
and you know like it does kind of live
on the physical hardware in some sense
but
I think it'll be a fairly different
product offering. Uh let's talk about
discovery quickly. Um you've said
something that's been really interesting
to me uh you that you think that the
models or maybe it's people working with
models or the models will make small
discoveries next year and big ones
within five. Is that the models? Is it
people working alongside them? And what
makes you confident that that's going to
happen? Yeah, people using the models
like the the models that can like figure
out their own questions to ask that does
feel further off. But if the world is
benefiting from new knowledge like we
should be very thrilled and you know
like I think the the whole course of
human progress has been that we build
these better tools and then people use
them to do more things and then out of
that process they build more tools and
it's this like scaffolding that we climb
like layer by layer, generation by
generation, discovery by discovery and
the fact that a human's asking the
question I think in no way diminishes
the value of the tool. All right. So, I
I think it's great. I'm all happy. Um
I at the beginning of this year, I
thought the small discoveries were going
to start in 2026. They started in 2025
in late 2025. Again, these are very
small. I really don't want to overstate
them, but
anything
is feels qualitatively to me very
different than nothing. And certainly in
the when we launched three years ago,
that model was not going to make any new
contribution to the total of human
knowledge. um
what it looks like from here to five
years from now. This journey to big
discoveries, I suspect it's just like
like the normal hill climb of AI. It
just gets like a little bit better every
quarter and then all of a sudden we're
like, whoa, humans augmented by these
models are doing things that humans 5
years ago just absolutely couldn't do.
And
you know, whether we mostly attribute
that to smarter humans or smarter
models, as long as we get the scientific
discoveries, I'm very happy either way.
IPO next year. I don't know. Do you want
to be a public company?
>> Um, you seem like you can operate
private for a long time. Would you go
before you needed to
terms of funding?
>> There's like a whole bunch of things at
play here. I do think it's cool that
public markets get to participate in
value creation and you know in some
sense we will be very late to go public
if you look at any previous company. Um
it's wonderful to be a private company.
Uh we need lots of capital. Uh
we're going to you know cross all of the
sort of shareholder limits and stuff at
some point. So,
am I excited
to be a public company CEO? 0%. Um, am I
excited for Open Eye to be a public
company? In some ways, I am. And in some
ways, I think it'll be really annoying.
I listened to your Theo van interview
very closely. Uh, great interview.
>> He was really cool.
>> Theo really knows what he's talking.
He's
>> He did his homework. You told him, this
was right before GPT5 came out, that
GPT5 is smarter than us in almost every
way. Uh, I I thought that that was the
definition of AGI. Does is that isn't
that AGI? And and if not, has the term
become somewhat meaningless? These
models are clearly extremely smart on a
sort of raw horsepower basis. You know,
there's all this stuff on the last
couple of days about GPT 5.2 who has an
IQ of 147 or 144 or 151 or whatever it
is. It's like, you know, depending on
whose test it's like it's some high
number and you have like a lot of
experts in their field saying
it can do these amazing things and it's
like contributing it's making it more
effective. You have the GDP things we
talked about. One thing you don't have
is
the ability for the model to not be able
to do something today, realize it can't
go off and figure out how to learn to
get good at that thing, learn to
understand it, and when you come back
the next day, it gets it right. And that
kind of continuous learning like
toddlers can do it. It does seem to me
like an important part of what we need
to build. Now, can you have something
that most people would consider an AGI
without that? I would say clear. I mean,
there's a lot of people that would say
we're at AGI with our current models.
Um,
I think almost everyone would agree that
if we were at the current level of
intelligence and had that other thing,
it would clearly be very AGI like. Um,
but maybe most of the world will say,
"Okay, fine. Even without that, like
it's doing most knowledge tasks that
matter. um smarter than us in mo most of
us in most ways. We're at AGI. You know,
it's discovering small piece of new
science. We're at AGI. What I think this
means is that the term although it's
been very hard for all of us to stop
using is very underdefined, right?
I I have a I have a a can like one thing
I would love
since we got wrong with AGI. We never
define that that you know the new term
everyone's focused about is when we get
to super intelligence. Um so my proposal
is that we agree that you know AGI kind
of went whooshing by. It was didn't
change the world that much or it will in
the long term but okay fine we've built
AGIs at some point you know we're in
this like fuzzy period where some people
think we have and some people think we
have and more people will think we have
and and then we'll say okay what's next?
Um, a candidate definition for super
intelligence is when a system can do a
better job being president of United
States, CEO of a major company, you
know, running a very large scientific
lab than any person can even with the
assistance of AI.
>> Okay,
>> I think this was an interesting thing
about what happened with chess where
chess got it could be humans. I remember
this very vividly. uh that deep blue
thing and then there was a period of
time where
a human and the AI together were better
than an AI by itself and then the person
was just making it worse and the
smartest thing was the unaded AI that
didn't have the human like
not understanding its its great
intelligence. Um
I think something like that is like an
interesting framework for super
intelligence. I think it's like a long
way off, but I would love to have like a
cleaner definition this time around.
>> Well, Sam, look, I I have uh been in
your products uh using them daily for 3
years. Um
>> definitely gotten a lot better. Can't
even imagine where they go from here.
>> We'll we'll try to keep getting them
better fast.
>> Okay. And uh this is our second time
speaking and I appreciate how open
you've been uh both times. So, thank you
for your time.
>> Thank you everybody for listening and
watching. If you're here for the first
time, please hit follow or subscribe. We
have lots of great interviews on the
feed and more on the way. This past
year, we've had Google DeepMind CEO
Demisabus on twice, including one with
Google founder Sergey Brin. We've also
had Dario Ammoday, the CEO of Anthropic.
And we have plenty of big interviews
coming up in 2026. Thanks again, and
we'll see you next time on Big
Technology Podcast.