In 1988 89 there were all kinds of
demonstrations in the Eastern block the
Soviet Union. In the Soviet Union
they're for political freedoms in the
Eastern block there for freedom from the
Soviet Union. And very
uncharacteristically the Russians didn't
send tanks. In fact Gorbachev welcomed
and encouraged reforms in the Eastern
block both political and economic just
as he was doing in the Soviet Union.
This is about the 40th anniversary of
the founding of East Germany and 70,000
people demonstrate at leipig and
November 8th the poll bureau resigns and
then on the 9th whatever is left of that
government is issuing new travel
regulations and you might wonder what's
travel got to do with it in response to
a question at a news conference this guy
Gre Shabovski who was one of the
remaining communists helping run the
show he gets asked a question doesn't
know the answer and so he wings it and
The question is, when do these travel
regulations go into effect? And he goes,
immediately. Well, crowds immediately
started gathering at the six gates to
the Berlin wall. And at one of them, the
border guards decided that discretion
was the better part of valor, and they
opened the gate. And East Germans poured
into West Berlin.