There was a period when Putin was still
winning somewhat free elections. And
then so if you look at why Russia's
economy recovers and why Putin is so
popular from 2000 to 2008, oil goes from
$10 a barrel to $140 a barrel. And this
goes to your point about we give credit
or blame political leaders for often
what are just long run macro trends.
>> Well, what I didn't cover is when the
Soviet Union collapses, the Russian
living standards implode and it's a mess
for 20 years. It is just unbelievably
difficult. Oh, and another piece of the
brilliant Soviet management. In order to
maintain control over the empire,
instead of building things all in a
place, you build some plane parts here,
some plane parts there, some plane parts
all over the empire. So when the empire
goes, great, I've got a quarter of a
plane and then you know where do I get
the other parts? So when Putin suddenly
has a lot of money and then he starts
spending it on people because initially
there's plenty of money. Russian
standard of living do go up and so of
course they like him and they give it
give him credit for all of that but then
that runs its course right it's his
mindset anyway when you get more money
you want to get the empire back
>> and then Russians also like That.