Around this time is when people are
finally learning about what actually
happened during the Stalinist period.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Um so people are optimistic that well we
can sort of have a changing of the guard
and maybe things will improve but at the
same time they're learning about how
terrible their history actually was. Oh,
I think there was a an understanding it
was uh terrible, but I think there's
this exuberance of thinking it's going
to get much better. And then the
disappointment is equally extreme. And
then there was this feeling that well
the west owes us because how I mean
you're all really rich and you now owe
us to fix everything. And the
counterargument to that is no, you are
enormous migraine. You set back all of
these countries across the globe back in
time with this nonfunctioning communist
model that you pedal around there and
now you want extra aid. The problem was
I think we wanted to do some of the aid
but they're not going to be receptive to
it. I think that was another conclusion
with the Bush administration is that if
we dumped a lot of money in it would
just go straight into corruption. You
need a legal structure and in order to
place money and they just plain didn't
have it. There's nowhere to put the
money. Living.