the symbol of the disco era uh Studio 54
was not particularly about politics. Uh
and there is this famous uh story that
you didn't get in. Recently I had a
podcast with Barry Dilla the Hollywood
mogul I know
>> who had a very similar experience. She
also wanted to go to 54, didn't get in.
And she described it in a way as a
motivator for for him to to get I don't
know, not only to get in, but to get
even better and show it to the rest of
the world. So your story uh led to uh
Lefrey, the most famous cheek.
>> Can you share that story with us?
>> Yeah. So it was um so we had uh the very
first song that I wrote, Everybody
Dance, was really the hip underground
chic record. Yes. Dance, dance, dance ya
was on the radio getting a lot of play.
Like you said, they played dance dance
the floor. Dance floor gets packed. But
but what everybody dance was the the
symbol of chic coolness. That bass
playing that Bernard laid on that was
just unbelievable. And that song was
actually well known in the underground
for about a year before we got a record
deal. So, Grace Jones had heard
Everybody Dance, and that was like
really an important song to her, and she
called us and asked us to uh come and
see her um because she was thinking
about having us be her then record
producers, you know, like in it would
be, you know, 1977
or something like that. Um Yeah. And
we couldn't believe it because we we had
never done anything with a star even
though all of our singles were hitting.
Every every single we put out bang bang
bang everything was in the top five
every song. So uh by that time we had
already had two chic singles that were
big. We had our first lead singer, Norma
Jean. Her record uh called Saturday was
big and we had done Sister Sledge. So we
had He's the Greatest Dancer and Now We
Are Family. And um even though we
recorded that album, at the same time we
recorded Chic's second album, uh we had
decided to give the song He's the
Greatest Dancer to Sister Sledge, which
we wrote for ourselves.
But when we went to Studio 54 that
particular night, now this is the true
story. That wasn't the first time we'd
ever tried to go to Studio 54. My
girlfriend
>> Did you get in before?
>> Oh, yeah. Many times. But I always had
to be with my girlfriend. She used to
work at a store called Fioruchi. And so
all the people in Fuchi were totally
cool and every you know, they all looked
stylish and fashionable. So when I was
with my girlfriend, I could get in. But
that's
>> Fiori.
>> Pardon me.
>> Exactly. Gucci Fiori.
>> You know that that's the very first time
anybody ever name checked fashion
designers on a record. And now I mean we
created a formula which we didn't even
realize that we were creating. Uh now
you can't buy a pop record without them
namechecking something. Um because it
sort of describes the person's
lifestyle. you know, you say you roll,
you were Lamborghini rolling or
whatever. So anyway, what happened was
that night we were really going to do
business. So the other times that I had
been to Studio 54 with my girlfriend, I
was going there to party and the
business that I was doing was just
taking what they played at Studio 54
compared to what they played at the
underground clubs. So now we were going
to do business. So we dressed like
gentlemen, so to speak, and we did what
Grace Jones had told us. So she cold
called us cuz we didn't really have any
managers. It was just chic organization.
And somehow she was able to use her
connections to find us. She called us
and she spoke in a way that seemed a
little odd to us. She says, "So darling,
I want you to come to the back door and
tell them that your personal friends are
misgr."
And to us, it sounded like a cross
between Bella Losce, Marlene Dietrich,
and Bob Marley. We didn't know, we
didn't know that that actually was her
speaking voice cuz, but we knew the
record's tired to get down on you. You
know, she had that kind of nasal thing
going on. you know, roll up to the
bumper, baby, with your long back limo,
you know, so we thought Grace Jones
would be speaking like that, but instead
she had this sort of continental accent
and it was odd. And we thought that
that's what we were supposed to do, that
we were supposed to imitate that very um
very
sort of distinguish sounding thing. And
you know we were she so we go to the
back door and we go hello we are
personal friends of m Jones the guy
looks at us and he slams the door in our
faces and but but when he was doing it
anyway he goes oh [ __ ] off we no no no
we kicking the door saying no this is
the truth we cuz this was New Year's Eve
right 1977 going into 78 like Studio 54
was the hottest place on the planet
everybody was trying to get into Studio
54 on New Year's Eve. So, we kicked the
door a lot because we had to be louder
than the music inside and to get this
guy's attention. And he came back and he
said, "Didn't I tell you to [ __ ] off?"
Well, Studio 54 was one block away from
my apartment at that time. Um, so we
walked to my apartment, but before we
got to our my apartment, uh, which is
where our instruments were, and you know
where Bernard and I would write all the
songs cuz we had recording studio that
we worked at right on the ground floor,
but I lived on the top floor. Um, we had
to pass a liquor store. We bought two
bottles of of Don Peron champagne, what
we used to call rock and roll mouthwash.
And we we down them like one swig
because we were pretty pretty upset
because we had our shoes. I was wearing
suede shoes that cost a fortune that
were now ruined because it was snowing
and they put you know they put salt out
and the snow the salt had
had penetrated my suede shoes. So, so
this night we couldn't think of anything
except for [ __ ] off. Oh, [ __ ] off. So,
we went to my apartment. I picked up my
guitar and started playing a little
riff. Um,
now if you notice that most chic songs,
um, and this is before the time, this is
before like the current market where
where music sort of, um, like in our
current world now, music is basically
loops, two bar loops, sometimes four bar
loops. And for some strange reason
reason, my compositions were these sort
of loop based compositions. Like it's
not that we were loops, but we were
actually playing. And so the choruses
and the verses are harmonically pretty
much the same. I'll just sometimes do a
different inversion or we'll dynamically
change it, but it's pretty much the same
thing. It's just a a revoicing of the
chorus, so to speak. So, we went back to
the apartment and I started playing a
[ __ ] off.
Don't [ __ ] studio 54. [ __ ] off.
[ __ ] off. and Bernard started going
and we singing and we wrote a whole song
where the uh we did verses and middle
and the whole bit and we wrote a song
where the most appropriate response
would be [ __ ] off. So we would say like
if a cab driver cuts you off, [ __ ] off
if your mom asks you to do homework,
[ __ ] off. It was great and we were
laughing. We were totally entertained.
And Bernard said, "Uh, my man, cuz he we
always wore dark glasses." Said, "My
man, you know this [ __ ] is happening." I
was like, "Bernard, this is like two
years before hip-hop. We like we're not
going to get [ __ ] off on the radio." But
I was I grew up as a hippie. Like my
parents would beat Nicks. I was a
hippie. Um, so I said to him and like my
whole demeanor changed. I went from
being like the cool club kid in the nice
suit to like, oh man, like you know, you
know, when you drop acid, man, cuz now
you were saying, "Oh, [ __ ] off." And we
knew a good euphemism for [ __ ] in
America is free. Oh, you freaking nuts.
You freaking maniac. Oh, freak. Get the
freak out of here. Um, so I said, "Oh,
man. You know, like when you drop acid
and you have a bad trip, uh, it's like
freaking out, man." And Bernard was
like, "He came from a completely
different background." And he looked at
me like I was crazy. And so right away,
I got my black union card back. I said,
"Well, you know, like if you see a fine
girl and you go out on the dance floor
and you just start freaking out," and he
says, "Oh, man." And it's like that new
dance my kids are doing. What new dance
her kids are doing? The Freak. Really?
Oh, wow. There's a dance called The
Freak. Yeah. So, we ran out to the
record store and we got the uh what we
thought would be the uh I guess the
template for a great record about a
dance.
Chubby Checker, the Twist. Like, what's
more iconic than that? like maybe one of
the biggest songs about a specific dance
ever. So we buy that and then we buy
Joey D and the Starlighter song called
The Peppermint Twist and we listen to
the record and Chubby Checker goes,
"Come on baby, let's do the twist. Come
on baby, let's do the twist. Take me by
the middle
bop and go like this."
We're like waiting for him to tell us
how to do the twist and we realize he
doesn't tell us. Joey D and the
Starlighters. Well, we got a new dance
and it goes like this.
Well, the name of this dance is the
peppermint twist.
The peppermint twist. Oh, all right. All
right. They don't say how to do them
peppermint twist. We go, what the hell?
We don't know how to do the freak. So,
we just say, "Have you heard about the
new dance craze list now? I'm sure
you'll be amazed. Big fun to be had by
everyone. It's up to you. Surely can be
done. Young and old are doing this, I'm
told. Just one try and you two will be
sold. It's called the freak. They're
doing it night and day. Allow us. We'll
show you the way." And of course, we
can't show you the way cuz we don't know
how to do it. So, we just go, "Ah, freak
out.
A [ __ ] off. A freak out." Unbelievable
story.
>> Biggest selling record in the history of
Atlante. Now we're talking the record
that has um everybody from Ray Charles,
Artha Franklin to
Cream, the Rolling Stones, biggest
record. Um uh Crosby, Stills and Nash,
um I mean just all these huge
superstars. But the biggest selling
single of all times is a freak out of a
frustration after you didn't get inu to
studio. Wonderful.