I feel like only 30 to 40% of what I've
learned in the last 15 to 20 years of
being in growth transfers here because
we just need to invest in such bigger
bets and innovate and create new growth
loops here. I usually spend maybe 5%
maybe 10% if I'm lucky innovating on
growth in my previous roles. Right now
I'm spending 95% innovating on growth
and only 5% on optimization. Here what I
find is that optimizations are just not
worth our time. And the market is moving
so quickly, you need to stand up a bunch
of initiatives to capture it because
it's perishable. We also have so much
competition. We're not alone here. So,
we can't ignore that. Everybody and
their mother is starting a VIP coding
business nowadays. We need to figure out
how to be ahead of them. And to be ahead
of them is not optimization of the
problem. It's reinvention of the
solution.