One of our biggest strategy is building
in public and it's coupled with employee
socials, founder le socials for sure.
What's really important to us is to
maintain noise in the market and that
noise in the market happens by us
shipping every day, every other day,
multiple times per day and just talking
about it constantly. Interestingly
enough, it's actually works as fantastic
resurrection strategy because people
like, "Oh, there's more things here.
Like, I need to go check it out." It
also works as great re-engagement
strategy. So instead of sending
newsletters to say like here's the
market trends or here's the user stories
like people are like literally logging
into their social to see like okay what
has lovable shipped now.